<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns='http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom' xmlns:g='http://base.google.com/ns/1.0'>
  <title>We Can Solve This</title>
  <updated>2020-11-01T12:11:00Z</updated>
  <author><name>Sandy Maguire</name></author>
  <id>http://sandymaguire.me</id>
  <link rel='self' href='atom.xml'/>

    <entry>
      <title>Month to Mastery: One Wheel Skateboard</title>
      <id>blog/mastery-skateboard/index.html</id>
      <link href='blog/mastery-skateboard/index.html'/>
      <published>2020-11-01T12:11:00Z</published>
      <updated>2020-11-01T12:11:00Z</updated>

      <content type="html">
        <![CDATA[
        <h2 id="the-project">The Project</h2>
<p>Now that Algebra-Driven Design is done, I’ve been looking to branch out of my traditional skill-set. With the exception of a little break at the end of last year, I’ve been programming continuously since 2003, and have gotten pretty good in that space. For the last five years, learning Haskell has been my primary intellectual endeavor, but these days I feel like I’ve learned about as much as it has to teach me. It’s time to tackle something new.</p>
<p>Looking for inspiration, I came across the wonderful <a href="https://medium.com/@maxdeutsch">Max Deutsch</a>, whose <a href="https://medium.com/@maxdeutsch/m2m-day-1-completing-12-ridiculously-hard-challenges-in-12-months-9843700c741f">Month to Master</a> project had him pick up and conquer one ridiculously difficult project per month. These weren’t things like “learn to play Wonderwall,” but were “learn to draw photo-realistic self-portraits” and “build a self-driving car.” At the beginning of each month he’d introduce the project, and then write daily microblogs describing the day’s progress. I love this idea, and have decided I’m going to follow in Max’s footsteps and aggressively tackle my own exciting projects.</p>
<p>Today, November 1, 2020, is the first day of the project. My intention for November is to <em>build a self-balancing, one-wheel skateboard.</em> I used to have a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=XNqOU4jx62I">OneWheel</a>, which was the most fun sport I’ve ever engaged in. When I <a href="/blog/burnout/">ran away from Ottawa</a>, I left it behind, and have regretted it ever since. But these bastards are expensive, and, having fixed it myself a few times, not overwhelmingly complicated.</p>
<p>I have no idea how to build such a thing, but I’m confident I can figure it out in a month. I built some lego robots in university, and once soldered together a clock, but that’s the extent of my hardware knowledge.</p>
<p>My plan is to build a model-scale skateboard, in order to test my engineering prowess, and ensure I have sufficient understanding of the control systems. Doing it with full-sized hardware is a stretch-goal, though the parts are quite expensive, so I’d like some assurance that I’m on the right path before investing in them. If the month ends with only a robust, working scale prototype, I’ll consider it a success if the only hurdle towards productionizing is one of economics.</p>
<p>I’m off to get started. Will report back, editing this post, with my progress each day.</p>
<h3 id="section">2020-11-01</h3>
<p>Today was less productive than I was expecting. I found a tutorial on <a href="https://circuitdigest.com/microcontroller-projects/arduino-based-self-balancing-robot">making a self-balancing robot</a>, and started working on it. I’ve got the electronics prototyped out, but when 3D printing the chassis, my printer started running into extruder problems. (I think) I’ve got that sorted out now, and tried to print the chassis again; this time somehow my bed had gotten out level, making the print extremely stuck to the print bed. When wrestling it off, the PLA snapped. I’m trying again with a re-calibrated, hopefully better-extruding system, but the chassis is a four hour print. If I don’t have a sturdy piece by lunch tomorrow, I’m going to macguyver something together out of cardboard and hot glue.</p>
<h3 id="section-1">2020-11-02</h3>
<p>My recalibrated 3D prints went well; I seem to have solved the brittleness and adhesion problems. But I didn’t realize the pieces needed to be bolted together. Three trips to different hardware stores and two hours later, I hadn’t managed to find the right bolts. I knew I needed 3mm diameter bolts, but they don’t sell them by diameter. Instead they have meaningless designations like #7, #6 and especially confusingly, #6-32. The #6-32s were the smallest I could find, so I picked those up. But they’re actually 4.5mm, which is TOO BIG. Covid has the industrial supply store closed, so if I want to find these pieces locally, it’s going to take a minimum of two days. Instead I bought a big collection of random bolts on Amazon and paid the express delivery fee to have them before end of tomorrow.</p>
<p>I was vaguely aware of this eventuality; that building things in meat-space require parts that I can’t just magic up by downloading a library. I <em>knew</em> this, but I didn’t <em>feel</em> it until now.</p>
<p>Feeling underwhelmed by my progress, I familiarized myself with the PID controller libraries, and how my accelerometer works at a high level. I think I have a good understanding of these thins, and verified it by seeing that the PID equations can be implemented in 6 lines of Haskell. I also confirmed that my Arduino environment and build-chain is working, so that I’m ready to go as soon as tomorrow’s chassis is built. Disappointing day, though.</p>
<h3 id="section-2">2020-11-03</h3>
<p>My partner last night asked “why didn’t you just 3D print some bolts?” Gotta admit, that idea never occurred to me. Apparently I’m not yet used to having a mini factory in my house. So I tried that this morning, but my tolerances aren’t good enough, and the resulting nuts didn’t thread successfully. Thankfully my Amazon delivery happened in the morning, so I set back to building.</p>
<p>My new bolts are the right diameter, but are TOO SHORT for what I need them to do. Fuck. So I just started hot-gluing things, and that worked well enough. A careful hour later (the PLA chassis still feels very brittle), I had everything assembled, hot-glued, rewired, and soldered together. Time to get to balancing.</p>
<p>Some combination of “bad tutorial” and “bad engineer following said tutorial” resulted in me not calibrating the accelerometer while it’s on flat ground, so instead I just tried to balance the robot and run the calibration there. I have no idea how important this step is, but it’s something I’ll do when working on my skateboard proper.</p>
<p>After 30 minutes of tuning parameters, I got the robot balancing somewhat well. I’d accidentally soldered the drive motors backwards, so the first time around it would be actively trying to fall over. Whoops. Thankfully this was easy to fix in software. When everything was turning in the right direction, I found that my wheels stopped spinning when the desired delta got too big. Suspect: too low amperage on my batteries. Something to investigate tomorrow.</p>
<p>Also! I only fastened down the accelerometer with a single bolt (the chassis print apparently didn’t have a plan for mounting any of these things?) This lead to all sorts of instability in my measurements, so I eventually bit the bullet and just hot-glued the fucker. I don’t know if I’ll regret that when I want to reuse the accelerometer, but that’s a problem for future me.</p>
<figure>
<img src="/images/m2m/robot.jpg" alt="" /><figcaption>I built something!</figcaption>
</figure>
<h3 id="section-3">2020-11-04</h3>
<p>Major success! I got the thing balancing!</p>
<video width="558" height="327" controls>
<source src="/images/m2m/balancing.webm" type="video/webm">
</video>
<p>After a bunch of troubleshooting, I realized that my power supply was completely fine. The motors would cut out when asked to spin too fast. Since these are boring DC motors, they operate via PWM — essentially, sending an oscillating square wave whose ratio of high-to-low duration allows you to effectively drive the motor at less than full speed. The problem I thought was the Arduino’s pins; perhaps there was a hardware flaw and they were unable to emit the same signal.</p>
<p>I split out the circuit and ran an LED on the signal (much easier to play with than spinning parts,) and I observed the same behavior there. Because there’s no way that a single LED is overloading my power supply, the issue must be somewhere else. I wrote a quick Arduino program to just modulate the LED at 100%, and, to my surprise, it worked just fine. Which means it’s thankfully not a hardware issue.</p>
<p>Returning to the self-balancing code, I realized the original author had multiplied an expected negative value by <code>-1</code>, rather than calling <code>abs</code>. In his code, it worked fine, but I had originally wired the motors backwards, and had mindlessly swapped the <code>DriveForward</code> and <code>DriveBackwards</code> calls. Works great, except that now the values were negative when the code didn’t expect them to be. So it would negate my values in an attempt to fix them, which resulted in asking the motors to spin at a <em>negative percentage!</em> Thus the weird behavior I was seeing yesterday.</p>
<p>Fixing the logic resulted in the excellent balancing you see in the video above — on my first try! Apparently yesterday’s careful calibration against a completely-broken implementation was more than good enough for a working one.</p>
<p>So, that’s the first step towards my skateboard goal. I’ve managed to put together (and mostly understand) a self-balancing robot. That’s the major hurdle. All that’s left is to change the form-factor into something more amenable to humans. Which means it’s time to focus on design.</p>
<p>After watching a few tutorials on FreeCAD, I figured I was ready to get started. Rather than diving into a skateboard, I thought I’d start on something easier. My alarm clock is currently some nixie tubes connected to a bare circuit board, so I thought this would be a good opportunity to make a proper enclosure. It’d be boxy, but have some interesting angles and holes.</p>
<p>Four hours later, I was yelling at FreeCAD for having the world’s worst UI. Conceptually I have a great mental model of how to build what I want, but the tool doesn’t make it easy. I think I have a working enclosure, so it’s currently printing. Tomorrow I’m going to take the Haskell-based <a href="http://www.implicitcad.org/">ImplicitCAD</a> for a spin, which seems like it will better play to my strengths.</p>
<p>All in all, I’m feeling great about the project today!</p>
<h3 id="section-4">2020-11-05</h3>
<p>I spent today traveling, so got less done than I’d hoped. But nevertheless, got a good two hours in looking at ImplicitCAD. As a library, I’m sure it’s excellent, but my god is it missing the everyday Haskell usability. ImplicitCAD suffers from the usual problem of mathematics — namely that there are no types and all numbers, regardless of purpose, are just the reals. Positions? Reals. Rotations? Reals. Curvatures? Reals. Worse, there is no indication of what the axes are. It was a frustrating experience, made more frustrating by the fact that I don’t really understand the domain I’m working in. I’m going to spend tomorrow also working with Implicit, as I think I’ve sussed out enough to be able to get some real work done. But if that doesn’t turn out to be the case, I’m going to cut my losses and use some other CAD tool.</p>
<h3 id="section-5">2020-01-06</h3>
<p>Today I gave ImplicitCAD another go, and made some solid progress on it. I learned that the default camera is facing the front of the object, and that the coordinate space is <code>(width, depth, height)</code>. After thinking very hard yesterday about how to construct the objects I wanted, I managed to put together a parametric version of the enclosure for my alarm clock, and the result is significantly easier to manipulate. I think I’m going to move forwards with ImplicitCAD as my modeling software.</p>
<p>Tomorrow all of the traveling should have died down, and I plan to get in a good session with my father, the king of batteries and building weird machines. It’ll be good to pick his brain on the feasibility of a full-sized skateboard, now that I’m reasonably confident this thing is doable.</p>
<h3 id="section-6">2020-01-07</h3>
<p>Spent the day discussing the project with my dad, who had some great ideas about how to go about actually manufacturing this thing. He also showed me some good places to look for parts, and we found some promising wheel/motor hubs. Furthermore, regenerative braking appears to be something I’ll get for free.</p>
<p>I also started CAD modeling the board. I’ve got its frame all modeled parametrically, so I can fill in real values when I get the real parts measured. I’m still missing the electronics and battery compartments on my model, but it’ll be easy to get that figured out tomorrow.</p>
        ]]>
      </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
      <title>Algebra-Driven Design</title>
      <id>blog/algebra-driven-design/index.html</id>
      <link href='blog/algebra-driven-design/index.html'/>
      <published>2020-09-10T16:55:00Z</published>
      <updated>2020-09-10T16:55:00Z</updated>

      <content type="html">
        <![CDATA[
        <p>Wondering where I’ve been lately?</p>
<p>After almost a year of work, I’m <em>thrilled</em> to announce the completion my new book, <a href="https://algebradriven.design">Algebra-Driven Design</a>. It’s the culmination of two rewrites, and comes with a beautiful foreword written by John Hughes, the inventor of QuickCheck.</p>
<p>In the book, we take a fundamentally different approach to the software design process, focusing on deriving libraries from equations, algebraic manipulation and well-studied mathematical objects. The resulting code is guaranteed to be free of abstraction leaks, and in many cases, actually writes itself.</p>
<p>If that sounds like the sort of software you’d like to write, I’d highly encourage you to <a href="https://algebradriven.design">give it a read</a>.</p>
<center>
<a href="https://algebradriven.design"><img src="/images/add.png" alt="Algebra-Driven Design"></a>
</center>
<p>Back to regular blogging sometime soonish.</p>
        ]]>
      </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
      <title>No Coffee and Quantifying the Self</title>
      <id>blog/no-coffee/index.html</id>
      <link href='blog/no-coffee/index.html'/>
      <published>2020-02-28T00:50:00Z</published>
      <updated>2020-02-28T00:50:00Z</updated>

      <content type="html">
        <![CDATA[
        <p>For my first two decades of life, I could never sleep. I’d go to bed at whatever time was my bedtime (maybe 9pm?) and lay restlessly in the dark for several hours every night until I finally got to sleep. I honestly had no idea that other people <em>didn’t</em> do that, that they got to sleep in an average of twenty minutes. I attribute a lot of my current mental acuity to this — that I had three hours of dedicated and mandatory <em>thinking time</em> every day for twenty years.</p>
<p>In retrospect, probably it was that can of Coke I habitually drank every dinner. It never felt like the caffeine affected me. Those endless nights of sleeplessness just felt like <em>the way it was.</em></p>
<p>I was reminded of this anecdote by a scary experience I had today. I ran into a guy who might have been my old coworker from halfway around the world, many years ago. We never worked together, but he had a distinctive face, and this guy had the same distinctive face.</p>
<p>He might have been my old coworker, but I’m not sure. I didn’t ask. Instead I got <em>the fear.</em> I got so fucking nervous about saying hi to this guy that I flinched away from the encounter, and am left to wonder about his identity forever. Or at least until tomorrow when I’ll probably run into him again at the same place.</p>
<p>These bouts of nerves — I used to get them all the time. But haven’t for the last four months or so. And my last four months have been overwhelmingly socially successful, most of which I attribute to higher-than-usual confidence. It’s the same nerves I used to associate with going over and talking to pretty girls. It’s the same nerves that I got before asking for a raise. It’s the same nerves I got while waiting in the queue at the bank.</p>
<p>Wait, what? Waiting at the bank? How is that nerve-racking? Good question. I’m not sure, but that was the first time I ever associated <em>my nervousness</em> with <em>all the damn caffeine I was drinking.</em> Not that I ever let that stop me from drinking coffee, but at least I was aware of it.</p>
<p>Today, nerves again, for the first time in months. And maybe it’s a coincidence, but I had just finished a strong coffee, after only eating soup for breakfast, after spending four months on an island with notoriously bad coffee, where the instant-variety is ubiquitous. I hadn’t stopped drinking coffee over the last few months, but maybe I’d accidentally stopped overdosing on caffeine?</p>
<p>I’ve been really grooving on being not-unbearably-nervous Sandy these last few months. It’s been a period of aggressive self-actualization; getting to a point where not only do I know I can take on the world, but I <em>feel it,</em> too. How silly would it be if my amazing change in personality was due to a fluke accident of stopping my socially-acceptable drug habit?</p>
<p>Now, granted, this is all conjecture, but it seems worth an experiment. So for the next two weeks, I’m going to consume zero caffeine, and see if I get any more of these nerves. I’ll keep track of my subjective confidence levels, and of my feelings of self-actualization.</p>
<p>On first glance, it feels like my productivity is going to suffer. “Of course caffeine makes me more productive!” Well known fact, that. <em>Everyone knows</em> caffeine makes you more productive. But I can think of more times I’ve been <em>way too caffeinated</em> and completely unable to work, than I can think of times I felt a profound performance improvement from taking a coffee (hangovers excluded.)</p>
<p>Last year I read a book on quitting smoking, even though I don’t and have never smoked. It made the interesting claim that over time, smoking lowers your default state, and having a cigarette brings you back to your old norm. The contrast is there; smoking does make you feel better and more productive, but only relative to your state of withdrawal. Relative to your non-smoking normal, it just brings you back to par. This feels very plausible for the case of coffee as well; I’ve heard much of the same comments from my friends who have stopped drinking it.</p>
<p>The great part is that I already have the infrastructure in place to measure my productivity. A little known secret of this website is that it <a href="https://sandymaguire.me/dailystats/">tracks my computer time <em>to the minute.</em></a> Which means that I have historical productivity data for the last few years, and so looking at trends during the next two weeks requires no extra effort on my part.</p>
<p>I’m writing this blog post mostly because I couldn’t sleep (related????) and figured I might as well do something productive instead of being uncomfortable in bed. I guess the takeaway here is to build lots of weird infrastructure just because it’s interesting. I never expected my daily tracking stuff to be <em>useful,</em> but having already done the legwork means that I’m now ready to carry out an <a href="https://sandymaguire.me/blog/time-compression/">exceptionally high value-of-information</a> experiment.</p>
<p>Oh, and also a reminder that our bodies are just meat machines that respond to chemical inputs just like any other automation does. This is a thing that I always seem to forget, and am constantly amazed when I remember it. Maybe writing it down will help. Hopefully.</p>
<p>You guys! We’re just <em>meat machines!</em> Maybe changing our personalities isn’t as easy as just drinking less coffee, but then again, <em>maybe it is.</em></p>
        ]]>
      </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
      <title>Resolutions for the Year</title>
      <id>blog/2020-goals/index.html</id>
      <link href='blog/2020-goals/index.html'/>
      <published>2020-02-03T18:19:00Z</published>
      <updated>2020-02-03T18:19:00Z</updated>

      <content type="html">
        <![CDATA[
        <p>Seeing as it’s already(!) February, now is a bit late to be writing my new year’s resolutions. But late is better than never, so instead, we’ll just call them <em>resolutions for the year.</em> I’ve been putting this stuff off for six weeks now, so shoutouts to my new friend Katha for holding me accountable.</p>
<p>I’m half-way through a blog post on “excellence comes from qualitative changes, not quantitative ones,” and with that in mind, much of my focus for the next year will be to do things differently than I have been. It’s pretty clear that I could write more blog posts or read more books or live in more countries. But those things are playing to my strengths, rather than work on my weaknesses.</p>
<p>The big theme of 2020 is that it’s the year I turn 30! My <em>god</em> where has the time gone? Thankfully I don’t feel old, nor am I worried about an arbitrary number — but 30 feels like a good excuse to make some lifestyle changes. I’d like to spend a lot of this year focusing on having my life in a stable configuration for the upcoming decade.</p>
<p>Along those lines, I’ve divided my goals for 2020 into three categories — two focused on the future, and one for making sure I keep doing cool stuff in the here-and-now. Since we’re <em>already</em> here and now, let’s talk about that one first.</p>
<h2 id="output">Output</h2>
<p><strong>First</strong>, this year I will finish and publish my new book, <a href="https://www.patreon.com/designandinterpretation">Design and Interpretation of Haskell Programs</a>. This isn’t going to be challenging other than simply putting in the time, so I’m including it just to ensure it actually gets done.</p>
<p><strong>Second</strong>, I am going to perform two hours worth of live music this year. I’m not sure if the format will be one big show, or lots of little ones, but I’ve got 11 months to figure that out. This is scary.</p>
<p><strong>Third</strong>, and relatedly, I am going to compose 5 songs that I’m proud of. I don’t really know how to compose music, but I am excited to learn. It’s probably one of those practice-makes-perfect situations — hopefully.</p>
<p><strong>Fourth</strong>, I am going to learn a new programming language. I’m getting musty and curmudgeonly by only writing Haskell, so it’s time to branch out and learn something new. To avoid any weaseling, this has to be an <em>interesting</em> new language, so something along the lines of Prolog or Rust or Lisp, rather than Ruby or Go. The metric for success here is to have written a non-trivial, real-life, idiomatic program in the language.</p>
<p><strong>Fifth</strong>, I am going to finish all of the exercises on <a href="https://portswigger.net">Portswigger</a>, because they’re interesting and very outside of my skill-set of writing good Haskell programs.</p>
<p><strong>Finally</strong> for this pillar, I am going to read 10 <em>really excellent</em> books this year. Last year was a bit of a dearth on the reading front, and despite reading something like 60 books, I found it very hard to pick 5 good ones. I want to change that; there’s no point in reading a bunch of shit just for the sake of it.</p>
<h2 id="health">Health</h2>
<p>A change I’ve really wanted to make in my lifestyle has been to get healthy. I’ve never been particularly <em>unhealthy,</em> which has been my excuse for putting it off for so long. But my biggest fear is that I am only operating at 1/10th of my productive capability, and simply have no basis for comparison. Rather than continue to worry about that, I’m just going to spend a year throwing empiricism at it and see what shakes out.</p>
<p><strong>First</strong>, this year I am going to learn to love vegetables. Currently I don’t. I never have. People keep saying they’re good for me and I am going to die without them, but seeing as I haven’t ever died<a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"><sup>1</sup></a> I haven’t really taken them at their word. BUT my god is this a ubiquitous one. At the very least, picking around the vegetables takes a big toll on my quality of life. So it’s time to face the fear, and learn to love vegetables. By the end of the year, I will be actively eating fruits and vegetables with every meal.</p>
<p><strong>Second</strong>, I am not going to consume any alcohol in 2020. I’m already about two months in, and have been having a great time. But sometimes the urge comes back, and I need to beat it down into submission. Qualifying this as an explicit goal for my year will assuage the desire, I suspect.</p>
<p><strong>Third</strong>, I am going to do at least 150 minutes of exercise every week this year. That’s about 20 minutes a day, and is allegedly the bare minimum necessary to keep yourself fit and healthy. Seeing as I currently do about zero minutes of exercise a week, this seems like a drastic improvement.</p>
<p><strong>Fourth</strong>, I am only going to watch high-value TV this year. Since I started tracking my youtube view-time, I’ve been disgusted with myself. There’s a lot of dumb bullshit I watch just because it’s there; I don’t find myself actively learning or feeling inspired by it, and I never feel like it was time well-spent. Any content that isn’t actively-educational to something I want to learn, or otherwise inspiring, will be forfeited. However, I will grant myself one movie a week, because media can be a social thing that I don’t necessarily want to miss out on.</p>
<h2 id="foundation">Foundation</h2>
<p>My final category of goals is of bigger, more meaningful stuff in my life that I think is missing.</p>
<p><strong>First</strong>, I am going to do consistent journaling this year. I will aim for at least five times a week, but not stress the actual numbers so long as it happens weekly. I find journaling helps me sort out my mind, but sometimes there just isn’t anything that actively needs to be sorted out!</p>
<p><strong>Second</strong>, I am going to volunteer my skills to a worthwhile organization this year. I don’t know who, exactly, but I’m sure almost every small non-profit has IT problems. And I’m good at IT.</p>
<p><strong>Third</strong>, I am going to make five <em>really good</em> friends this year. Over the last several years I have moved too often to really invest in tight friendships. While we do our best to stay in touch, it is often not particularly successful. But strong friendships are an important part of any nutritious breakfast, and I find myself lonely without them. So it’s time to put in the work, and make some really good friends. They don’t necessarily need to be new acquaintances — new friendships with old people is OK. My criteria for success is to see these people at least once a week, and to always come away from my interactions with them feeling powerful, inspired, and better about life than I did before.</p>
<p><strong>Finally</strong>, I’m really fucking tired of being on the move. By the end of this year, I am going to have found a place to settle down for a good portion of my 30s. Somewhere I’m allowed to live, with my own place, with a good and solid social network around me. This is the most important thing I’ve been missing for the last several years, and I am <em>aching</em> to get it resolved.</p>
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr />
<ol>
<li id="fn1" role="doc-endnote"><p>Not even one time.<a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li>
</ol>
</section>
        ]]>
      </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
      <title>Habits</title>
      <id>blog/habits/index.html</id>
      <link href='blog/habits/index.html'/>
      <published>2020-01-13T14:21:00Z</published>
      <updated>2020-01-13T14:21:00Z</updated>

      <content type="html">
        <![CDATA[
        <p>One of the things I learned last decade (<a href="/blog/2010s/">but forgot to mention</a>) is that actions are the only things that matter. Who you are inside simply doesn’t count if you never show it to people. This is an important realization — that true beliefs must guide action. Nobody in a mind-reader, and so nobody will never know what’s inside if you don’t show them.</p>
<p>Beliefs that are only inside you, by definition, are not out in the world, and thus can never influence the world. Action are what count — in fact, they’re all that count.</p>
<p>Before this week, when I thought of “habits”, I associated “thing that you consistently do”. But as I’ve been coming to realize, habits of “things you consistently do not do” are likely just as important, if not more. For example, late last year I was going through a machine learning course, and while I made it a habit of watching a lecture every day, I also made a habit of not actually trying any of it myself. The result: I have a high-level idea of how machine learning works, but I’ve never tried it, and the thought of getting started and <em>actually doing it</em> feels uncomfortable. My habit is now to learn about machine learning, but to not actually practice it.</p>
<p>Bad idea.</p>
<p>All we are is creatures of habits. In a very real sense, we are defined by the things we do habitually. And this is an important thing to recognize — that if we don’t nip small problem, they will quickly grow into traits that fundamentally weaken our character.</p>
<p>Dollar to donuts, I would guess that this idea of “negative habits” is why university is so much more successful at teaching than self-directed online classes. Having graded homework that you’re paying for is one hell of a motivator to get into the habit of applying what you learn.</p>
<p>Right now I’m studying computer security from a textbook. The nice part of a textbook is that you can work on it anywhere. After three days of study, I realized I had made terrific progress through the book, but, like in machine learning, hadn’t attempted any of the exercises for myself. Worse, the thought of doing an exercise already filled me with apprehension.</p>
<p>Another bad situation to be in. So I <a href="/blog/strength/">drew up some willpower</a>, then and there, to get started on one. Mustering the energy was hard, but learning this stuff is important to me — and it definitely wasn’t going to get easier to break the habit if I put this thing off again.</p>
<p>On a related note, I have recently identified a failure mechanism in myself. I just got out of a short, but fiery relationship. Within a month we went from having never met to living with one another in a foreign country where neither of us spoke the language, and spending literally all of our time together.</p>
<p>As you might expect, things exploded rather spectacularly, and I think a huge part of it was due to the fact that neither of us could practice the habits that define us. We were too crowded by one another to maintain ourselves. Without practicing our habits, we stop being ourselves in a very literal sense — after all, we are what we do.</p>
<p>I think this is an important thing to keep in mind when navigating a new relationship: the reason you like someone is the culmination of the things they do. As such, we should be very hesitant to disrupt that balance. Unless you’re impossibly compatible to begin with, introducing charge slowly (maybe imperceptibly) seem like a prudent move.</p>
        ]]>
      </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
      <title>What Did I Learn in the 2010s?</title>
      <id>blog/2010s/index.html</id>
      <link href='blog/2010s/index.html'/>
      <published>2020-01-12T12:48:00Z</published>
      <updated>2020-01-12T12:48:00Z</updated>

      <content type="html">
        <![CDATA[
        <p>Not only is it a new year — and therefore a new me — but it’s also a <em>new decade.</em> Having been born in 1990, new decades for the world roughly correspond to new decades for me. I thought it would be interesting and nostalgic to look back at the last ten years to see what I’ve learned.</p>
<p>The most important thing I learned in the last decade was <strong>confidence.</strong> Interestingly, in my <a href="/blog/the-secret-of-happinesstm/">earliest blog post</a>, I give the advice to “trust yourself. I mean, really trust yourself.” Apparently I thought I was already confident — I wasn’t. In particular, I learned to be aware of <a href="/blog/double-dipping/">Dunning-Kruger</a>, and that <a href="/blog/brilliance/">most problems are effort-constrained</a>. I learned that there is nothing magical <a href="/blog/no-miracle-people/">separating me (or anyone else) from geniuses</a>. I learned to <a href="/blog/a-lesson-learned/">separate the person I am from the person I want to be</a>, and to focus on the latter. I learned about the <a href="/blog/neighborhoods">importance of knowing the people around you</a>, and of <a href="/blog/home-is-where-your-people-are/">having good social support structures in place</a>. Along those lines, I started being <a href="/blog/outside-view">very selective about the people I was spending time with</a>. I <a href="/blog/get-the-girl/">learned about dating</a>, and how to be attractive, and how to make moves — it turns out people aren’t mind readers, and if you don’t tell them you’re interested, they don’t know.</p>
<p>But in general, what I really learned here was to <a href="/blog/building-over-the-abyss/">stop being so <em>fucking scared</em></a> of <a href="/blog/comfort-zones/">everything all the time</a>. I learned to just go do things. Sometimes they’ll go poorly, but more often they’ll go well. And if you’re smart and trust in yourself to be able to handle the failures, well, that’s most of life right there. I learned about <a href="/blog/shame/">how I failed</a>, and to <a href="/blog/why-i-quit/">reflect on those things</a>, and to promise myself <a href="/blog/letter-to-myself/">to never do them again</a>. One particular tactic that came out of this new understanding is to <a href="/blog/new-city-guide/">always say “yes” to thing.</a></p>
<p>The second most important thing I learned over the last decade was <strong>strategy.</strong> I learned to <a href="/blog/affording-ascendancy/">build up momentum</a> in roughly the right direction, even if I wasn’t <a href="/blog/one-night-stands/">entirely sure</a> where I was <a href="/blog/showing-me-the-way/">intending to land</a>. I used this technique to <a href="/blog/book-mechanics/">systematically put together</a> an amazing CV, and arguably <a href="/blog/become-a-programmer/">an even more impressive set of skills</a>. I learned about the <a href="/blog/say-hi-to-lucy/">notion of career capital</a>, and <a href="/blog/book-mechanics/">accumulated enough of it</a> to turn it into a <a href="https://thinkingwithtypes.com">successful book</a>. I learned about the value of publicly <a href="/blog/book-mechanics/">committing to doing something that sounds hard and scary</a><a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"><sup>1</sup></a>. After some talks at work that went <em>very badly,</em> I learned the importance of playing to your audience. Perhaps <em>most importantly</em>, I learned that I need <a href="/blog/looking-back-on-2018/">very specific goals and metrics</a> if I want to have <a href="/blog/2013-in-review/">successful years</a>.</p>
<p>The third most important thing I learned was how to get a sense of my <strong>limits and capabilities.</strong> I learned that that feeling of “omg I am <em>already</em> working at full capacity” is <a href="/blog/nanowrimo-postmortem/">usually wrong</a>, and that <a href="/blog/burnout/">real burnout</a> feels more like carrying physical weight. I successfully <a href="/blog/generalization-as-intelligence-amplification/">identified abstraction as being a worthwhile tool</a> to <a href="/blog/chunking-conceptual-legos/">study in its own regard</a>. I realized that Haskell is <a href="https://reasonablypolymorphic.com/blog/archives/">the best vessel for exercising those abstraction muscles</a>. I learned to put <a href="/blog/first-20-recursive-bees/">my money where my mouth is</a> and to always be willing to bet on my beliefs. I further learned that this makes <em>everyone else</em> very very uncomfortable. I learned how to focus my zen, and how to be responsible for how I feel, and to not try and shirk it off onto other people. I learned a lot about my <a href="/blog/thrashing-wildly/">common</a> <a href="/blog/too-smart/">failure methods</a>. I realized the importance of having <a href="/blog/reclaim-your-attention/">uninterrupted attention</a>, and <a href="/blog/reflections-on-a-dumb-phone/">threw my phone into a large body of water</a> not once, but three times, during the last decade.</p>
<p>Fourth on the list of big things I made progress on is my <strong>sense of purpose.</strong> In the early days of the decade, I spent a <a href="/blog/along-for-the-ride/">lot of time</a> talking about <a href="/blog/not-for-its-own-sake/">saving the world</a> without knowing what that meant or what it would look like. I think I have made some good progress on this, and to be specific, I think that climate change and late-stage democracy are big problems that could be solved by a few smart, technical people working evening weekends. I intend to spend the next decade being one of those people. I learned to start <a href="/blog/building-over-the-abyss/">taking responsibility</a> for my failings, and <a href="/blog/shame">for problems around me.</a><a href="#fn2" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref2" role="doc-noteref"><sup>2</sup></a> I learned to <a href="/blog/authority-and-momentum/">question authority</a>, and that <a href="/blog/where-uni-fails/">the people in charge</a> don’t <a href="/blog/teaching-badly">know any better than I do,</a></p>
<p>Finally, I made a lot of progress on my <strong>lifestyle.</strong> I learned that the traditional Western path is <a href="/blog/perpetual-motion/">definitely not</a> <a href="/blog/reaching-climbing/">for me.</a> I learned that I need <a href="/blog/no-possessions/">very little</a> to survive, and that realization has afforded me the ability to <a href="/blog/skaidre/">pack up and leave</a> whenever I <a href="/blog/best-place-to-live/">feel like it.</a> These days, my total worldly possessions weigh about 7kg. I’ve learned how to travel, and how to put myself in uncomfortable situations in which I need to YOLO my way out. Through lots of trial and error, I learned <a href="/blog/new-city-guide/">how to move to a new city</a>.</p>
<p>In addition to all of this, I learned lots of <em>things.</em> After all, I spent five years this decade in university, another five teaching myself Haskell, and one year <a href="https://reasonablypolymorphic.com/tags/polysemy.html">actively doing research</a>. As a programmer, I’m several orders of magnitude better than I was ten years ago. I’m also <a href="/blog/play-lots-of-music/">ten times a better musician</a>, much better at speaking French, and infinitely better at skateboarding, improv, electronics repair, building IKEA furniture, and miming in languages I don’t understand.</p>
<center>
<p><a href="/images/decade/world2020.png"><img src="/images/decade/world2020.png" alt="Everywhere I've been"
width="80%" height="80%"/></a></p>
Everywhere I’ve been, as of 2020
</center>
<p>All in all, it’s been a great decade. I’m happy with how much progress I’ve made, but it’s clear that I need to get better faster if I want to tackle everything on the bucket list.</p>
<p>Thanks for staying with me over the last decade. Let’s strive, and collectively make the 2020s our best decade yet.</p>
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr />
<ol>
<li id="fn1" role="doc-endnote"><p>Which, as it happens, is why I’m writing this post today. I promised my friend Ciara that I would. Thanks Ciara!<a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li>
<li id="fn2" role="doc-endnote"><p>In particular, my good friend Austin Dobrik has been a huge role model on this front. I’ve spent the last ten years constantly amazed at his bravery in calling out bad behavior and helping people in dire situations.<a href="#fnref2" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li>
</ol>
</section>
        ]]>
      </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
      <title>Revisiting 2019</title>
      <id>blog/revisiting-2019/index.html</id>
      <link href='blog/revisiting-2019/index.html'/>
      <published>2020-01-01T14:58:00Z</published>
      <updated>2020-01-01T14:58:00Z</updated>

      <content type="html">
        <![CDATA[
        <h2 id="looking-back">Looking Back</h2>
<p>With 2019 so recently behind us, it seems like as good a time as any to reminisce. This is actually my second attempt at doing a yearly write-up; as it happens, the year of our lord 2019 wasn’t a particularly good one for me, and as a result, my first write-up came off aggressively negative.</p>
<p>But negativity feels like a poor way to start the new year, and thus, I’ve decided to focus only on the best parts of the last one.</p>
<p>2019 started off with a great deal of promise. Ariel, one of my best friends, came to ring in the new year with me. We spent our time jamming on Grateful Dead covers, doing the monster mash, and listening to Suavemente… over and over and over again — much to the dismay of poor roommate James. For new years eve, we rigged up my old Arduino-controlled light vest, and headed down to karaoke night. Starting off with so much music inspired my only resolution for the year — to <a href="/blog/play-lots-of-music/">play more music</a>.</p>
<p>Too soon Ariel needed to head home, and I found myself deep in a new romantic relationship with my roommate. I knew it was a bad idea. She knew it was a bad idea. Literally everyone told me it was a bad idea. But we didn’t let that stop us. Instead we leaned into it. Maybe it was too much Elvis Crespo, or maybe it was too much lovey-dovey roommate stuff, but we accidentally pushed James out of the house. He left without so much as a word to me, while I was traveling in San Francisco. Apparently he responded less well to the Suavemente than I thought!</p>
<p>I was in SF for business. The AI-safety non-profit MIRI and I were courting one another, and after a successful first few interviews, they invited me down to meet in person. Since I had spent a few years there in the past, I decided to take the opportunity to spend a week in my old stomping grounds — meeting up with old friends and taking in the scene.</p>
<p>While it was excellent to see everyone, I noticed something scary. Every single one of my friends was aggressively depressed. They all seemed to simultaneously hate living in SF, and be completely oblivious to this fact. Their vibe reminded me of <em>my</em> depression when I lived in the Bay, and sufficiently spooked me away from attending the MIRI interview. I was afraid if I went I would be tempted to take the job, and subsequently need to return to the Bay.</p>
<p>My good friends Fintan and Vikrem also came to SF to see me. We spent the week getting into lots of trouble, including (but not limited to) being literally kicked in the ass by a hobo, and witnessing a back-alleyway blowjob.</p>
<p>Vikrem is a man who is notoriously anti-SF, and upon my return, he deluged me with SF-is-shitty memes. One of them was a video about some guy who lives in a shitty SF apartment without enough space, and so needs to rig up stupid engineering projects to cope. I felt inspired by the video, and decided to do some DIY to spruce up my own place in Ottawa.</p>
<p>The result was some lights beneath my bed that simulated the northern lights. They would imperceptibly change colors and patterns, but always be colorful and always fill me with joy. I also did some redecorating, and commissioned a painting from my friend Anika. It helped make Ottawa feel a little more like home.</p>
<p>But Ottawa never truly felt like home. I had moved there on a whim in September of 2018, mostly due to the convenience of it. I was moving back to Canada, but there was no obvious place to be — my family and friends had all performed their own diasporas, and there was no critical mass of people I knew anywhere. Other than SF, which was a) in the wrong country, and b) not a place I was going to move to.</p>
<p>The lesson I learned from living in Denver is that if a city doesn’t feel like home, it’s probably because you aren’t working hard enough to meet people. So I went out, in Ottawa. I joined a pub trivia group, a choir, a jam group, an engineering space, an improv troupe, the functional programming meetup, two climbing gyms, among other activities. Most of these were delightful amounts of fun, but I never really met anyone I really connected with.</p>
<p>Instead, I started diving into my work. A few weeks previous, I had come across an academic paper that promised to solve some theoretical problems I’d been wrestling with for two years. It caught my attention, and after internalizing the approach, I immersed myself. For eight to ten hours a day, for roughly four months, taking no time off, I worked and researched and created. It felt good. It was the only intellectual exercise I found myself getting in Ottawa. The result was my <a href="https://github.com/isovector/polysemy">polysemy</a> project.</p>
<p>Somehow, I became aware of the Montreal functional programming group, and was invited by the very excellent <a href="http://gelisam.blogspot.com/">gelisam</a> to come and give a talk. My presentation was on the research I’d been so deep into the last few months, and this was the first time I was widely showing it to the world. The response was stellar — not only the feedback from the talk, but also just all of the super-cool people I met.</p>
<p>At some point, I bought an <a href="https://onewheel.com/">electric, one-wheel skateboard</a>. Cruising through Ottawa late at night on that thing, grooving out to surf-rock was one of the closest things to ecstasy I’ve ever experienced. I rode it out through one too many thunderstorms, and waterlogged the electronics. In an amazing fit of engineering prowess, I later managed to fix all of the destroyed electronics. The joy of riding around on <em>previously broken,</em> electric, one-wheel skateboard <em>that you’ve fixed yourself</em> is even more incredible than the original experience.</p>
<p>My now-ex had decided she too was leaving Ottawa, but not for six weeks. It didn’t seem fair to kick her out and make her find such a short-term lease, so we continued living together. We decided to make the best of a bad situation, that we should unite against the manchildren in the basement, and not bring anyone home (our rooms shared a thin, thin wall.) Over the weeks, we tentatively became friends again, and it was nice. The city felt a little less empty.</p>
<p>I started thinking about leaving Ottawa. Living there had been a solid attempt, but was clearly a failed experiment. Unfortunately the situation hadn’t changed — there was <em>still</em> nowhere obvious to move to. I had an inkling of an idea, to emulate Paul Erdos and spend the rest of my life surfing on excellent engineers’ couches. I dreamed of moving from city to city, spreading my knowledge, connecting like-minded people, and building cool things. So I put out a call for interested parties, and my god did they come. Before I knew it, I had two years’ worth of couches to stay on. That cemented the idea, and I started planning to sell my things and learn how to live out of a suitcase.</p>
<p>As a test run, I reached out to two people in Toronto — my old friend <a href="https://github.com/davidrusu">David Rusu</a>, and my soon-to-be new one, <a href="https://github.com/JonathanLorimer">Jonathan Lorimer</a>. The experience was stellar. Both men were <em>hungry to create,</em> just like I was. In the course of a week, I think I did about 60 hours of dedicated engineering work. It was everything I had been dreaming about for a year. I returned to Ottawa, my heart heavy to be coming back, and knew it was time to pull the plug.</p>
<p>My other cousin Charlotte had recently moved to town, and we found ourselves reconnecting over a forgotten-decades-ago appreciation for Jeopardy. In a very fortuitous state of affairs, Jeopardy history was in the middle of being made, so we hunkered down at the beginning, and spent weeks powering our way through.</p>
<p>In my last weeks in Ottawa, an old friend and I went out to hip-hop trivia. We crushed it, placing first. WE ARE THE BIGGIE PROFESSORS — more like Notorious PhD, am I right???</p>
<p>I left my skateboard with John, the coolest person I’d met in Ottawa, though unfortunately I’d met him only a month before. In that time, we spent something like twenty hours discussing philosophy and life and all sorts of deep, interesting stuff. Leaving the skateboard and leaving John were the hardest parts of leaving Ottawa, so it seemed poetic to leave them together.</p>
<p>My last day in Ottawa rapidly approached, and I found myself on a bus to Toronto, to meet back up with Jonathan. He graciously invited me to give a talk at the Toronto functional programming meetup, and I accepted. There I had my first taste of fame, where after my talk, <em>everyone just hung around,</em> casually listening to me talk. There was a gaggle of like 20 fanboys, sitting around to hear me ramble on without a shred of eloquence about GADTs and type-level programming. I felt famous, like the next coming of Ed Kmett. Then we went to the bar and everyone forgot about me and the universe went back to normal.</p>
<p>Somehow I ended up in Vancouver, to stay with my excellent, ex-coworker, Travis, and an equally excellent old-friend, Andrew. Being back in Vancouver was delightful, especially my munchkining discussions with Andrew, weird mathematical discussions with Reed, and a wistful fourteen hour catching up with Erin — a personal favorite human of mine.</p>
<p>My location rapidly converged upon my parents’. I spent a nice week with them, involving swimming, learning to make Caesars, an excellent painting lesson from my aunt, and a fun night at the local observatory. My dad’s health isn’t particularly good, so I decided to be around for his upcoming operation a few weeks later.</p>
<p>In the meantime I went to visit the awe-inspiring <a href="https://chrispenner.ca/">Chris Penner</a>. We had a great week together, culminating in an epic piano jam sesh. It was the first test of my year’s new music skills, and I came out from it very impressed with my newfound abilities.</p>
<p>The plan was to head south into the States, and spend a few months rail-tramping my way across the continent. But my inclination to stay in North America was rapidly fading, so I took my friend up on her invitation to come to Amsterdam.</p>
<p>Amsterdam was much less fun than I was expecting. We spent most of our time in the library, but I did meet an old friend from back home who is now the Amsterdam cheese girl. So that’s cool I guess! Also I did a lot of bicycling, and came away convinced that bike-only cities are the future.</p>
<p>I went off to Munich. While waiting for the train (it had hit someone, and was thus DELAYED), I met a fun woman from Leipzig. She told me stories of being an au pair, and of her paired child who, in cold blood, threatened to set her on fire. We had a great chat, and she invited me to come visit.</p>
<p>In Munich I stayed with the excellent <a href="https://dev.to/jvanbruegge">Jan van Bruegge</a>. He met me at the train station at midnight, and despite having never met before, we quickly became close friends. That night, getting comfortable on his couch, I was struck by the most amazing feeling — that my life is so incredible, to have such fantastic people willing to host me on their couches. I’ve never experienced such true gratitude before.</p>
<p>Thank you, from the very bottom of my heart, to <a href="http://reasonablypolymorphic.com/erdos/">everyone who hosted me this year</a> — thanks David, Jonathan, Boris, James, Travis, Chris, Andrew, Gintare, Jan, Soares, Justin, Anna, Andy, Asad and Vincent.</p>
<p>My travels took me all over. I went to Leipzig to meet that woman from the train, and to play harmonica, and to do cool category theory stuff with Soares — who graciously invited me to the Haskell eXchange. I headed back to Munich to build watering systems and fight Scala’s variance mechanism with Justin. I had a romantic little week with Elli. I met up with Matiej, my close collaborator in Bratislava, and with an old flame in Vienna. She’s since gotten <em>fit</em> and took me to the gym during my visit, during which time I was completely emasculated by just how much stronger she was than I! Her roommate Andy and I had an excellent daylong conversation about computers, and I met the mysterious spy woman Moni, whom I was relatively certain wanted to kill me.</p>
<p>But she didn’t. And so I went to London.</p>
<p>London and I have been flirting with one another for years. I’d considered moving there in 2018 for a woman, in 2019 it invited me <a href="/blog/gatekept/">to do a PhD</a>. Then the Haskell eXchange rang, and I couldn’t resist its siren call. It was a grand time.</p>
<p>But a <em>weird</em> time. I met a lot of people whom I then considered to be personal heroes. It was a rather underwhelming — one was a total dick, and another seemed like he was intentionally not understanding what I was trying to say. But besides that, the conference was a blast. I met the eminent <a href="https://richarde.dev/">Richard Eisenberg</a>, who knocked me off my feet with his overwhelming intelligence, thoughtfulness and kindness. Another personal favorite person of mine, <a href="https://github.com/judah">Judah Jacobson</a>, was there, and reconnecting with him was particularly joyful.</p>
<p>HsX had too many excellent people to iterate them all, but one other person who stood above the crowd was <a href="https://github.com/masaeedu">Asad Saeeduddin</a>. I’d met Asad briefly in Toronto a few months earlier, where we’d had an amazing conversation and he’d taught me a whirlwind of cool new stuff. My intended roommate had come down with the plague, and so I found myself homeless. Asad kindly let me stay with him, and we had a few great nights sharing music and doing old-school bro-ing out.</p>
<p>Also, I found myself as a minor celebrity at HsX! Several people had read my book, and went out of their ways to say nice things about it. One guy interrupted my conversation with someone else in order to have his book signed. It was an incredible pleasure to feel just how much people liked this thing I’d created. And the conversation I was in wasn’t particularly good, so there was no love lost on that front.</p>
<p>During the tail-end of the conference, I got extremely sick. Like, “oh god, this is probably the night I die”-extremely sick. Thanks to Asad, I didn’t, but it was too close a call for comfort. Though I didn’t realize it at the time, this was a symptom of too much traveling, too much work, simply too much everything.</p>
<p>A few months earlier, I’d applied for a job at Imperial College, after not getting in with my PhD program. They called me in for an interview while I was in London, and apparently I aced it, because (SO MANY WEEKS LATER) they offered me the job. I spent a few days hanging around Imperial, working with my amazing, would-be colleagues, <a href="https://kcsongor.github.io/">Csongor Kiss</a> and <a href="https://www.imperial.ac.uk/people/n.wu">Nick Wu</a>. I can’t say enough good things about these two. At the end of the day, I decided that my mental health wasn’t good enough to sign a year-and-a-half contract with Imperial, and so, with many regrets, I passed on the job. It was hard, but definitely the right thing to do.</p>
<p>A week later, back in Munich, I was still trying to sort out my life plans. I had several “maybe we could do this” options on the table, but nobody on the other side seemed very keen on giving me a definite yes or no. In a move of desperation, I booked a ticket for Bangkok two days ahead of time. I needed a reminder that this was my life, and that I was in control of it. And what a better way to remember than to drop everything and head to a different continent with no plans other than “diving might be nice” and “I need a place to write this book.”</p>
<p>Oh yeah, I’d decided to write a book, and was actively working on it.</p>
<p>During my last trip to Thailand, I’d met a man who continually told me of how great Koh Lanta was. Since I didn’t have any other ideas, I finally took him up on that. Over the next six weeks, Koh Lanta became the closest place to home I’ve had in several years.</p>
<p>Not much happens on Koh Lanta. It’s one big island with one big road going all the way along it. I spent my days swimming, reading, writing, playing guitar, doing karaoke, and socializing at the hostel.</p>
<p>Because Koh Lanta is nestled in the middle of several BIG PARTY PLACES, it filters those people out of the equation. As a result, those who come to Koh Lanta turn out to be stellar humans on average. Some particularly great people I met were Heleen, Lily, Pavel, Jake, Ciara and Toby. Ciara and I spent a week traveling together, and she helped me realize just how burned out by programming I really was.</p>
<p>I decided to <a href="/blog/burnout/">take a clean break</a> from programming and from writing the book I was working on. At time of writing, I now haven’t touched any software for a month — the first break of its kind in 16 years. It feels <em>so fucking good.</em></p>
<p>My Thai visa was expiring, so I took a trip down to the Krabi Immigration office in order to convince them to grant me another week in this magnificent country. While bopping around Krabi Town, I met Natalia — the most scintillating, inspiring and fun person I’ve had the good fortune to encounter in years. The last few weeks of 2019 were spent with her, painting and playing music and skinny dipping and drinking mocktails and engaging in lots and lots and lots of amazing conversations.</p>
<p>All in all, 2019 wasn’t stellar, but got markedly better since I made the decision to come to Thailand. I’m feeling mentally and physically healthier than I have in a long, long time. It’s a powerful way to start the new year, and I’m ready to make the most of 2020.</p>
<h2 id="work-and-misc-metrics">Work and Misc Metrics</h2>
<p>I (and a robot on my account that I’m unable/unwilling to separate) made 3,137 commits to software projects in 2019. Some of the most impressive things were:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://gitlab.haskell.org/ghc/ghc/merge_requests/668">GHC !668</a>: A patch to GHC that makes the simplifier work harder on higher-rank functions.</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/isovector/polysemy">polysemy</a>: My fast and easy effect system.</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/isovector/dynahaskell">dynahaskell</a>: A proof-of-concept editor for Haskell that writes most of your code for you.</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/isovector/suavemente">suavemente</a>: An applicative GUI that runs Haskell applications over websockets.</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/isovector/hs-vexflow">hs-vexflow</a>: A DSL for generating sheet music in Haskell.</li>
</ul>
<p>Overall, I spent 567h in 2019 <em>doing work</em> on miscellaneous projects, of which 156h were spent directly on programming and doing research for polysemy. Another 46h went towards writing <a href="https://www.patreon.com/designandinterpretation">Design and Interpretation of Haskell Programs</a>.</p>
<p>In total, I published 32 blog posts, totaling 46,000 words.</p>
<p>Additionally, I sold 847 copies of <a href="https://thinkingwithtypes.com">Thinking with Types</a> this year.</p>
<p>Scarily, I spent 258h on the functional programming slack — which probably greatly contributed to my eventual burnout. That is a <em>lot</em> of time to spend thinking about Haskell.</p>
<p>Some other miscellaneous things I spent time doing:</p>
<ul>
<li>215h on facebook messenger</li>
<li>65h on email</li>
<li>48h recording music and learning music theory</li>
<li>40h on the phone</li>
<li>24h reading papers</li>
<li>15h preparing talks</li>
</ul>
<p>I spent 3185 hours on the computer in 2019. Yikes.</p>
<h2 id="books">Books</h2>
<p>I read <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/user_challenges/14778474">65 books</a> in 2019, which is a little better than my 56 in 2018, and much better than my 15 in 2017. Unfortunately, the books this year were lower quality on average, and finding five favorites was rather challenging. Regardless, here are my top books of 2019:</p>
<ul>
<li><em><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/530415.The_Art_of_Doing_Science_and_Engineering">The Art of Doing Science and Engineering</a></em>: This is the most inspiring book I’ve read in a very long time. It’s Richard Hamming’s (of Hamming problems fame) self-proclaimed “manual of style.” TAoDSaE is a frank look at Hamming’s life, how he was successful, where he wasn’t, and commentary on how he should have done better. This is a refreshing style of autobiography, that’s chocked full of important advice on how to choose good problems, and how to have a meaningful career.</li>
<li><em><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/49634053-radical-markets">Radical Markets</a></em>: A book on interesting ways of applying more economic theory to everyday life. It makes strong arguments for better strategies of governance, taxation, and immigration that will plausibly lead to better allocation of global resources.</li>
<li><em><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/8205855-the-4-hour-workweek-expanded-and-updated">The 4 Hour Workweek</a></em>: Campy but good — a nice book on debugging your mind away from “I need to work a <em>job</em>” towards <em>I just need to make enough money.</em> Comes with lots of practical advice about how to actually go about doing this — though admittedly a lot of it is obsolete today in
<ol start="2020" type="1">
<li></li>
</ol></li>
<li><em><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/18930446-thinking-in-jazz">Thinking in Jazz</a></em>: My goal for 2019 was to get good at music, and so I picked up this hoping to get an idea of how people actually become jazz musicians. And amazingly, this book <em>delivered!</em> It’s a fascinating compilation of dozens of interviews with jazz musicians, coalescing the commonalities into “the way to think about jazz,” primarily using first-hand prose. I’d strongly recommend this book, even if you aren’t interested in learning to play jazz.</li>
<li><em><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/40672036-digital-minimalism">Digital Minimalism</a></em>: Cal Newport is back, making the claim that cellphones and social media are bad for us. He makes a good case. The reason I like this book is it confirms what I’ve been saying for years — being always connected <em>sucks.</em> Digital Minimalism offers a gentler path to kicking the habit than my recommendation of “throw your phone into the ocean. CMON! DO IT! STOP BEING AFRAID!” Somewhat amazingly, my approach has <em>never once</em> worked. Can you believe that?</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="music">Music</h2>
<p>I didn’t listen to a lot of music from 2019 <em>in</em> 2019, with the notable exception of <strong>Sandy’s Official Banger of the Year:</strong> <a href="https://everyoneisdirty.bandcamp.com/">Everyone is Dirty</a>’s <a href="https://everyoneisdirty.bandcamp.com/track/hit-girl">Hit-Girl</a>.</p>
<p>My favorite newly-found artists of 2019 were:</p>
<ul>
<li>GDP</li>
<li>Mac Miller</li>
<li>New Monsoon</li>
<li>Nik Baertsch</li>
<li>Rhymefest</li>
<li>Strangefolk</li>
<li>Tennyson</li>
</ul>
<p>I’d like to take a second to shout-out Rhymefest, who has my <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=pMz6aRwpHVM">favorite rap line of all time</a>.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>You’re dangerous but I’m game for this and I don’t kiss ’cause that could get cankerous white girls complaining the sun is cancerous pull my dick out and I done caused the damn eclipse</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I guess that’s as good of a place as any to leave this post. Thanks to everyone who helped make 2019 as excellent as it was, and here’s to an even better 2020. Much love.</p>
        ]]>
      </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
      <title>Burned Out</title>
      <id>blog/burnout/index.html</id>
      <link href='blog/burnout/index.html'/>
      <published>2019-12-10T00:46:00Z</published>
      <updated>2019-12-10T00:46:00Z</updated>

      <content type="html">
        <![CDATA[
        <p>Two days ago, I made some drastic measures — withdrawing from almost all facets of my online life. This has probably come as a surprise to many, and I feel like I owe some of you an explanation.</p>
<p>The short of it is that I’m tired out. Really fucking burned out. It’s sort of a weird thing to say, given that I’ve been retired for the last two years, but nevertheless, it’s true, somehow.</p>
<p>Since I first left Munich, I’ve had this unbearable weight on shoulders — exhaustion. I’d been couch surfing for three months, meeting up with nerds I’d met on the internet, and building cool things with them. I was <a href="https://isovector.github.io/erdos/">emulating my hero Paul Erdos</a>, who spent his life traveling and working with first-rate mathematicians. While a few of my hosts were excellent, first-rate engineers, most of them were not. What was once my joy, this Haskell stuff became blasee. I was hoping to rediscover my love of programming, but instead found myself arguing with people who just seemed unable to see the bigger picture, and teaching them everything I knew. Each and every one of them was a good person, but they simply weren’t the people I was looking for.</p>
<p>All of this culminated in London. The stress of nonstop traveling, combined with attempting to give an impromptu talk, at a conference where I was sure to meet an ex-girlfriend, that I still had feelings for, who clearly didn’t want to see me, was simply too much. I collapsed, and spent a night genuinely worried that I was on the absolute verge of death.</p>
<p>It wasn’t a great experience.</p>
<p>This last year has been a hard one. I found myself trapped in an emotionally draining relationship, and set my sights on doing work as a refuge. What began as <a href="https://github.com/polysemy-research/polysemy">a fun foray into some interesting questions</a> turned into a compulsion. I spent ten hours a day working on this research that not only did anyone understand, but also told me could never possibly work. I gave my heart and soul to a community that just didn’t seem to care.</p>
<p>Compassion and patience were my answer. To just keep reiterating my points, to always take the high road, to continue believing their attitudes stemmed from ignorance and not from malice. And it worked. Minds started changing, slowly but surely. I moved the discussion from “it’s impossible” to “ok, but how do I do this?” But every step was a fight, and soon all of the technical bits were finished. All that was left were the politics. My soul is truly that of an engineer, not a politician. It stopped being fun, and I felt like I was trying to help a group of people who truly were disinterested in my help. It left a sour taste in my mouth.</p>
<p>Then there was the <a href="/blog/gatekept/">Imperial fiasco</a>. For eight months they jerked me around, continually setting me up just to knock me down again. Eventually I did get my foot in the door, but by that point it was too late. I was no longer enthusiastic about the project, and I realized that my self-respect was more important to me than any pedigree they could lend to my name.</p>
<p>After all, turning down Imperial is almost as good as attending Imperial.</p>
<p>To make matters worse, I was also <a href="https://www.patreon.com/designandinterpretation">writing a book</a> on the same topics. It had been going slowly, mostly due to the burnout, but also due to the fact that I no longer have any skin in the game. I just don’t care if other people are writing good, maintainable software. <em>Who gives a shit?</em> But I promised myself that I’d work on it every day, and that I wouldn’t quit until it was published. And so I worked on it, true to my word, and hated every moment of it.</p>
<p>Software has stopped being fun for me. I’ve stopped learning, and instead have found myself in the role of an expert, which is nice, but the day-to-day feels too much like resting on my laurels, rent seeking, and answering the same questions day in and out. There’s not currently any joy in it.</p>
<p>Forcing myself to do more of it, out of some misplaced sense of identity, is clearly an aggressively unhealthy response to the situation. So, I just pulled out. I dropped my committee duties, rescinded my verbal agreement to a new job, gave up ownership of my programming project, announced that I’m no longer working on the book, and unsubscribed from every piece of programming media I could find. I need a clean break from it all, before I collapse again.</p>
<p>So instead, what? Honestly I’m not sure. But I’m hiding away in southeast Asia, learning new things and playing lots of music and doing lots of writing. And just generally doing stuff that feels good for the soul. I don’t know what healing is going to look like, or how long it’s going to take, but I’m not too worried. I’ll pull through; I always do. In the meantime, don’t expect much output on my end.</p>
<p>To everyone who has extended kind words, asking about me, thank you so much. I don’t have the energy to reply to you individually yet, but please know that I’ve read all of it, and appreciate each and every word. I love you all.</p>
        ]]>
      </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
      <title>Making and Spending Money</title>
      <id>blog/making-and-spending-money/index.html</id>
      <link href='blog/making-and-spending-money/index.html'/>
      <published>2019-11-12T23:14:00Z</published>
      <updated>2019-11-12T23:14:00Z</updated>

      <content type="html">
        <![CDATA[
        <p>I read an excellent blog post yesterday: <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/slatestarcodex/comments/duv1x8/making_money_isnt_magic/">Making Money Isn’t Magic</a>. It’s a great look at strategies for generating cash. Several techniques that won’t get you rich quick, though they will clearly work given a year or two of preparation. And significantly less lead time if you come ready.</p>
<p>Anyway, this got me thinking about my approach to this money stuff — which is notably different than how most people seem to think about it. My family is aggressively the upper middle class. With the notable exception of a failed startup in the extended parts of the tree, every one of them works as a professional or at a not-for-profit. You name it, we got it. From engineering to law to medicine to police to university professor — my family has flourished by having a job and working for the man.</p>
<p>Tried and true, it’s a strategy that’s been working for us for generations — at least as far back in the lineage as I’m privy to.</p>
<p>With the exception of my uncle, there isn’t a shred of entrepreneurship anywhere in the blood. My family is particularly risk averse; not only in business, but also in temperament. The emphasis is and has always been on credentials and a good job with a good salary. Although no one would explicitly say it, I suspect they equate a hard day’s work with both financial success and with honesty. To make money without exchanging it for time at a linear rate is both unfathomable and immoral.</p>
<p>Me, I’m much more of a libertarian than my family is. Its the source of no end of (mostly) good-hearted ribbing at the Maguire-family dinner table. I believe that money is just and foremost a measure of value. We exchange money for things we care about more than money — otherwise tautologically we’d hold on to it.</p>
<p>If someone is willing to give you money, it means you are creating value for them one way or another. They must think it’s worthwhile. This was the first big hurdle in debugging my brain about money — and huge shoutout to <a href="https://joshkaufman.net/">Josh Kaufman</a> for spending an evening setting me straight. Where things go weirder is on the other side of that transaction. Just because someone is willing to pay me to do something doesn’t mean I must do it. Even if the money is really good.</p>
<p>Last week I stopped responding to a recruiter trying to place me at a job offering me half a million in salary. Tempting to be sure, but he got miffed when I asked to use Hangouts instead of doing a phone call. I don’t have a phone, you see. But instead of just saying yes, he got grumpy. I’m not sure if he’s lazy, inflexible, or incompetent, but either way, it reflects poorly on both him and the company. I don’t need the money, so why would I subject myself to that kind of an environment?</p>
<p>My rule of thumb is that the more a job pays, the more unpleasant it is. This is not a deep truth about the universe, but it seems to be a good heuristic nevertheless. If a job were good, they wouldn’t need to pay people so much to fill it.</p>
<p>Clearly this company thinks I’m worth the pay, but are <em>they</em> worth <em>my</em> time and attention?</p>
<p>The interesting thing about knowing how to make money is that it makes you care less about it. Once it stops being hard, you can just stay prepared and make some whenever you need it. I can’t generate $10k overnight, but certainly could in two weeks — probably in one if my life depended on it.</p>
<p>This is unfathomable to most people in most of the world. Nobody in Ottawa would give me an apartment because I didn’t have any “steady income.” They didn’t care that I could pay the entire lease upfront, nor that I <em>actually offered</em> it to them to get around the income “issue!”</p>
<p>There’s an excellent quote in the Elon Musk biography:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Every time Tesla interacted with Detroit it received a reminder of how the once-great city had been separated from its own can-do culture. Tesla tried to lease a small office in Detroit. The costs were incredibly low compared with space in Silicon Valley, but the city’s bureaucracy made getting just a basic office an ordeal. The building’s owner wanted to see seven years of audited financials from Tesla, which was still a private company. Then the building owner wanted about two years’ worth of advanced rent. Tesla had about $50 million in the bank and could have bought the building outright. “In Silicon Valley, you say you’re backed by a venture capitalist, and that’s the end of the negotiation,” Tarpenning said. “But everything was like that in Detroit.”</p>
<p>Ashlee Vance, Elon Musk: Tesla, SpaceX, and the Quest for a Fantastic Future</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Money really and truly is just a number in a computer somewhere — especially in the 21st century. So long as you have enough runway to last you until you’re prepared to make more, you’re fine. But this is where it breaks down for most people. Most people are under prepared and their spending is too damn high!</p>
<p>A few years before I retired (but after I had decided to,) I started judging amounts by how much of my retirement they would consume. After a few months of living well in Lithuania, I calculated that I could live on $25 a day, housing included. That meant every $25 I spent, I got one fewer day of <em>not working.</em> $25 doesn’t buy a hell of a lot; it doesn’t buy a thing! It’s meaningless psychologically, but my brain sure as heck understands the value of having a day off. And I’d gladly buy a <em>lot</em> of days off at $25 a piece!</p>
<p>I found myself doing the math before every transaction — and, almost always — realized it wasn’t a worthwhile trade. That’s a powerful technique they don’t teach you in school.</p>
<p>I’m not saying you too should measure your life in terms of $25-per-day retirement, but by god, measure it in terms of something meaningful to you! If you’re saving money, what are you saving it for? If you don’t set a concrete, specific goal, you’ll never get there — forever making money you don’t need to spend on things you don’t really want.</p>
<p>Is “owning” a mortgaged house really worth the down payment and mandated years of slavery to pay off the rest of it? I’m not so sure, but I do know how much life you can buy for that same down payment. And I guarantee you that the grind to make the mortgage payment gets in the way of a lot of preparation to make money.</p>
<p>Out of all my professional engineering friends, I’m probably the poorest of all of them, likely by a factor of 5x or more. But I haven’t worked a job in two years. I travel all around the world on a whim, and spend month at a time living on tropical islands and doing scuba everyday. Amazingly, despite this, my bank account has the same number it showed the day I quit working.</p>
<p>I don’t live off the interest or any “safe” strategy like that — I just have lots of time and energy to create. And that’s the kind of stuff that people find valuable and are willing to pay me for. Is it a lot of money? No, it works out to about minimum wage, but that pays for rent, food, travel, and diving vacations. Crucially, it’s not a minimum wage that I need to spend 40 hours a week earning.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, every time I go to visit my professional friends, I’m struck by <em>just how miserable</em> they are. And what’s worse is they don’t even notice it — not even after breaking into tears at the mall food court. But this is a choice that they are making, every day. It’s the safe path that I inherited from my upper-middle class upbringing, and likely they from theirs. But all you need to do is pay rent and food. Literally all the rest is non-essential bonus stuff.</p>
<p>Find a way to take care of that part, and then spend a lot of time thinking about what you want your life to look like. How much money do you need to make that happen?</p>
<p>One common objection I hear to this is “but I don’t know, so I will keep making money until I figure it out.” This would indeed be a good strategy if it weren’t based on a fundamental misunderstanding. Deciding what you want your life to look like is scary as hell (“what if I get it wrong?”) and so defaulting to the status quo is a defense mechanism.</p>
<p>Instead, we must ask ourselves whether we want the rest of your life to look like it does now. We must come to grips with the fact that this is all it’s ever going to be, unless we change it. This is all we get. Lets try our best not to squander it.</p>
        ]]>
      </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
      <title>The Mechanics of Writing a Book</title>
      <id>blog/book-mechanics/index.html</id>
      <link href='blog/book-mechanics/index.html'/>
      <published>2019-11-03T12:56:00Z</published>
      <updated>2019-11-03T12:56:00Z</updated>

      <content type="html">
        <![CDATA[
        <p>One of my core tenets is that processes are much more important than results. A well-executed result is good for me, but a good, reified process is good for the world. Far too much human ingenuity is spent figuring out how someone else made something cool, and we’d all be better off if we could just communicate those things openly.</p>
<p>If you haven’t heard the good word, I’m actively writing a book called <a href="https://www.patreon.com/designandinterpretation">Design and Interpretation of Haskell Programs</a>. It’s about writing good and robust software in Haskell, something that is regrettably not yet very well known. But don’t worry, I’m not going to talk about Haskell today. I want to talk about how I go about writing a book.</p>
<h2 id="where-does-a-book-come-from">Where Does a Book Come From?</h2>
<p>I write practical nonfiction. My impetus to write nonfiction comes from spending a lot of time thinking about just how frustrating life today is, and how it doesn’t need to be that way. Paul Graham has a quote on this that I really like and identify with:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Live in the future, then build what’s missing.</p>
<p>-Paul Graham</p>
</blockquote>
<p>For me, writing books isn’t about <em>building,</em> but about <em>bridging.</em> In technology, most of our problems were solved 30 years ago, but nobody knows about it because minds are slow to change and academics are particularly bad at communicating. As such, my work doesn’t contribute anything new, it just synthesizes other people’s work into one place.</p>
<p>This is great news, because it means that I can just spend lots of time reading weird, obscure things, and keep track of which ones feel like they’re onto something. I’m very familiar with the day-to-day workings of my field, and by paying attention to research that tackles the everyday problems, that’s most of the work right there.</p>
<p>At the end of the day, a book comes from wanting the world to be different, and, in particular, knowing in what way you’d like it to be different. If your personality is like mine, this is sufficient motivation. Knowing the right answer and feeling like society is to sluggish to get there on its own makes it feel like writing this book is a <em>responsibility</em> that you have to the world.</p>
<p>If you are going into this project to get rich, <em>stop right now.</em> It’s a) the wrong motivation, because you probably won’t, and b) going to be very obvious to all of your readers. Audiences can smell a cash grab a mile away, and aren’t likely to reward you with their hard-earned cash.</p>
<h2 id="getting-started">Getting Started</h2>
<p>I begin by identifying a theme for the book. Roughly, what is it going to be about? This thing should be the length of a subtitle, for example “type level programming in Haskell” or “a guide to building robust software.” Having a theme helps identify who would be interested in such a thing, and roughly what sorts of things you should be writing about (which is less obvious that it sounds!)</p>
<p>This gets me thinking about the people that I know personally. Are any of them the target audience? I’ll make a list of people I know who might be interested, and then roughly estimate how much they know about the topic at hand. I am always looking for someone I know personally who is a) smart, b) interested, and c) average in their knowledge on the subject.</p>
<p>After identifying one to three of these people, I’ll go and explicitly say to them “hey, I’m thinking about writing a book on topic X — how likely would you be to buy such a book?” I will iterate on the theme, and the people until I find a combination that evokes enthusiasm.</p>
<p>Enthusiasm is the key. I am looking for sentiments along the lines of “thank god, I’ve been waiting for someone to write that,” or “I didn’t know I wanted that, but now I can’t wait,” or, “shut up and take my money!” If you can evoke that sort of response, and have no reason to believe that your friend is alone in that opinion, then congratulations. You’ve found a market for your book.</p>
<p>It’s important to target a friend who is in the average understanding. If you find someone who is far below average, your book is going to need to spend a lot of time covering first principles. If they’re far above average, the pool of people who will buy your book is going to be unreasonably small.</p>
<h2 id="the-target-audience">The Target Audience</h2>
<p>This enthusiastic friend of yours is your greatest asset in writing a book. You are writing this book <em>for them,</em> and for no one else. The goal is to take your friend, at their current level of understanding, and gently lead them to your point of view. Doing so requires a deep understanding of what you want to teach, but it requires a <em>deeper</em> understanding of the way that they see the world. It’s okay — and natural — to be a little fuzzy on what you’re going to write about. That part gets solved by actually writing it. But you need to understand your friend well enough that you can frame the problem and motivate the solution in language that they can understand.</p>
<h2 id="promise-yourself-to-get-it-done">Promise Yourself to Get It Done</h2>
<p>I always make a promise to myself that if I’m going to do this work, I’m not going to waste my time by <em>not finishing it.</em> That’s not to say I should sink my costs if the book truly isn’t very good, but it’s a good defense against akrasia.</p>
<p>This comes in two flavors. The first is that while I’m committed to finishing the project, I need to work on it <em>every single day.</em> “Working” here is intentionally defined very loosely. Fixing a typo counts as doing work. Writing a single sentence, or editing a paragraph for flow counts as doing work. Obviously, writing significant amounts of prose also counts as doing work. So long as my document isn’t in exactly the same state as it was 24 hours ago, it counts.</p>
<p>The psychology here is that projects that are always being worked on are eventually finished. But, it’s an acknowledgment that life can often get in the way of the best laid plans. And so, we define progress by input, not by output. So long as you do <em>something, anything,</em> you haven’t broken the streak.</p>
<p>Having a low barrier on this front is amazingly powerful. Often I’ll find myself in bed getting ready to sleep, and realize “oh shit, I didn’t work on the book yet today!” My initial reaction will be “eh… fuck it.” But having such a low barrier to progress means I’ll feel like a piece of shit if I’m <em>so lazy</em> that I can’t manage to pull open my laptop, write a single sentence, and then put it away again. It’s the inertia the counts, not the speed.</p>
<p>Working on it every day is a good way to prevent the accidental death of your project. But it’s not a good strategy if this thing you’re creating <em>truly isn’t worth finishing.</em> For that, I also write a quick document describing under which circumstances I’m allowed to quit, and when. For example, on my last book, I wrote this:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>When To Quit</p>
<p>There will be no quitting, unless another book comes out before this, also targeted explicitly at type-level programming in Haskell, which is judged by me to be superior.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Notice how clear that is. It gives an explicit stop condition — someone writing a better book, <em>as judged by me.</em> In fact, while writing my book, someone else did publish first, but after skimming a few chapters, it was clearly an inferior product. Rather than let it get me down, I realized that neither my mission nor the world had changed in light of this other book, and so I should keep my head down.</p>
<p>And the market agreed with me. To date I’ve sold at least 20x more copies! The power of strategic perseverance is a powerful one,</p>
<h2 id="work-on-philosophy-first">Work on Philosophy First</h2>
<p>Spend a lot of time writing the philosophy of the way you see the world. Describe the problems you see with great anguish. Really sell just how painful this experience is, and try to motivate a world in which we haven’t already internalized this pain. How if your solution were already the status quo, we’d never think about trying the things we’re doing now. Rhetoric is a powerful tool here.</p>
<p>Your argument doesn’t need to be technical. Not yet. All it needs to do is be strongly motivating. You need to convince your reader that this problem is worth solving, and, by extension, that your book is worth reading.</p>
<p>Throughout the writing process, I will often finish five or six chapters along these lines. Few if any of them end up in the final print. But the exercise is not for naught; by expounding on these issues you will clarify exactly what problems you see, you will discover a natural structure for the book, and you will come up with good material for copy.</p>
<p>The philosophy is much easier for people to understand than the technical solutions. The latter require significantly more attention, and so by making the philosophy as persuasive as possible, you are readying your reader for the difficult tasks ahead. In my experience, very few nonfiction books take the motivation aspect seriously enough. With so many excellent books out there, it takes quite a lot to convince me that <em>this one in particular</em> is worth reading.</p>
<p>Nailing the motivation is by far the hardest part of the process. So spend lots of time waxing poetically on the way the world should look. Tackle it from as many different angles as possible. If possible, show that several real problems all share the same structure, and thus that your one solution would solve all of them simultaneously.</p>
<h2 id="test-your-assumptions">Test Your Assumptions</h2>
<p>Take two of your best motivating pieces, and start rolling with them. Find a relatable example, show how it’s a problem with traditional methods, and do a case study of applying your technique to it. You don’t need to spend a lot of time on this, just enough to convince yourself — and an audience — that everything works as you say it does.</p>
<p>Write prose around the example, explaining every piece in great detail. Assume the reader knows exactly what your target audience friend does, and explain the bits that you would explain to your friend. Walk them through your thought process, about when this technique can be expected to work, and good heuristics for how to use it.</p>
<p>Tackle two of these case studies, ideally two that are in very different domains, which can showcase different aspects of the solution.</p>
<p>Compile the two case studies and two best pieces of philosophy into a single document, and spend an hour or two polishing it. When you’re done, here comes the scary part: sharing it. You need to distribute this document of yours widely. Make it freely available in the circles that your ideal readership hangs out in. See how people respond to it. Make the necessary changes in order to convince them that your nascent book is worthwhile.</p>
<p>If you’ve done your homework and made a compelling case, I suspect the audience will be supportive. But there’s always the chance they aren’t, and this too is valuable. Honestly consider their concerns. If you can’t convince your core audience to get excited about this thing, you’re probably not going to convince a wider audience either. If it seems like the problems are solvable, go back to the drawing board and try again. Otherwise, now might be a good time to cut your losses.</p>
<hr />
<p>This is about as far as I’ve gotten in my new book, so it’s as much as I’ve been reminded about. More to come as I get further in.</p>
        ]]>
      </content>
    </entry>
</feed>

