<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns='http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom' xmlns:g='http://base.google.com/ns/1.0'>
  <title>We Can Solve This</title>
  <updated>2023-10-30T13:55:00Z</updated>
  <author><name>Sandy Maguire</name></author>
  <id>http://sandymaguire.me</id>
  <link rel='self' href='atom.xml'/>

    <entry>
      <title>Certainty by Construction: Done!</title>
      <id>blog/certainty-by-construction/index.html</id>
      <link href='blog/certainty-by-construction/index.html'/>
      <published>2023-10-30T13:55:00Z</published>
      <updated>2023-10-30T13:55:00Z</updated>

      <content type="html">
        <![CDATA[
        <p>Happy days and happy news: it’s done.</p>
<center>
<a href="https://leanpub.com/certainty-by-construction"><img src="/cbc.png" alt="Certainty by Construction"></a>
</center>
<p>After a year of work, I’m <em>thrilled</em> to announce the completion my new book, <a href="https://leanpub.com/certainty-by-construction">Certainty by Construction</a>.</p>
<p>Certainty by Construction is a book on doing mathematics and software design in the proof assistant Agda, which is the language Haskell wants to be when it grows up. The book is part Agda primer, introduction to abstract algebra, and algorithm design manual, with a healthy dose of philosophy mixed in to help build intuition.</p>
<p>If you’re the sort of person who would like to learn more math (including all the proof burden), and see how to apply it to writing real software, I think you’d groove on this book. If it sounds up your alley, I’d highly encourage you to <a href="https://leanpub.com/certainty-by-construction">give it a read</a>.</p>
<p>I’m not much on social media these days, but if you are, I’d really appreciate a signal boost on this announcement! Thanks to everyone for their support and understanding over the last year. I love you all!</p>
<p><a href="https://leanpub.com/certainty-by-construction">Go cop Certainty by Construction!</a></p>
        ]]>
      </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
      <title>2022 Recap</title>
      <id>blog/2022-recap/index.html</id>
      <link href='blog/2022-recap/index.html'/>
      <published>2023-01-04T00:32:00Z</published>
      <updated>2023-01-04T00:32:00Z</updated>

      <content type="html">
        <![CDATA[
        <p>2022 is coming to a close, which means it’s time for my annual look back at the year, telling the stories and coming to realize that I didn’t accomplish many of the things I said I was going to. But that’s OK; hope springs eternal. Maybe next year! More on that in a bit.</p>
<p>We rung in the new year doing fondue with a small group of friends. The vibe was magical and really felt like the GLOBAL PANDEMIC was over. We put down the quiet evening to being old, not to being unable to go hard. It was lovely. The morning after we started a new new years tradition, nursing our hangovers with steam-it-yourself dim sum. Strongly recommended.</p>
<p>A week later, Erin and I headed off to Mexico. I don’t exactly remember why; maybe it was just to get out of the Canadian winter or something cliche. We went to Sayulita — which is a bit of a meme town in my family — and spent the week eating tacos, hanging out on the beach, and surfing. Well at least, that was the plan. Instead, we both got aggressive norovirus infections and the trip was mostly spent in the bathroom. But we also heard the most amazing family fight across the open air (“MOM! YOU BIT ME IN THE NECK. WHAT THE HELL?”). It was nice to escape Canada, and also nice to come back, which is about the best you can hope for in a trip.</p>
<p>While in Mexico, I set off on my “review 52 papers” project, and spent like ten hours of the vacation working through some gnarly math. It was great, and I started learning the Agda programming language in a serious manner. This turned into wanting to write it myself, which turned into needing to build all my own tools, which turned into <code>cornelis</code> — my most successful open-source project to date. That was cool, and I got pretty good at Agda by the end of the year. More on that later.</p>
<p>I had been secretly planning to create a podcast for the last few months, and this project finally got rolling in January. I researched and interviewed people in my little programming community, seeding the conversation with “what are you better at than anyone else here?” and seeing where that lead to. I did four episodes, and felt like I was really hitting my stride by the end. But the process was more energy than I wanted to put in, and quickly burned out on the idea. The interviewing and hanging out with people was fun, but the preparation and editing wasn’t. Eventually I hired an old friend as an editor, which dramatically improved the situation, but it wasn’t rewarding enough to pursue further.</p>
<p>As part of my yearly goal to get fit, Erin convinced me I should do <a href="http://www.c25k.com/">Couch to 5k</a> — a 9 week running program to turn a non-runner into someone who runs 5ks. In my case, it was only a single 5k, because I did it with bad shoes and hurt my knees or something. I never ended up loving running, but it was nice to have done and kind of fun to get sweaty.</p>
<p>Erin on the other hand, decided to run a 10k race, so we headed to Vancouver for the weekend and she crushed it, placing as the third fastest woman in <em>the entire city.</em> My job was to be there and cheer, which I did with great relish and talent.</p>
<p>All this time, I had secretly been preparing a secret: engagement! But it turns out it’s hard to charter a boat in February in Canada without the weather destroying your plans while your partner is in law school with a very busy schedule AND keep the whole thing a secret. It didn’t work, so instead I opted to take her out to a nice place for a picnic. After a nice picnic, we jointly decided it wasn’t a sufficiently good engagement, so I gracefully went back to the drawing board, and bided my time.</p>
<p>Instead, I came up with a much better engagement, but it required doing ARTS AND CRAFTS. You wouldn’t expect it could take multiple professional printing houses several weeks and several attempts to print 120 sheets of paper, but there you have it. You can pay people to do a job, but you can’t pay them to care. The flowers needed to be delayed <em>four times</em> because they were the only people who seemed capable of doing the thing they advertise doing professionally. I ended up doing my ARTS AND CRAFTS at Staples, by hand, in a FURY of anger and speed, because they somehow lost my job and asked for my help in getting everything cut. Still charged me full price though :)</p>
<p>Nevertheless, it was worth it. Erin loved the ARTS AND CRAFTS and we jointly agreed it was a much better engagement than the previous attempt, because this time it caught! I had become a betrothed man!</p>
<p>Our time in Victoria was numbered. Erin was only there for law school, which was about to finish, and I was only there for Erin. During the last few months, I had put together a local functional programming community out of nothing but elbow grease and bullying people to come. It was really paying off, with nearly ten excited members coming regularly. BUT THEN WE LEFT TOWN and I think it imploded. Oh well. Good practice for next time.</p>
<p>On my last day or so, my friend Mike The Crane Operator took me up the famous crane. I don’t have much to say about this other than it was one of the highlights of the year (but not as much of a highlight as getting engaged, he said wisely.) Thanks Mike The Crane Operator!</p>
<p>Then it was time to set sail on adventure. Both literally and figuratively, but only if you count the literally part a few days later. Erin and I flew to New York as a staging ground before our Grand Tour across Europe. But first we had to get to New York, which involved going through Calgary. We were flying at the end of the month, and while Erin got her boarding card no problem, mine continued to say “unable to issue boarding card, please speak to an agent.” You see, I’m cursed when it comes to technology and bureaucracy and <em>especially</em> technology in the service of bureacracy.</p>
<p>The issue was that I was assigned the dreaded SSSS status, which is short for something along the lines of “you’re going to have a really bad time.” Quad-S status means your suitcase gets unpacked at every security checkpoint and everything gets scanned for bombs. You have to take off your shoes and your pants and submit to cavity searches while they go through your email accounts. And worse, this is not just when you go through security; it’s every time you go through security, which they make sure happens along every leg of the trip. Just in case the last guys missed something, I guess.</p>
<p>Thankfully I do all my seditious activities somewhere other than my cavities, so despite the annoyances, we made it to NYNY just fine. We were met there by my old friend Ariel, whom we’d given permission to book us fun things without asking first. He took us to a great comedy show and an… “alternative” hipster music thing, all the time while speeding around town at speeds that shouldn’t have been possible on legs the size of his.</p>
<p>And then it was time for the cruise ship. And Oh My God. We were clearly not the target audience for the thing. It was twelve long days of crossing the Atlantic, without booze or anything fun to do or anyone interesting to meet. But I have <a href="/blog/cruising-facade/">written about this before.</a></p>
<p>The cruise ship dropped us off roughly in London, where we stretched our legs, appreciated how young people could be, spent some quality time with Erin’s parents, got yelled at by an Italian man named Luigi, and went to a great play set in — and physically located in — a court room.</p>
<p>We wanted to take the train to France but it’s wildly expensive so instead we took a Ryanair flight for £6 headed to Tours. We left for the airport with plenty of time, but the bus didn’t come, and then we had to make a MAD AIRPORT DASH. Except I didn’t take out my liquids so my bag went for secondary screening by people who gave no fucks about efficiency. Erin went ahead to try and hold the plane, but she texted me saying “sweet lord it’s a hundred BILLION miles so you should probably run.” My bags finally cleared security and I started running, and she was right because it was like a five minute run all the way through the winding duty-free store.</p>
<p>Of course, we made it to the gate long before boarding started.</p>
<p>We arrived in Tours and thought it would be nice to walk from the airport into town. As soon as we got outside, it was scorching, like 30C+! Realizing we were now in the Mediterranean, I changed into my shorts behind a gas station, and left the jeans and coat behind, ready for this new tropical paradise.</p>
<p>Tours was pretty OK. We got Ethiopian food and Erin found a nice riverside festival with a great-but-not-at-all-tight jazz band. We settled in with some beers and had a magical night, but realized Tours was not for us. So we booked a train ride down to Bordeaux, and bought charcuterie for the trip! The French train system is marvelous: smooth, clean, quiet, timely. Eventually we got into the charcuterie and all of the French people gave us surreptitious glances, as if we were doing something egregious. We were never sure if it was our choice in charcuterie, our brazen technique, or maybe that you’re just not supposed to eat charcuterie on a train. It will forever remain a mystery.</p>
<p>Bordeaux is much more happening than Tours, so we decided to go on a tour of Bordeaux. Unfortunately, most of France is neither the Mediterranean nor is it tropical, and I spent the day regretting having thrown away all of my warm clothing behind a gas station. I was rocking a tank top and sandals and my god was it cold. To warm up after the tour, we ducked into a small cafe and I had an embarrassing experience trying to order food in French. Eventually we got it settled, and set up for some laptop time upstairs. A random stranger in the cafe recognized my Haskell sticker, and then recognized me! Tomas turned out to be super cool, and we set up some time the next day to nerd out without our partners. The next day was also cool, so Tomas and Kayleigh invited me and Erin to a cheese restaurant for dinner, which was ALSO cool so then they invited us to come on a roadtrip to the beach with them. One marvelous and extremely sunburned day later, we returned, searched for after-sun, and retired, patting ourselves on the back for a job well done.</p>
<p>Erin and I didn’t love France, and we didn’t know where to go, so we hopped on the cheapest Ryanair flight we could find, which took us to Agadir, Morocco. We had talked about finding a surf/yoga retreat in Morocco and so this seemed like a good move. We crossed the Moroccan border, and learned the customs agent also didn’t love France. He was very vocal about it. One chatty cab drive later, we found ourselves in the middle of nowhere Tamaraght, Morocco, across the street from a carpet shop and a cafe owned by a seven-year old. The place is a surf town, but for some stupid reason, we didn’t lean in, instead, doing… well, I’m not quite sure.</p>
<p>The coolest thing about Tamaraght is that it’s a dry town: there is no alcohol to be found. I have a complicated relationship with alcohol, and it was really cool to find a place that just didn’t have any. Alcohol is so ubiquitous in Canada that I’d never imagined you could just <em>not.</em> So instead everyone just smoked a lot of hash. Humans gonna be humans I guess.</p>
<p>Erin wanted to go on a tour in the desert, and we figured we’d both have more fun if I didn’t come since I’d be a grumpy Gertrude and Erin would worry about whether or not I was having fun. Avoiding it dodged both problems, so while she and the ENTIRE HOSTEL all went for a week-long trip to the desert, I instead ate Moroccan tacos and headed for the next surf-town over, Taghazout. Taghazout was cool; I stayed at a coworking space and met a bunch of cool people, including Josh who had spent the last evening waterboarding anyone who was interested (and it sounds to have been quite popular!) Finding some other digital nomads who were traveling but not there to party was good for the soul, and helped me realize just how scroogey I was being for the whole trip.</p>
<p>I reunited with my One True Love (Erin) in Marrakesh, where we were planning to meet up, but then randomly stumbled across one another in the medina. What a sight for sore eyes! The trip that morning to the big city had been something; I took a shared taxi to the bus station with some other strangers I met on the street, ended up paying about $1 for it, and then took a six hour bus ride sitting next to a woman who spent the entire trip sending a <em>lot</em> of voice messages. I was annoyed about it until I remembered that 30% of women in Morocco are illiterate, which helped me empathize. This woman just wanted to talk to her friends during the long bus ride.</p>
<p>Erin had picked up some stomach bug while out in the desert, and so I did a lot of Marrakesh on my own, involving getting abducted by a Swiss woman who tricked me into thinking she spoke English, and then used the <em>driving</em> directions for us to <em>walk</em> around the Medina. I was hoping for a quick beer downstairs, and instead got taken around ugly parts of the city for an hour before I saw an exit to escape. Yeesh. Erin and I then escaped the medina and went for McDonalds, which was exactly what we needed. Moroccan food just isn’t “all that.”</p>
<p>We were killing time until I had to be in Zurich for a Haskell conference, and that time was now upon us. So we Ryanaired our way up to Geneva, and had a magical afternoon lying in the grass, exploring green spaces, and listening to an amazing piano player practicing in the park. I didn’t know CERN was in Geneva, and so I didn’t go, and it’s one of my biggest regrets of the year. Alas. Also there was a STRANGE MAN who was staying in our hostel room. He kept coming into the room, and then turning right back around. Odd. Peculiar. Who is this mystery man?</p>
<p>Geneva gave way to Zurich, which enamored us both. There’s such a stark contrast between Zurich and Marrakesh. In Switzerland, there are huge, free, publicly-available drinking fountains everywhere. The cities are gorgeous and green. The people are quiet and respectful. Contrast this to dusty Morocco where you will die if you are not constantly drinking bottled water while you’re being harassed by merchants (and lusty men, if you’re Erin!)</p>
<p>We had planned to stay in a hostel in Zurich, but something went wrong last minute, and I decided that my company could afford putting us up in a nice hotel for the week. Exceptionally good idea on my part. I spent the weekend at the hackathon, and brought Erin out a few times to meet some of the nerds. She was pleasantly — and thankfully — impressed after me building up the general character of your average Haskell programmer for years.</p>
<p>While in Zurich, I had the pleasure of reacquainting with Farhad Mehta, one of the organizers of Zurihac, and a genuinely delightful human. He suggested we spend a week doing a study-group, and I jumped on the opportunity. We spent a week doing Agda and Isabelle, punctuated by my living arrangement’s shower grading me on my water usage, many noodle breaks, and a fondue vending machine. Only in Switzerland!</p>
<p>Zurich lead to Vienna where I caught up with my old friend Anna and bought Erin some cursed new headphones (though I didn’t know they were cursed when I bought them.) Aching for some culture, I headed off to a local jazz bar where I was treated to an <em>extremely intimate</em> concert of some bass player doing a set for his birthday with musicians in his life. It was a nice idea but everyone else there was in the show, and you can really only listen to so much jazz lead by the upright bass.</p>
<p>After a brief stint, I ended up in Budapest, intending to reunite with Erin, but she was trapped in Barcelona. So instead I went out on a pubcrawl with my roommate, and somehow got adopted by 15 Indians, none of whom knew one another. The pubcrawl was a bust, but my new friends were delightful.</p>
<p>Erin arrived at 5 in the morning after a CHAOTIC AIRPORT EXPERIENCE, so we took it easy for a few days. The week culminated in Budapest’s Turkish Baths, which are like a western swimming pool except literally a million times better. You can pick your desired temperature water in two-degree increments, and when you’re tired of being in the water, you can pick a sauna by how hot and how salty you want it to be. Truly a marvel of the modern world, even though nerds will tell me this stuff is ancient.</p>
<p>We took a delightful train ride down to Croatia, which I’m sure is a lovely place, but for me the charm was primarily the old man who complemented my new Birkenstocks (“not just a shoe for old men!” they told me) and the discovery that white noise helps adults sleep too. However, Split paled in comparison to Dubrovnik, where we accidentally found ourselves on a nude beach with THE LADS, met an Olympic swimmer, and almost died in the sun due to missing our bus home.</p>
<p>This whole time we had been meandering our way down to Greece, where Erin and I had signed up for a week-long sailing lesson on the Aegean sea. We finally got to Athens, where the airport experience was amazing, and where our hostel room burst open five minutes after we arrived at 3am when two keen and amorous youths made their way in, oblivious to our presence. After the whole thing was sorted, we did all the stuff you’re supposed to do in Athens like looking at old stuff and looking at other old stuff.</p>
<p>You’d think after the whole Greek economic thing that there would be lots of enterprising souls working the markets, but we found a disappointing lack of pandering Greek mythological merchandise. What a missed opportunity. We did, however, find a great t-shirt of Zeus as a hipster.</p>
<p>Other highlights of Greece: going ring shopping, getting stealth-drawn by my roommate, and visiting a “political party” where we hung from a ring on the ceiling and took turns showing off our best moves on the stripper pole.</p>
<p>Finally it was time to go SAILING. We took a (rather stressful, due to me getting us lost) ferry to Aegina where we met our crew for the week. Skipper John, salty Sven, and Douwe. The crew had evidently been assembled for Erin and my pleasure; Sven and Douwe were just there to get some paperwork stamped: they already knew perfectly well how to sail. We spent the week sailing around at INSANE SPEEDS which felt very fast indeed but instead were along the lines of 15km/h. On one particularly memorable night, we were night sailing without any wind. It was a gorgeous, starry evening, with nothing to do and nowhere to be. Thankfully our evening was rescued by Sven, who decided what the evening <em>really</em> needed was a loud, driving Eurotrace soundtrack.</p>
<p>While Douwe and Sven were nothing to write home about, meeting Skipper John was perhaps the highlight of my year. Skipper John has spent his entire life sailing around, a good chunk of it on the Mediterranean, and he has the mental health that comes hand-in-hand with a life lived simply but well. I hadn’t realized how atrocious my mental health had gotten during the pandemic. When I compared my mental well-being to other people, it felt like I was doing OK, but I wasn’t. I’m not much of a fatalist, but it seemed like the universe was conspiring to send me to spend a week with Skipper John. His unbridled enthusiasm for life was a stark contrast to my own, and I’m happy to say my life has changed for the better since having met him. Thank you, Skipper John, wherever you might be. Happy days; happy days.</p>
<p>Sailing was the end of our trip in Europe, and happy we’d left and even more happy to be leaving, Erin and I boarded a flight back to Canada. We found a temporary place to live while we house hunted. The place was a gorgeous, 28th floor apartment right on the north end of Vancouver’s downtown. The only problem was that it seemed like a huge scam. We were supposed to rent the place from Sasha, except that she didn’t own the place, her parents did, and she was renting it out while they were on vacation. It seemed too good to be true, which, as we learned, was what they thought about us too! “We just want to make sure you’re not the sort of people who are going to film a porno in our house” they commented when we met in person. Thankfully, both sides were delighted to learn the other consisted of good people, and thus we landed a swanky pad that would make any place we could actually afford under a lease pale in comparison.</p>
<p>There was a whirlwind trip through Toronto where we almost missed our flight, but ran through the airport and instead made it safely, crashing on Andrew’s couch when we arrived in Vancouver. Thanks mate!</p>
<p>Figuring we hadn’t had enough adventure as of late, Erin and I got tickets for the Vancouver Folk Fest which was pretty cool in that I got to see the New Pornographers. But really, I was exhausted and jet-lagged and just wanted to not go anywhere or do anything for a few weeks. So instead we took the bus up to Penticton to see our parents!!</p>
<p>Come late September, I realized my ongoing contract for 18 project days had begun the previous October, and it seemed embarrassing to let it linger for a whole year. So I got my act together and behaved like a proper business man, and finished the contract. Figuring I had completely blown my chance at getting hired back, I sent a professional-sounding “thank you” letter to the company. Oddly enough, they liked me enough to send back a “would you consider re-signing?” I checked to make sure they hadn’t said <em>resigning,</em> but no, everything was good!</p>
<p>Being back in Vancouver was really, <em>really</em> good. Erin and I found a place no problem, and carried a yellow couch across the city to furnish it. I had been hankering for a place to settle into since before the UNCERTAIN TIMES, and finally it felt like I was in a place I could do that. So instead I took the bus up to Penticton to see my dad <em>again!!</em></p>
<p>Which was really nice, actually. We got some quality, dedicated father/son bonding time in for the first time in over a decade, when we’d driven across Canada together. As I’ve gotten older and wiser, I’ve realized that my parents are too, and therefore it’s both important and relatively-urgent to prioritize seeing them. This wouldn’t be my last time seeing them this year!</p>
<p>Back in Vancouver, I was called up by EF, the startup accelerator firm which had caused me no small amount of stress the year before. But this time they wanted me to come to a nice dinner on their dime, and meet other cool people. I went, with trepidation, but had a surprisingly nice time. In fact, I met one <em>particularly</em> cool people, Lazar, with whom I’ve stayed in touch and who has grown to be a good friend.</p>
<p>The EF dinner reminded me that I wanted to go try to be a startup man. But EF told me they were full up, and that I should apply next round instead. One morning however, I found myself with spare energy, so I decided to apply. An hour later I was on the phone with EF, who were all of a sudden VERY KEEN to get me to move to Toronto in three days’ time. Which, if you remember from last year, seems to be their M.O. Erin and I had discussed the possibility, and she was OK with it if I was. Seeing as I was just getting settled into Vancouver, moving to Toronto seemed like it was right in the cards. EF forced me to buy a flight to YYZ before they’d send me the contract (WTF?). Thankfully my lawyer didn’t like the contract, and EF was unwilling to budge, so I didn’t end up moving to Toronto. Instead, EF went bankrupt a month later.</p>
<p>My neighborhood in Vancouver has a parkour gym just down the street. As a boy, I used to while away the time in Terrace BC by getting drunk and climbing buildings. Parkour seemed like the adult version of that very hobby, so I signed up for a trial month. It’s been life altering. I’ve never had fun doing exercise before, but parkour has changed that dramatically. All of a sudden I found myself going three, four times a week, just because it was fun to jump on/over things and to hang out with other people who also wanted to jump on/over things.</p>
<p>At some point during these months, I thought that I might have ADHD. I asked a doctor friend who said he “knew a sketchy guy” I could talk to about that. The sketchy guy called me in THAT EVENING for an EMERGENCY CONSULTATION, where I was asked all sorts of leading questions. When it was all over, in a left-field move that nobody could have predicted, the sketchy guy diagnosed me as having ADHD! It’s a bit of a sham because I was hoping to actually talk to someone about it, but instead managed to just get a prescription. That being said, the meds do seem to help, so maybe the sketchy guy isn’t as bad as he sounds. I have much more to say on this topic, but will put it into blog format some other time.</p>
<p>The year steadily marched on, unlike Erin, who steadily RAN. A marathon, that is. In the cold rain and snow, on the water, with a bone-chilling wind under <em>dry</em> circumstances, which it most certainly was not. I was the designated helper! My job was to drive around and make sure she had everything she needed. It was all going well until my phone died and I got lost and spent an hour driving around and very nearly missed her crossing the finish line. Thankfully I didn’t, and we are still happily engaged.</p>
<p>In November, I decided to do NaNoWriMo again, this time writing a math textbook. I succeeded with flying colors, and now have a (very) rough manuscript for another book. I plan to get it cleaned up in the next few months, so keep an attentive ear out for Sandy Maguire’s next flying-off-the-shelf best seller.</p>
<p>And that was pretty much the whole year, except for the Christmas fiasco where our flights got cancelled due to SNOW, and then our moms got sad, so we made lots of very-last-minute plans to not merely double-down on Christmas, but to <em>triple-down!</em> Like I said, I’m learning that family is much more important than I realized, and so I’m trying to do my best on that front. The drive up was terrifyingly low in visibility, and the resulting visit with an ominous prophecy, but otherwise, a spectacular cap off to the year.</p>
<p>One last thing! I bought a smart phone this year, and decided I wanted to take a daily selfie. That didn’t end up happening, but I did manage to take 225 photos. Now you can watch me age much faster than I actually age!</p>
<iframe width="485" height="863" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Y6rc4i4ZD_I" title="Sandy Takes a Selfie for a Year" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen>
</iframe>
<p>Thanks for a lovely year, 2022. See you all next time around.</p>
        ]]>
      </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
      <title>Exploring the Small Web</title>
      <id>blog/exploring-the-small-web/index.html</id>
      <link href='blog/exploring-the-small-web/index.html'/>
      <published>2022-08-31T19:24:00Z</published>
      <updated>2022-08-31T19:24:00Z</updated>

      <content type="html">
        <![CDATA[
        <p>A few weeks ago I wrote <a href="https://reasonablypolymorphic.com/blog/monotonous-web/">a little ditty</a> about how awful the internet has gotten, compared with the web of my youth. It garnered much more attention than my usual musings, and, as a result, <em>lots</em> of people chimed in. They shared with me great websites, sympathies, and <em>tons of unsolicted advice,</em> some of which actually happened to be good!</p>
<p>The good news: I was right — there still is tons of cool stuff on the web; it’s just hard to track down if you aren’t already in the know. This post collects all the stuff I’ve learned recently about finding cool stuff on the web in 2022.</p>
<h2 id="the-small-web">The Small Web</h2>
<p>Turns out there’s a name for this thing I’ve been seeking, it’s called the <a href="https://ar.al/2020/08/07/what-is-the-small-web/">small web</a>. The small web is a bunch of decentralized individuals who want to use the internet as a medium of self expression, where they can do weird and wonderful things. Like the <a href="https://solar.lowtechmagazine.com/2018/09/how-to-build-a-lowtech-website">low tech magazine</a>, whose website runs on solar panels and therefore might be offline. Or the guy who <a href="https://digdeeper.club/articles/browsers.xhtml">reviews the privacy policies of web browsers</a>. Or this dude who puts way <a href="https://coffeeadastra.com/2019/08/04/an-in-depth-analysis-of-coffee-filters-2/">more effort into making coffee</a> than has ever been justified. Or, how about a website dedicated to <a href="https://www.glorioustrainwrecks.com/">really awful video games?</a> Or, my personal favorite, the implementation of <a href="https://coral.shoes/nojs/">cooker clicker using no javascript</a>.</p>
<p>Amazing stuff, truly.</p>
<p>So, where does the small web hang out? A huge chunk of it is on <a href="https://neocities.org/browse">neocities</a> (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yahoo!_GeoCities">geocities</a> for the modern age.) Haphazardly clicking around on neocities, however, shows that <em>not everything on the small web is a gem!</em> There are a ton of angsty teens’ homepages. But that’s OK. We used to call being online <em>surfing the net</em> because you’d sometimes catch a cool wave, but most of the time be waiting around in the deep hoping for something interesting to come along. It was a lot more experimental, both on the side of content creators, and for consumers. On the consumer side, you spent a lot of time hitting the back button.</p>
<p>Per capita, there are far fewer teens hanging out on the <a href="https://tildeverse.org/members/">tildeverse</a>, which is allegedly a loose collection of old-school *nix hackers and academics. The stuff I found there is a little more polished, but <em>significantly less weird.</em> It’s the sort of place you find arcane technical blogs and professors’ websites which haven’t been updated since the 90s — that is, if you can find anything at all. Tilde sites are often a byproduct of being a user on a shared computing system, many of whom are members for reasons other than to host a website. I personally haven’t found much on the tildeverse, but several of my friends swear by it.</p>
<p>The reliably best stuff I’ve found, however, has all come from webrings, which are a bygone piece of web history/technology. A webring is a what it sounds like: a ring of websites, each with a “next website” link. Webrings are a great way of rapidly getting to bizarre parts of the internet; keep hitting “next” until something tickles your fancy. <a href="https://george.gh0.pw/">GEORGE</a> is a particularly weird one, and something that’s very clearly <em>not</em> an artifact of the boring-ass <a href="https://reasonablypolymorphic.com/blog/monotonous-web/">monotonous web.</a> I haven’t managed to find a webring-webring — that is, a webring whose constituent members are themselves webrings — which is very clearly a huge opportunity in the market. Someone get on it! However, I did find a <a href="https://indieweb.org/webring#Examples">list of webrings</a> which isn’t nearly as satisfying a concept.</p>
<h2 id="alternative-search-engines">Alternative Search Engines</h2>
<p>You probably already know about Google and Bing. And maybe even Yandex. Lots of people yelled at me in my last blog post for not knowing about <a href="https://searx.github.io/searx/">searx</a>, which isn’t particularly relevant to my gripes, but in the words of a <a href="https://vancouverguardian.com/vancouver-comedy-jon-endo/">comedian I just met</a>: “it is what it is.”</p>
<p>That stuff’s all tired and blase. Have you heard of <a href="https://www.marginalia.nu/">marginalia</a>, which lets you control which categories of websites you’re looking for. Or how about <a href="https://gigablast.com/">gigablast</a>, which combats dead links by finding archived versions of them? Or how about <a href="https://www.mojeek.com/">mojeek</a>, which <a href="https://seirdy.one/posts/2021/03/10/search-engines-with-own-indexes/">seirdy</a> figures is the best alternative search engine out there?</p>
<p>Turns out there’s a ton of innovation in this space, along which lines I have a personal announcement to make some time in the near future. But that’s getting ahead of myself.</p>
<h2 id="combating-the-monotonous-web">Combating the Monotonous Web</h2>
<p>After a month of exploring weird stuff on the internet, I’ve realized that the number one way that webmasters (to use a throwback term) can help combat the monotonous web is to just link to sites you think are cool.</p>
<p>You’ll notice there are more links in this post than usual. That’s not by accident.</p>
<p>Search engines discover sites by automating surfing — that is, they just click every link on every page, and see what they find in the process. On a more human level, if you like my stuff, you’re pretty likely to like the stuff I like. And so, to be part of the change, here are some websites I find unusually interesting:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.paulgraham.com/articles.html">Paul Graham’s essays</a> — fascinating musings on doing important work with your life.</li>
<li><a href="https://mitxela.com">mitxela</a> who makes weird and delightful DIY gadgets</li>
<li><a href="http://journal.stuffwithstuff.com/archive/">Bob Nystrom</a> — high quality blog posts on game design and the mechanics of writing books</li>
<li><a href="https://blog.plover.com/">Mark Jason Dominus</a> for whom there are no words. A true 21st century polymath, whose blog spans from etymology to abstract math.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.lesswrong.com/tag/original-sequences">LessWrong</a> which taught me most things I know about the art of thinking.</li>
<li><a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/about/">Slate Star Codex</a> which taught me how to write, and whose clarity of thought I aspire towards.</li>
<li><a href="https://dominiccummings.com/">Dominic Cummings</a> who gives an unprecedented look behind the usually closed-doors of politics.</li>
</ul>
        ]]>
      </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
      <title>Sandy Maguire Escapes the Room: Lost in Space</title>
      <id>blog/escape-room-lost-in-space/index.html</id>
      <link href='blog/escape-room-lost-in-space/index.html'/>
      <published>2022-08-13T14:18:00Z</published>
      <updated>2022-08-13T14:18:00Z</updated>

      <content type="html">
        <![CDATA[
        <p>For my birthday, Erin and I headed to a local (literally across the street) escape-room in Vancouver called Exit Gastown, where we played <a href="https://e-exit.ca/escape/games/lost-in-space-ecape-room/">Lost in Space</a> with just the two of us.</p>
<p>Online the difficulty is three stars, but I swear in person it was labeled as four. It’s always hard to get a sense of the actual difficulty between companies, so we went in expecting to escape. We didn’t. By the end of our 45 minutes, we were on the last clue — figure out a lot of math for teleporter coordinates — but nowhere near solving it. Alas.</p>
<p>Erin and I are very new to the world of escape rooms. This was her second, and my fifth, and neither of us came away very impressed with the puzzles. The concept is pretty great, but the execution left a lot to be desired. Let me explain.</p>
<p>LOST IN SPACE. You’re on a space ship that has crash-landed. The lights are off, so you need to get the power back on, and then find the teleporter room and teleport home. Or something. The crash-landing stuff was (very) briefly mentioned in the beginning dialog, and the only other clue to it is a window painted onto the wall that looks cracked. OK fine, except that this is a critical clue in teleporting away; you need not only decipher the coordinate system, but you also need to remember where you are in the solar system. And if you don’t remember from the initial briefing, well, good luck!</p>
<p>A few other dings. I liked the idea that the lights are off, but you’re given only one flashlight, which means your group can’t parallelize any solving. You start the game with an “engineering” binder explaining all the subsystems, and roughly how to go about accomplishing them. One of the things to do is to get the ship’s power system on emergency batteries, and then eventually running again, but accomplishing neither of them turns the lights back on! They’re just off, for 45 minutes.</p>
<p>The better design here is that the lights come on to 10-20% brightness after you get onto emergency power, and then turn on in full when the generators are running again. It’s an interesting gimmick that you need to get the power back on, but it needs to be rewarded, rather than being an arbitrary key to ungate progress.</p>
<p>Half way through, you do get a second flashlight. But the batteries were (unintentionally) half-dead and died before the end of the game. I had to leave the room to get new ones, which ate a few minutes out of our failed escape.</p>
<p>Most egregious, however, was the binder’s engineering list of “spare parts.” There are three spare parts listed: a set of jumper cables, a spare battery, and a wiring diagram. We found the jumper cables first, and five minutes later found the spare battery. So we were primed to think about the spare parts as literal objects that could be picked up. But then the wiring diagram doesn’t fit the pattern. It’s drawn onto the wall behind the puzzle, and is presented as the wiring itself.</p>
<p>The puzzle is that you need to shine a light into four holes in the right order. We fucked around with it for a while, following the obvious route implied by the wiring on the wall. At each step, the thing beeps at you. But if you hold your light on a little too long (we’re talking half a second or so), it beeps again, and that is the system resetting itself. Our progress was hampered by this for probably ten minutes before we asked for a hint — we could neither find the wiring diagram, nor could we brute force the puzzle. But there was no wiring diagram, and our understanding of the thing was entirely correct, it’s just that the mechanism was incorrectly resetting our progress.</p>
<p>Very annoying.</p>
<p>I’ll also ding the room for having several unintentional typos in the manual; usually things like these are secret clues, or something to decipher. Nope, here they’re just someone not using spellcheck, which doesn’t inspire a great deal of confidence that the game designer is a person of care.</p>
<p>There were some things I liked about this room though; the system to get the power back on was interesting. You need to find some jumper cables, put them into the right place, and then identify that the battery is broken, and find a better one that won’t short out the circuit. I like puzzles that require disparate pieces to be solved, rather than being one-key-one-lock deals.</p>
<p>Despite my complaints, I liked that the lights were off at the beginning. It was thematically interesting, but overstayed its welcome.</p>
<p>Overall though, I wasn’t very impressed with Lost in Space. Progress was entirely linear, and at no point did were we required to use information we’d learned somewhere else. Puzzles like these are frustrating: if you get stuck on something, you’re just stuck with no recourse. Oh well. This one is a nice case study in how to not structure an escape room.</p>
<p>Two out of five stars.</p>
        ]]>
      </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
      <title>The Cruise Facade</title>
      <id>blog/cruising-facade/index.html</id>
      <link href='blog/cruising-facade/index.html'/>
      <published>2022-05-08T05:21:00Z</published>
      <updated>2022-05-08T05:21:00Z</updated>

      <content type="html">
        <![CDATA[
        <p>Warning: snooty and written at 5AM. Am I becoming my mother?</p>
<p>I’ve been out of contact lately; consider that a symptom of being in the middle of the Atlantic ocean on a Cruise. The idea was merely that it’d be cool to cross an ocean like our forefathers did, and a Cruise just happened to be the easiest way to make that happen. My mom, when hearing of this plan, said (rather disappointedly) “oh… I didn’t think you were Cruise People.”</p>
<p>And my god, are we not.</p>
<p>There are two good things I’ll say about the experience. It’s relaxing to spend all day in the pool and not need to worry about food. And, we have <em>clearly</em> managed to get outside of our filter bubble.</p>
<p>Cruising People are a peculiar bunch. Primarily American. BIG Americans. The sailing has 2500 passengers, of whom 40 are under 18, and easily 50% are over 65. I’d say there are maybe 50 people in our extremely permissive 20-40 age cohort, and a good chunk of those are families.</p>
<p>The on-board entertainment knows its audience, and it is not us.</p>
<p>For example, early on, we went to a stand-up comic’s set. The bits ranged from “you know how when you call the airline to make a booking, you need to navigate a lot of phone menus? AND THEN WHEN YOU GET THROUGH, IT’S NOT EVEN TO AN AMERICAN!!!!” all the way to “I sure am glad I’m not old!!”<a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"><sup>1</sup></a></p>
<p>There are shows and activities every hour. Bachata classes, karaoke night, lots of <em>easy</em> trivia<a href="#fn2" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref2" role="doc-noteref"><sup>2</sup></a>. The dance classes are nearly empty, the karaoke nights are full but non-participatory, and Frank Sinatra is chosen more than every other artist combined.</p>
<p>But Beatles Night is always packed, and is by far the liveliest thing on the ship. Those boomers be shimmying!</p>
<p>There are “Enrichment Seminars” on topics like <em>romantic comedies of the ’90s,</em> and <em>things you didn’t know about John Wayne.</em> That is, anything someone on the boat could plausibly talk about for 20 minutes. There was a (technically amazing) cabaret consisting of lots of flashy dance moves, without any coherent story or theme. There was an (also technically amazing) “theatre production” consisting of lots of flashy dance moves, without any coherent story or theme, but set to pop music that you’ve familiar with.</p>
<p>I have lots to say here. The ship clearly knows its audience, so we can work backwards from the shows to figure out who that audience must be. The entire cruise experience is an excellent example of [premium medicre]<a href="#fn3" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref3" role="doc-noteref"><sup>3</sup></a> — that is, “exclusive” without actually excluding anyone. Night 2 was a “black-tie formal night”, and they let my jeans-and-a-button-down-in-sneakers backpacking ass right in without a second glance. But it <em>feels</em> exclusive: it must be, because they keep saying so!</p>
<p>Over the first few days, we kept meeting cruisers who seemed genuinely shocked to hear it’s our first cruise.<a href="#fn4" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref4" role="doc-noteref"><sup>4</sup></a> “Oh you’ll <em>just love it!</em>” they would keep telling us. And clearly they did indeed love it; cruisers keep telling us about their loyal program; we’ve met many people who have spent more than 365 days of their life cruising. And we met one guy who has spent over 720.</p>
<p>So, who is this cruise for? The entire experience is a weird facade; lots of stuff with no actual substance behind. It’s an experience that feels classy, without actually being classy. Cruisers can point to the cabaret and theatre and enrichment lectures and feel like they’re living a refined life. They know that these are the sorts of activities that high-status people enjoy, and are delighted to find that they too like these high-status activities!</p>
<p>I have never seen a cabaret before, and thus didn’t know what to expect. I quite liked what I got, because it was well-choreographed and technically impressive (there were six robotic arms that were in motion the whole time, and never once bashed into one another!) But Erin was unimpressed; “that wasn’t a cabaret” she said.</p>
<p>Here’s what I think is happening. Take 250 fit, sexy, twenty-something dancers and give them a week to choreograph and rehearse a bunch of dances to pop music. Take the resulting three minute pieces, and stitch them together with the barest amount of thread to pass it off as a work of high-culture. Set it in “another world” to lampshade any issues in continuity or theming, and voila, you have a cabaret, or a musical, or a hip-hop dance class, or whatever you want!</p>
<p>What you’ve come up with is something easily palatable. It’s got flashy dance moves and songs that you’ve heard before. If you call it a cabaret, it must be. And someone (like me) who might not be familiar with the intricacies of cabaret can come away being impressed, both with the show, and with the fact that I am the sort of person who likes cabarets. I too, must be high-class.</p>
<p>The whole ship feels like that. Which is weird, because all the talent is genuinely amazing. The musicians we’ve met are all very accomplished session players. The ones we haven’t met are also fantastic. We met one of the costumers, who made a dress for Lady Gaga. We’ve yet to meet any dancers, but my guess is that they’re equally accomplished. But there’s a creative flare missing, and I’d wager that’s intentional.</p>
<p>And then there are the art collecting lectures. The first three days had enrichment lectures on how to <em>appreciate,</em> and, subsequently, <em>value</em> art. Funnily enough, the next day there was an art auction. How about that? I overheard a woman saying she spent $5000 on art: “I’ve never really paid much attention to art before, I guess because I wasn’t really grown up enough. But now I’m ready to start collecting.” Did I mention there isn’t any internet on the ship? Well, there is, if you’re willing to pay a years’ worth of internet bills for a week. I haven’t worked out whether or not most people footed that bill, but I suspect they aren’t using it to get a second opinion before buying <em>priceless</em> art prints.</p>
<p>The average person on this cruise clearly considers themselves to be on an adventure. They are traveling! And seeing the world! We’ve been told we’re very brave for making a trans-Atlantic cruise our first one; it has almost no stop-overs, did you know!</p>
<p>Yeah, OK.</p>
<p>The staff, however, are much more clearly our people. Millennials, working weird-ass jobs in order to sail around the world and send money back home. People who are interesting and adventurous enough to pack up their lives for a few months at a time. From them we’ve learned all sorts of juicy gossip; that the entirety of the 3rd floor is off-access not because of ongoing maintenance like they say, but because it’s the covid quarantine floor. And <em>everyone</em> is sick. Or, how five old people die every cruise, and how the ship has a special morgue freezer to keep them in. The staff recognize how ridiculous the entire experience is, and it’s a refreshing reminder that we’re not crazy.</p>
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr />
<ol>
<li id="fn1" role="doc-endnote"><p>This from a comic who was easily in his 70s, and not looking the better for it.<a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li>
<li id="fn2" role="doc-endnote"><p>eg. From which film is the line “may the force be with you?”<a href="#fnref2" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li>
<li id="fn3" role="doc-endnote"><p>https://www.ribbonfarm.com/2017/08/17/the-premium-mediocre-life-of-maya-millennial/<a href="#fnref3" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li>
<li id="fn4" role="doc-endnote"><p>And our last, but we are savvy enough to hold our tongues about that part.<a href="#fnref4" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li>
</ol>
</section>
        ]]>
      </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
      <title>Be a Lighthouse</title>
      <id>blog/be-a-lighthouse/index.html</id>
      <link href='blog/be-a-lighthouse/index.html'/>
      <published>2022-04-13T23:25:00Z</published>
      <updated>2022-04-13T23:25:00Z</updated>

      <content type="html">
        <![CDATA[
        <p>A few times a year I’m asked by people what’s the value in maintaining a blog. To their eyes, a blog is a liability. Not only is it extracurricular work, it also, (they say) limits personal growth, since the old things you’ve said stick around. Furthermore, in today’s age of hyper-cancellation, keeping old ideas around is downright dangerous. Who knows what ideas will be out of vogue next week?</p>
<p>None of these problems bother me. I like writing — attempting to serialize ideas into prose acts as an excellent forcing-function. Writing it out makes clear the bits which are weak, and ideas get fleshed out as I try to glue together the disparate pieces. Often, a second essay will be born from the digressions that happen while writing the first.</p>
<p>Furthermore, I’m OK saying I was wrong and stupid in the past. Its a necessary part of growth, and of intellectual honesty — which itself contributes to getting smarter. After all, learning is really hard if you are lying to yourself about what you already know.</p>
<p>As for being cancelled, well, fuck it. If it happens, it happens. But I’m a small target with no audience to speak of. I’m about as uncancellable as can be, and I guess I’ll worry about it if it ever becomes an issue.</p>
<p>So those are some reasons why to not not have a blog. But, as we know, the law of the excluded middle is bupkis. So, why have a blog?</p>
<p>Blogging acts as a lighthouse.</p>
<p>Lighthouses are famously easy things to spot. They broadcast their presence far and wide. It’s their only function. Being a lighthouse makes you easier to find, which is to say, it helps advertise your existence to the sort of people you’d like to find.</p>
<p>Once a month or so I get a cold email from someone who has found my blog and liked it so much they wanted to get in touch. Almost by definition, these are my people. They are people from all around the world, who are thinking about and trying to solve the same problems I am. And that’s a magical gift that I wouldn’t be able to find any other way.</p>
<p>Being a lighthouse is the most important piece of advice I have that isn’t already in the mainstream spotlight. Importantly, it transcends any particular tactics. You don’t need to blog to be a lighthouse. Putting stickers of things you like on your laptop makes you a lighthouse at the coffee shop. Starting (and advertising) a local club for one of your interests makes you a lighthouse.</p>
<p>Niche things, by definition, are hard to find community for. So do your part by organizing enough neg-entropy around you that members of your desired tribe will recognize you when they see you.</p>
<p>Be a lighthouse! You never know what marvelous people might find you.</p>
        ]]>
      </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
      <title>Pillars of the Community</title>
      <id>blog/pillars-of-the-community/index.html</id>
      <link href='blog/pillars-of-the-community/index.html'/>
      <published>2022-03-31T05:43:00Z</published>
      <updated>2022-03-31T05:43:00Z</updated>

      <content type="html">
        <![CDATA[
        <p>I managed to wake myself up at 4 in the morning with an insight, and figured I should write it down. As you might imagine, I haven’t been sleeping well lately, so I don’t know whom to credit with this idea — apologies. I’ve been wandering around in a bit of an exhausted zombie funk the last few weeks, and apparently not forming as many short-term memories as one would like.</p>
<p>But, anyway, someone and I were talking about community, and how to find it. Erin and I often say that community is the people you don’t necessarily like, but whom you have a reason to see over and over again. For better or worse, you’re stuck with them.</p>
<p>This seems true, but it doesn’t feel like the whole story. For example, when you think of the term “pillar of the community,” who comes to mind? For me it’s people like small business owners, religious leaders, club organizers, mail delivery people, voracious volunteers, the bartender at the local pub, and the like.</p>
<p>None of these people are best differentiated by being “not necessarily liked,” though they do have a reason to be seen over and over again. But I also see Sideways Man<a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"><sup>1</sup></a> on the street maybe once a week, and I wouldn’t describe him as a pillar of the community.</p>
<p>My interlocutor had a different idea of what it meant to be part of a community.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>A community is a group of people who can depend on one another.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This lens connects the dots. The mail person does a great service for the immediate area, as does the small-pub bartender. But, not only this. We can also expect the mail person to come with great regularity; neither rain nor sleet, you know. If you’re feeling down and need a dispassionate ear, this is a service offered by the bartender. And, importantly, the bar is always open.</p>
<p>What about small business owners? These are people who’ve strongly invested in the area. Their personal livelihood is attached not only to the neighborhood, but, importantly, to the ongoing success of the neighborhood. Business owners are necessarily among the most-invested in their community, since putting food on the table is linked to making and maintaining relationships. When you are looking to buy something expensive, it’s probably worth buying from someone you can keep an ongoing relationship with; someone you can depend on to still be around in a year if something goes sour.</p>
<p>Religion likewise. I suspect the bit about “religious leader” is a cached meme in the 21st century, but places of worship definitely do their part for the community. Name a choir or support-group that doesn’t depend on a church for a place to meet. Or, Erin points out, consider <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Langar_(Sikhism)">langar</a>, the Sikh practice of a “community kitchen” where anyone can show up for a meal.</p>
<p>On a personal level, this checks out with my experience. I felt significantly more involved in my community when I decided to <a href="/blog/neighborhoods">meet everyone in the neighborhood</a>. All of a sudden, I was going out of my way to talk to people I’d see on a regular basis. They didn’t depend on me for any service, but they could depend on me to say hi.</p>
<p>Likewise in Victoria, where I’ve been trying to put together a functional programming meetup. The local tech scene hasn’t been scratching my itches, so I figured I’d just take matters into my own hands. So, every two weeks, I’ve been hanging out at the same place at the same time. People can depend on me being there, and thus can swing by on the spur of the moment. We’re getting lots of repeat attendees, which suggests the meetup group is serving some need.</p>
<p>Where does this leave us? Is this an idea we can exploit to get closer to the good life? What courses of action does it suggest?</p>
<p>The most obvious is that if you’re feeling like you’re lacking community, put yourself in a position of being required. An easy starting point is to just regularly show up at a local meetup. Half the battle is showing up, after all. Offer to help organize things.</p>
<p>At an intermediate level, get involved with a group of people who create things, and then help them create that thing. It could be a choral performance, or an art exhibit or whatever. Something with a deadline. Everyone involved is going to want the thing to be as good as possible, and will thus be depending on you (and you, them) to put in as much as you can afford.</p>
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr />
<ol>
<li id="fn1" role="doc-endnote"><p>You’d understand if you saw him.<a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li>
</ol>
</section>
        ]]>
      </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
      <title>Excellence Orbits</title>
      <id>blog/excellence-orbits/index.html</id>
      <link href='blog/excellence-orbits/index.html'/>
      <published>2022-03-17T23:42:00Z</published>
      <updated>2022-03-17T23:42:00Z</updated>

      <content type="html">
        <![CDATA[
        <p>Thailand is known as a place that has Figured Out Tourism. Not only is it a great place for a week holiday, it’s also a widely touted as a fantastic choice for first-time backpackers. These things are all true, and Thailand is in fact a blast. But it’s <em>mostly</em> a blast if you’re 18 and looking to get drunk and party. Which I am not.</p>
<p>And so, for me, Thailand was this nice tropical place, full of first-time traveling teenagers looking to get drunk and party. Not that there’s anything wrong with that, but I’ve been there and done that, and don’t need to do more of it. Thus, when I ran off to Thailand after my <a href="/blog/burnout/">breakdown</a>, I was underwhelmed. I was looking for young, driven, idealists, who had identified Thailand as a great place to escape from societal norms while they worked on building something cool. What I got instead was a lot of nights at the bar with whomever I happened to meet, talking mainly about nothing. But there sure was a lot of partying!!!!</p>
<p>A guy I had met once on a fateful night a few years back had mentioned he was heading to Koh Lanta, a nice quiet island to go hang out and do diving. It Sounded better than getting drunk and partying, so I hopped on a boat and arrived later that afternoon. I ended up staying for three months.</p>
<p>Koh Lanta is an island nestled-in between three giant party spots in Thailand — Koh Phi Phi, Ao Nang, and Phuket. As a result, anyone in the area who wanted to get drunk and party ended up at one of those spots, and meant the only travelers on Koh Lanta were the ones who were looking for something else. By virtue of being in the orbit of big party spots, Koh Lanta filtered out the big party people.</p>
<p>Does this idea generalize? Can we find the other Koh Lantas in spirit? What notable features should we be searching for?</p>
<p>Andrew McKnight helped me come up with some other examples. Continuing on with the travel example, the Baltics are a lovely place, but aren’t known for their tourism. As a result, the only people who travel to the Baltics are the experienced backpackers; the ones who have been everywhere else, and who want to continue exploring. Travelers who successfully escape Southeast Asia’s gravity field are almost immediately filtered for being interesting and well-traveled.</p>
<p>It’s a poorly-kept secret that at any tech conference, the “real conference” goes on in the hallway while most people are listening to scheduled talks. The people who aren’t going to talks are the ones who don’t want to go there, either because they aren’t interested, already know the material, or have something better to do. In any case, those are the people you should be hanging out with — they either have better taste than the mainstream, more knowledge than the mainstream, or have also identified that the hallway track is the place to be. People who escape the (focused) mass appeal of the talks are immediately filtered for being knowledgeable.</p>
<p>Or consider wine bars. Wine bars are notoriously more classy than sports bars. One way this plays out is that they don’t have TVs on the wall, which means if you’re going to the wine bar, you’re not there to mindlessly drink. You’re probably out with some friends, deliberately going to an environment where you can interact with one another. People who escape the attractor basin of sports bars are immediately filtered for interpersonal interactions.</p>
<p>Something like 99% of AI funding is going into deep learning. Though they don’t get much publicity, there are tons of other subfields. Things like robotics, expert systems, fuzzy logic, decision algorithms, search methods. What’s keeping people in those subfields, when they could easily switch to deep learning and make bank? Presumably they know something the rest of us don’t; it’s hard to believe that the people working on AI are all idiots. People who escape the attractor basin of money are immediately filtered for having some principles.</p>
<p>What do all of these examples have in common? The defining characteristic seems to be that within some special interest group (vacationers, travelers, conference attendees, drinkers, researchers), there exist strong attractors in the field which capture most of the interest-mass. The worthwhile things we’ve identified exist in the same space, but are robust enough to avoid being captured by the bigger attractor.</p>
<p>This makes a lot of sense. Someone loosely interested in a field will immediately discover its strongest attractors, and will likely be pulled in. That means the population around a strong attractor will be disproportionately newbies, weak affiliates, and “lifers” — people who were pulled in, and have never explored the space other than around the first attractor they found.</p>
<p>Gravity makes an excellent metaphor here, thus the term “attractor.” Imagine you’re traveling through space and accidentally end up in our solar system. If you end up sticking around, it’s probably because you got caught in the sun’s gravity well; everything else is too small to have any likelihood of grabbing you. Circling around the sun is better than careening through space — at least it’s warm. But, all things considered, the sun is the least interesting thing you could be orbiting in the whole solar system. Left to chance, you will probably stay orbiting the sun for the rest of your life, being warm but lacking any deep sense of purpose or belonging.</p>
<p>Now consider how much better it would be to be in Earth’s orbit. You would have to dodge the neverending launch of cube sats. You’d see all sorts of interesting developments happening on the surface. You’d probably be curious enough to put some brain cycles towards figuring out how get out of orbit and onto the planet. All of a sudden you’d have purpose, intrigue, direction. So many cool things — much better than just going around the sun every 30 years or whatever — but you’d be completely unaware of all of it if you just stayed around the big attractor in the system. The one that catches things by default.</p>
<p>The more I think about this, the more it seems obviously true. A central tenet of mine for a long time was “<a href="/blog/comfort-zones/">the best things in life are outside your comfort zone</a>,” but reality seems even weirder. In fact, if all this stuff about attractors is true, the best things in life are outside our <strong>awareness entirely.</strong> But, this gives us an algorithm for finding them: look for proximate attractors that haven’t yet pulled in. That’s where the interesting stuff is going on.</p>
        ]]>
      </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
      <title>What I Have Resolved To Do</title>
      <id>blog/2022-goals/index.html</id>
      <link href='blog/2022-goals/index.html'/>
      <published>2022-01-09T17:50:00Z</published>
      <updated>2022-01-09T17:50:00Z</updated>

      <content type="html">
        <![CDATA[
        <p>2022 is here, and I’m very determined to kick its ass. My best years have been those which I came to with a specific, scary plan. I’ve had sloppy, weak plans for a few years in a row, and the years turned out pretty sloppy and weak as a result. NOT THIS YEAR, BABY.</p>
<p>One big issue I’ve had with the last two years is that I haven’t had enough to fill my (copious) time, and because of that I fell back on traditional (and stupid) ways of killing time: scrolling dumb websites, watching TV and playing video games. That’s no way to be spending my golden years of retirement. If I’m going to be wasting my time, I might as well be getting paid to do it. Instead, the plan is to say “YES!” to enough cool projects that I don’t have time to spare.</p>
<p>Before getting to the actual goals, I have a mantra for the year that I’d like to focus on:</p>
<p><strong>Brook no excuses for suboptimality.</strong> This is my mantra for the year. Whatever I do, I will do it with gusto. This is not to say that every essay needs to be ruthlessly edited, but it does mean that every essay must accomplish my goal for it. It means I will go the two minutes out of my way to fold my laundry, or to get rid of the unused, uncomfortable chair gathering dust in the corner. It means actively working towards making everything in my life better. I’m retired with infinite time and effectively infinite money; I have no excuses for living a suboptimal life. And this mantra is to help me remember that.</p>
<p>My goals for the year, in no particular order:</p>
<p>In 2022, I am going to <strong>read and engage with 52 papers on topics that I find interesting.</strong> The engagement part is critical — it’s easy enough to “read” a paper but moving your eyes over it. However, the purpose here is to rapidly inject ideas and methods into my head. Engagement here means I need to produce some sort of artifact as a result of working through the paper: something that proves I understand the ideas in it. I’ve already done <a href="https://reasonablypolymorphic.com/blog/adders-and-arrows/">one</a>, which should give you a sense of what it means to engage.</p>
<p>A common failure mode I see in myself is engaging in suboptimal behavior due to a lack of easily-discovered knowledge. For example, I put off playing piano pieces in Gb for like a decade because I didn’t know what notes were in that scale — even though when I sat down to think it through, it took less than 2 minutes to do. Thus, be it resolved that I will <strong>spend 2 hours a week this year researching high-value topics.</strong></p>
<p>One of the things I have been consistently putting off is learning how to feel good in my body. My body is a weak programmer body, and it gets hurt all the time when I try to exercise. Getting hurt all the time really kills any sort of fitness momentum I have. So this year I will <strong>get fit, or at least get to a point where I understand my body well enough to not get hurt when doing fitness.</strong></p>
<p>This year, I am not going to go to bed until <strong>my living and work spaces are tidy.</strong> This includes the kitchen.</p>
<p>I will <strong>compose and publish 12 original songs</strong> this year.</p>
<p>In 2022, I resolve to <strong>not be a curmudgeon.</strong> This means that when things annoy me, I will calmly go and discuss the issue with the first parties. Whenever that isn’t an option, I will come up with some other pro-social solution to the problem, possibly including just deciding to not be bothered by it.</p>
<p>Relatedly, this year I will <strong>not attempt telekinesis.</strong> Attempting telekinesis is when you try to solve a problem by wishing really hard that it would go away. Like, when someone is bothering you but doesn’t realize it, and instead of solving the problem you just sit there smoldering — in essence, hoping that if you concentrate hard enough you could make their head explode. Similar to above, I will either go calmly attempt to solve the problem, or stop being bothered by it.</p>
<p>During 2022, I will <strong>publish 100k words</strong>. They do not necessarily need to be in text format.</p>
<p>My biggest takeaway from the Elon Musk book is that Elon is significantly more willing than most people to invest in himself financially. I recognized that fact when I read it, but didn’t do anything with it. So this year, I’m going to <strong>spend $10,000 of my own money on my own projects.</strong> Not only will this help my projects, it will also help me burn my runway cash, which should get me off of resting on my laurels.</p>
<p>Similarly, I am earmarking <strong>another $5,000 for solving trivial problems in my life.</strong> I don’t like spending money on things, even when that money would pay off in big dividends, and this is a current failure on my part.</p>
<p>On the community front, this year I will <strong>reach out cold to one cool person a week.</strong> I figure that even if only 5% of them respond, that will be two new excellent humans I’ll have created new relationships with.</p>
<p>Something I did during 2018 that aggressively changed how I felt about my city was to <a href="/blog/neighborhoods/">actively meet people.</a> This was one of the best exercises I’ve ever done, but I’ve fallen out of the habit and find myself pining for the results. So in 2022, I will <strong>meet two new people a day.</strong></p>
<p>Playing music with other people is one of my most cherished hobbies, and I barely do any of it. By the end of the year, I will be a member of a musical community in the same way I am a member of many programming communities. I realize this is not a very SMART goal but I don’t know how to make it into one and it’s very important to me regardless. Please get in touch if you have some ideas!</p>
<p>I don’t have enough good friends in my life. By the end of the year I will <strong>have five really good friends.</strong> Musicians from the above goal are allowed to count towards this. The SMARTer version of this goal is that I will <strong>spend quality time with three friends a week</strong> on average this year.</p>
<hr />
<p>Whew! What a lot of things to track. I’m fully aware that when I make goals, I usually completely miss the ballpark on what I’ll think of as important a few months down the line. So instead of just weaseling out, this year I am allowed to <strong>cancel one of these goals</strong>, and <strong>adjust the parameters on another two.</strong> I hope to not need to do these things, but they’re available if I need to.</p>
        ]]>
      </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
      <title>Looking Back on 2021</title>
      <id>blog/looking-back-2021/index.html</id>
      <link href='blog/looking-back-2021/index.html'/>
      <published>2022-01-01T07:28:00Z</published>
      <updated>2022-01-01T07:28:00Z</updated>

      <content type="html">
        <![CDATA[
        <p>Well, 2021 is over. I’ve been dreading writing this retrospective blog post for a few weeks, because every time I tried to think about what happened last year, I couldn’t come up with anything. The GLOBAL PANDEMIC of yesteryear has shown modest signs of abatement, but life remains pretty weird. Personally I’ve stopped caring about the GLOBAL PANDEMIC and would be happy to just get the thing and have it over and done with, but I appear to be in the minority on this one. I digress.</p>
<p>So what happened in 2021? It’s a little hard to remember, as my specific memories are usually attached to weird places I found myself, people I was hanging out with, or particular projects I was working on. Due to UNCERTAIN TIMES, most of those hooks are unavailable, so this post comes with no promises that it is comprehensive. But that’s OK.</p>
<p>Erin and I rang in the new year in my old apartment. We’d gone out for fancy cocktails, but previously unbeknownst to us, the bar started the new years countdown at 7:30pm. Why? Bonnie had announced at the eleventh hour that new years was canceled, and that all establishments had to be closed by 8. So we took our fancy cocktails, and spent the rest of the night at my place, in rather low spirits. To celebrate the new year, we screamed “fuck 2020” off the balcony, and most of the nearby apartment blocks joined us in our fury. It was the closest thing to “community” I’d felt in Victoria up to that point.</p>
<p>January was spent trying to <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8vWaawiUteM">emulate George Hotz</a> and throw knowledge of computation at a field that was explicitly non-computational. My target was Canadian case law, trying to mine as much insight out of the field without knowing anything about it. <a href="https://reasonablypolymorphic.com/blog/exploring-case-law/">I wrote about the process</a>.</p>
<p>In 2020, Erin had also expressed interest in having me build a robot for her. I decided to make an (ill-fated) roomba. <a href="https://reasonablypolymorphic.com/blog/roomba/">It wasn’t the world’s best robot,</a> but I learned a lot about how to not build robots for next time. There hasn’t yet been a next time though, and for good reason.</p>
<p>In February, my alma matter reached out, asking if I wanted to be a mentor for Women In Engineering. I get a few weird invitations like this every year, usually from people incorrectly assuming I’m a woman based on my name. I replied saying I’d be interested to mentor a Woman In Engineering, so long as they were OK with me not <em>being</em> a Woman In Engineering. Surprisingly they said yes, and so I was matched with Rebecca, a biomedical engineering student, who clearly thought about me as a boomer. We spent the year doing biweekly calls, with me ostensibly doing Mentoring, but all things considered I don’t think I did a very good job of it. Regardless, it was cool watching Rebecca’s growth over the year, and I don’t mind taking credit for it — even though she did way more work than I did!</p>
<p>Also in February, someone started paying me to tutor them in Haskell! It was a cool experience, but ultimately fizzled out. I learned a lot about teaching, and about learning, and perhaps most importantly about the value of setting expectations. It was lots of fun, and I’d love to do more of this! Feel free to hit me up if you’re interested and diligent.</p>
<p>I did <a href="https://blubrry.com/sessions_by_se/73979973/from-silicon-valley-to-digital-nomad-sandy-maguire/">two</a> <a href="https://haskellweekly.news/episode/39.html">podcasts</a> in March, one for the University of Waterloo Software Engineering podcast, and another for Haskell Weekly. Both were tons of fun, and briefly amplified my message — lots of really cool people reached out to me to chat about life.</p>
<p>Erin got a fancy job at a fancy law firm in Vancouver for the summer, so we made plans to move to Vancouver. We both gave up our apartments, and immediately after her law firm informed everyone that the job would be remote due to THE GLOBAL PANDEMIC. Rude. We spent a huge amount of energy house hunting in Vancouver, and found a great place, which fell through a few days before we were supposed to move in. Assuming the whole thing was cursed, we decided to stay in Victoria, and found a great place a few blocks away from my old place. We moved in together, and it was by far the best change in my life of the last year.</p>
<p>While we were still house hunting in Vancouver, Erin and I accidentally crossed paths with a world-famous Youtube celebrity. Erin was mortified when I called her over and asked “excuse me, but are you a world-famous Youtube celebrity?”</p>
<p>THE GLOBAL PANDEMIC had me down, so I decided to join a “rock band class” at the royal conservatory. I wasn’t sure what to expect, but I thought it would be nice to play music with people, since playing bass by oneself sorta defeats the point. Whatever I was expecting, it wasn’t what I got. What I got was to paired up with a handful of super boomers. There was Bill and Mike, Rob and Bob, and John and Mustafar. They were all pushing 70, and only wanted to play Herman’s Hermits. And they already had a bass player, and he was better than I was. We had to play behind GIANT PLEXI-GLASS SHEETS, and the entire experience was just terrible.</p>
<p>At the time, I was reading an excellent book about orthodox Jews, and somehow got myself all excited to celebrate the Sabbath. Erin and I started taking Saturday off, avoiding work and technology, trying to make time and space for friends and family. I started studying “how to study the Torah”, which <a href="/blog/hamming/">turned into a fantastic reading club</a> of Hamming with my friend Andrew. It was a blast of a time, even though we got through like one page an hour.</p>
<p>Relatedly, one time we were studying the “Torah” (read: Hamming) in the park, when a crazy man started harassing some poor woman. We intervened, the thing turned into a fracas, and ended with us dodging a gallon projectile of orange juice hurled directly at us.</p>
<p>Sometime in March, I decided to grab the GLOBAL PANDEMIC by its ugly horns. There’s a project called <a href="https://radvac.org/">RaDVaC</a>, which is an open-source vaccine project. It was unclear how much longer the (official) vaccines were going to take, and I figured I had some idle capital to throw at weird projects. Two of my friends were interested in collaborating, and we figured we could make 500 doses at a little less than $300 each. Unfortunately, it seems quite hard to get peptide synthesized in Canada, and nobody got back to me. Still, I think this was a worthwhile way to spend a few weeks. I want to train my “protagonist” muscles, and get into a headspace where the next time a big world-scale problem comes along, I won’t just give up two years of my life without <em>trying.</em></p>
<p>Erin and I decided we’d avoid a lot of marriage-like-relationship problems if we just hired someone to clean our apartment, rather than doing it ourselves. We hired an agency, who sent a man that I googled immediately before his arrival. Turns out he was recently acquitted from a giant sexual-abuse scandal. Acquitted is a good thing, but it didn’t make us feel particularly good about the whole affair. We sat down and had a discussion about what sort of citizens we wanted to be — do we trust in the legal system to have done its job properly? And even if it didn’t, what should society do about people like this? We decided to keep him, but after a few disappointing cleans, the moral quandary was put behind us and we hired a friend of a friend who did a much better job.</p>
<p>In June, I applied for a super-cool sounding job involving making specialized hardware for accelerating machine learning. It sounded right up my alley, and was a pretty unique fit for my skills, so I was keen! But the interviewer didn’t show up. It took a week to reschedule, during which time I remembered that “machine learning” is just a code word for “AI that doesn’t work very well” and I remembered that <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/AI_control_problem">I don’t actually want to speed up bad AI</a>. Also there was probably something in there about not wanting to have a job. But a big chunk of it was the “don’t help cause the apocalypse” thing. Shame, really.</p>
<p>Concurrently, Erin and I got into a giant fight. Neither of us are sure what it was about, but man was it rough. Erin can be actively passive aggressive when she’s angry, and that wasn’t a very pleasant few days. I thought it would be funny if I got us a plaque memorializing the end of our fight, but didn’t actually do it. When our fight was over, I mentioned this idea to Erin, who thought it was hilarious. And so thus was born the “Sarin Board of Relationship Growth and Development” award. To this day there is only the single fight engraved on it, and we’d like to keep it that way. To avoid meta-fights, we’ve decided that the fights are remembered only by their dates: they don’t come with a title, so we can’t disagree about what the fights were about. Also, I get the odd numbered fights engraved, and Erin does the even ones. It’s a smooth system.</p>
<p>Since wrapping up my book last year, my main intellectual project for the year was <a href="https://haskellwingman.dev/">Wingman</a>. I was invited to <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=S0HvfXq3454">give a talk on it at ZuriHac</a>, which was a nice culmination of all of my work. It garnered a lot of attention, and felt good to finally show off in full glory.</p>
<p>My parents came to visit in July. It was fantastic to see them, and in an attempt to show them a good time, I bought us tickets to a Cuban music concert. But the restaurant I took them to beforehand had a mouse running around (they thought it was less charming than Erin and I did), and then I misread the starting time of the concert so got us there 90 minute early. And then the Cubans started 45 minutes late, so by the time they got started everyone was already tired and cranky. The show itself was a marvel of modern art. The musicians did a bit about how they were just practicing for a big show, and every song was punctuated with a 5 minute intermission with bad acting. It was not the hit for my parents that I was hoping.</p>
<p>After last year’s underwhelming birthday party, I wanted to make this year special, so I reached out to everyone I’d ever met, and invited them to A BIG SHINDIG. The turnout was OK, but special props to Malcolm, Sarah, and Eric for taking a ferry to come! THE GLOBAL PANDEMIC was not kind to everyone’s partying skills — we’d all sorta forgotten how to do it. Thankfully Erin peer pressured us all into shotgunning beers, which helped get the energy restarted!</p>
<p>Erin’s summer was rough. We canceled something like four weekend vacations because the workload was overwhelming. So when it was over, we decided to take a two-week vacation to the UK to visit her family. But the UK required a 10 day quarantine, which was going to aggressively eat up our vacation time. So we booked tickets to go to Texas, but then there was a huge GLOBAL PANDEMIC outbreak in Texas. So then we booked tickets to go to New Orleans, but it was hit with a hurricane. So then we booked tickets to Guatemala.</p>
<p>But Guatemala kinded sucked. It was soured by our stress levels, and wasn’t helped by all the stories we heard about just how dangerous Guatemala is. The guys walking around at every street corner with giant shotguns didn’t improve things. And the air quality was bad, and there were no sidewalks. Rough!</p>
<p>It wasn’t all bad — we went to visit our friends Christian and Paula, who had just left Canada to live in Guate. It was great to see them, and they took us to some pretty incredible places, including the most amazing beach house. The beach house was custom designed by two architects, in a crescent shape around a giant tree, complete with a cook and a guy whose job it was to drive us around in the boat. And the house was hidden behind a fake wall in the middle of a field outside of the sketchiest town I’ve ever seen. On one of our boat outings we met a woman who lived in the forest and who is “you, and you, and you.” We didn’t exactly get along.</p>
<p>Erin signed us up to hike up a damn (dormant) volcano. I was expecting like, a Canada-level hike. But this wasn’t that. It was six hours of steep, muddy climbing, carrying six liters of water in tow, through wet cloud cover. The Europeans (Erin included) gracefully leaped up the mountain like gazelles, while a few Middle Eastern men, some extremely unprepared Americans, and I trudged up, bonding in our shared misery.</p>
<p>We had been promised stellar views of active volcanoes when we reached the top, but all we got was thick clouds. It was damp and cold and there was nothing to see and the guides were unable to make a fire because it was too damp and cold, which didn’t add much to the damp/cold problem. But all sins were forgotten when in a magical moment, the cloud cover disappeared, and the crack of a nearby volcano erupting shook our (dormant) volcano. To date, it was one of the most magical sights I’ve ever seen, and might have been worth the cold, the damp, the almost dying from hypothermia overnight, the aggressive wildlife that tried to break into our cabin, the mouse that ate all of our food, and the searing pain in my knees by the time we got to the bottom.</p>
<p>But I also got to see an Austrian law professor squirm when I asked about his favorite administrative decision maker. “We don’t do that in Austria” he said.</p>
<p>After a week in Guatemala, we decided to cut our losses and head to Mexico. My cousin had recommended a place called San Cristobal de la Casas, citing it as a magical place. So we packed up and arrived there on a Friday night. The city was fully alive, with music on every corner, and more tacos and street merchants than you could shake a stick at. What a delightful change of pace after two years of THE GLOBAL PANDEMIC. I asked a local if there were any GLOBAL PANDEMIC restrictions and she laughed at me — “if they tried to stop us from dancing we would revolt.” Sentiments I wished my countrymen shared.</p>
<p>Erin and I took an awkward cooking class while in SCdlC. She went to the market to help buy ingredients, but I ducked in half way through. Erin greeted me at the door and whispered “we’ve made a huge mistake.” But the food was great, even if our compatriots’ conversational skills weren’t.</p>
<p>With our vacation time up, Erin headed for home. But I decided to stick around for another week or so, since I had nowhere to be and SCdlC was good for the soul. I spent the week exploring the city, hitting up cool jazz bars, reading lots of books, and generally reorganizing my life trying to get over an existential crisis. While in retrospect I didn’t solve it, I made great progress and came back raring to go.</p>
<p>While in SCdlC, I negotiated a contract for my newly-created business, and took on my first work as an independent contractor. The task was to help a business port their system to use one of my open-source libraries. It was fun work for a while, but I ran out of steam for the project due to some logistical problems. The result was less-than-stellar work on my part, and I’m mortified about the whole thing. I’m still trying to figure out how to sort everything out.</p>
<p>Also while in SCdlC, I applied to join an entrepreneur incubator. Essentially they pay your room and board to come spend three months meeting cool people and forming companies with a fixed investment for any good idea that comes through. It seemed like low risk (and I was the new owner of a new business) so I figured I’d give it a go. I got in, but ultimately turned it down because it was in Toronto and I couldn’t bear the thought of spending 3 months without Erin. More on this later.</p>
<p>Back in Victoria, I decided to try to make the most of the GLOBAL PANDEMIC. I took up improv classes, and Erin and I started taking swing dancing classes. Both were a blast, in completely different ways. Swing has continued to be awesome, but improv fizzled out. Erin and I have been having a blast with swing — it’s so cool how a particular lead on my end <em>forces her to twirl</em> without either of us understanding the dynamics. The art form itself has internalized lots of rules of physics that I can exploit as a lead. I can see how people get really into dance.</p>
<p>Mid-October I hopped on a plane to go visit some friends in Ontario. I was reunited with the excellent Jonathan Lorimer, and we pushed out a cool software package over the weekend — very reminiscent of my Erdos project. I took a “train” to Waterloo, but it turned out to be a bus that happened to be driven by a train conductor. We were like two hours behind schedule, and then the bus went rogue and went right past the terminal stop. For like 20 minutes. But Austin was waiting to pick me up when the dust settled, and I got to hang out with him and his partner whom I was ostensibly there to vet before they got married. I’m happy to report that Rosie passed with flying colors, and would make a great match for my heterosexual life-partner Austin.</p>
<p>While in Waterloo, I got to spend a few days on the university campus, haunting the old stomping grounds, and made friends with some of the baby software engineering students. It was a blast, and I tried to impart lots of good wisdom onto them. They didn’t care and went on with their homework, as is exactly the right response to old people butting in with advice. God knows I did the same.</p>
<p>I also ran into Alec Strong while in Waterloo, whom I have always really liked, but never known that well. We caught up over beers, and the night was one of the highlights of my year.</p>
<p>November came. Or more specifically, it didn’t, because on a whim I decided to participate in No-Nut November. Which is an online meme where you go for a month without having any orgasms. I made a valiant effort, but was thwarted in the final days by a brilliant ploy on Erin’s part. All in all it was great fun, and I’d strongly recommend NNN to everyone.</p>
<p>Some other stuff happened, like trying to volunteer for the local jazz bar. But I only made it a few shifts in because it was a horrible experience, impressively managing to not only give me no training, but also to schedule a bunch of new, untrained people to have a shift together, and also to write a really aggressive email when it predictably didn’t go well. It was a nice thought. But this is a long enough post already, so the remainder of the year’s anecdotes will stay mysteries.</p>
<h2 id="quantified-stuff">Quantified Stuff</h2>
<p>I read 49 books in 2021. Lots of them were light fiction, which I like reading before bed because otherwise my brain gets too engaged and I sleep poorly. But of the 49, five especially stood out:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/524985.The_Brothers_Ashkenazi">The Brothers Ashkenazi</a> — it’s hard to pin down exactly what I liked about this book, but it’s probably the best fiction I’ve ever read. The experience feels a lot like The Unbearable Lightness of Being, which is also a hard book to pin down why it’s as good as it is.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/18834806-art-fear">Art and Fear</a> — musings on how to be artistic, and how to actually get art done. Most of art is pouring your soul into things and having it be misunderstood or ignored. This book really resonated with me as an independent researcher, where I feel like most of the things I pour my soul into get misunderstood and ignored.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/17930467-the-fourth-phase-of-water">The Fourth Phase of Water</a> — water is way more interesting than anyone thinks. It has all of these funky physical properties, like you can use it as a battery. Sounds crazy, except that this is exactly how cells work. Reading this book really changed my everyday experience, and inspired a huge amount of wonder whenever I interacted with water.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/13036014-endless-forms-most-beautiful">Endless Forms Most Beautiful</a> — like the above, except about life forms. The idea is “what can we learn when we start treating biology quantitatively?” Like, if you classify families of life by what percentage of DNA they share, rather than what things seem to be the same, you can all of a sudden start tracking the evolutionary timeline. What tools in the toolkit of life developed when? Which things evolved repeatedly? For example, animal wings happened three times in three flavors: “arm wings” for birds, “hand wings” for bats, and “finger wings” for pterodactyls. Fascinating stuff.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/42036377-where-is-my-flying-car">Where’s My Flying Car?</a> — some boomer grew up in the golden age of science fiction, and took all of its promises to heart. This book is him trying to figure out where it all went wrong and why all of the predictions from the 50s didn’t shape out. It’s an inspiring book, if only to get a sense of what the future might look like if we set our sights higher than “our phones might be faster.”</li>
</ul>
<p>In addition to reading books, I also sold a bunch of books in 2021. Last year I sold 209 copies of Thinking with Types, and 266 copies of Algebra-Driven Design. If you put those numbers together, I sold more than one book a day, which is a pretty cool passive income stream. At time of writing, I’m 13 sales away from 1000 copies of Algebra-Driven Design sold. Go buy some!</p>
<p>Over the last year, I did 963 hours of deep, focused work, 294 of which were spent on Wingman.</p>
<p>I spent 737 hours watching TV which is about 2h a day and a disgusting amount and I am ashamed. I will do better next year.</p>
<p>I spent 285 hours playing video games, mostly in the form of Civilization, which I have since uninstalled and unpurchased because it’s not even fun.</p>
<p>I also spent 163 hours breaking my new years resolution, which is not so good, but also I think the resolution might have been missing judicious thought.</p>
<p>I made 1208 commits last year and published 30,422 words.</p>
<p>I listened to 23,920 songs, and my favorite new artist of the year is <a href="https://open.spotify.com/artist/6RhsbxbsDk5ypSXFkS41J5">Marlowe</a>.</p>
<h2 id="wrapping-up">Wrapping Up</h2>
<p>When I started out to write this post, I was feeling quite glum about the whole year. But having written everything out, I’m actually quite pleased with how it went and how much I grew during it.</p>
<p>My feelings were that I didn’t accomplish much during the year, but this isn’t true. While no, I didn’t publish a new book or anything, I did make a really fucking cool piece of technology. More importantly however, I realized that my crowning achievement of 2021 was the relationship I’ve built with Erin. That’s where the majority of my energy went, and it shows. I’ve never been so happy with anyone ever before. Not by a long shot.</p>
<p>However you want to cut it, 2021 was a good year and 2022 is going to be much better again.</p>
        ]]>
      </content>
    </entry>
</feed>

