<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<feed xmlns='http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom' xmlns:g='http://base.google.com/ns/1.0'>
  <title>We Can Solve This</title>
  <updated>2021-12-23T11:17:00Z</updated>
  <author><name>Sandy Maguire</name></author>
  <id>http://sandymaguire.me</id>
  <link rel='self' href='atom.xml'/>

    <entry>
      <title>An Open Letter on Banning Uber From Operating in BC</title>
      <id>blog/open-letter-uber/index.html</id>
      <link href='blog/open-letter-uber/index.html'/>
      <published>2021-12-23T11:17:00Z</published>
      <updated>2021-12-23T11:17:00Z</updated>

      <content type="html">
        <![CDATA[
        <p>Mrs. Allevato,</p>
<p>I am the owner of a small, local, technology-focused business in Victoria, and was shocked and dismayed to hear your recent ruling blocking the operations of Uber in BC. The ruling is clearly anti-competitive, and reeks of rampant corruption. The meteoric rise of passengers choosing to use Uber and other ride-sharing apps is clear evidence that they <em>prefer</em> Uber over taxi services.</p>
<p>Perhaps you haven’t ridden in a taxi recently, but it is an awful experience. Last week I took a cab to the airport. The vehicle was smelly, rundown, and extremely uncomfortable due to a broken seat and seat-belt. This is not an outlier in my biweekly taxi usage. Of course taxi cabs will be in this state. They are rented by drivers who have no incentive to keep the vehicles well maintained. The cab companies have a monopoly, meaning that they can afford to keep their cab fleet in awful condition, since there is no competition to improve.</p>
<p>Worse, it cost $65 to get to the airport, when an Uber would have cost roughly half of that.</p>
<p>I can’t overstate this point: every cab ride I have ever taken in Victoria has been an awful experience. This sentiment is shared by many of my colleagues and friends.</p>
<p>Contrast this with ride-sharing apps, where drivers use their own vehicles, and have their cleanliness and behavior moderated by a convenient rating system. The drivers thus have an incentive to offer excellent cleanliness and service — first in that they are using their own personal property, and second in that their livelihood will be threatened by bad ratings otherwise.</p>
<p>None of these feedback mechanisms exist in the taxi industry.</p>
<p>Furthermore, not only is Uber a better experience for riders, it is also better for drivers. Your decision quotes the following passage from the report:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>during an ongoing driver shortage, it is possible that taxi company margins will be squeezed by fixed meter rates to the point where they cannot retain drivers even though taxi demand justifies it. The drivers will then tend to move to TNS where the hourly earnings are higher because of the higher average rates and the high customer demand.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>which makes the very clear claim that drivers would prefer to work for TNS than for taxi companies. I have lived in many cities with ride-sharing, and this sentiment resonates with my experience — every single TNS driver has told me they make much more money than they ever would working for a taxi company.</p>
<p>Compare this against the cab system, where drivers must rent a cab from the taxi company for a 12 hour shift at a fixed rate. A 12 hour shift is too long for any human to safely perform a high-focus activity, but the incentive structure of the taxi industry encourages drivers to work as many hours as possible, regardless of whether it’s safe to do so. My most recent cab ride to the airport was at 5am. The driver was barely awake and couldn’t keep his eyes on the road. I was genuinely afraid for my life, but, crucially, <em>had no other alternatives.</em></p>
<p>Ride-sharing apps don’t suffer these problems. The driver rating system incentivizes safe driving, and because they work on their own schedule, drivers aren’t punished financially for stopping when they are tired.</p>
<p>It is clear that ride-sharing apps are better for both the rider and the driver. Your decision has thus sold out to the taxi cartels at the expense of local people on both sides who long for a better system. The decision states:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>In the Board’s view, existing licensees should have the opportunity to start up and be successful in their business without additional competition which may be harmful.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The entire purpose of competition is to force better behavior from incumbents. Taxis exist to get people from one place to another. They exist to provide society a service. Society does not owe taxi companies the right to exist if they are worse on every front than a superior competitor — and taxis are.</p>
<p>Given these reasons, it is unconscionable to protect the taxi cartel, and corruption is the only logical explanation why the Passenger Transportation Board would do so.</p>
<p>I urge you to reconsider your decision to ban Uber from operating in BC. It is unconscionable and serves only to protect a parasitic drain on society.</p>
<p>Yours, Sandy Maguire</p>
        ]]>
      </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
      <title>Notes from My Copy of the Art of Doing Science and Engineering</title>
      <id>blog/hamming/index.html</id>
      <link href='blog/hamming/index.html'/>
      <published>2021-11-17T01:02:00Z</published>
      <updated>2021-11-17T01:02:00Z</updated>

      <content type="html">
        <![CDATA[
        <p>Sometime during the summer I had a religious experience. My girlfriend and I decided that we needed one day off technology and work every week, and we jokingly called it the sabbath.</p>
<p>On the first sabbath, I didn’t know what to do with myself, so I started googling for “what to do on the sabbath?”<a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"><sup>1</sup></a> I went through several listicles, with some good ideas and lots of bad ones. But one thing came up again and again: <em>study the torah.</em></p>
<p>What the hell did that mean? What does it mean to <em>study</em> a book that isn’t about math? I called Grace, my only friend who is a practicing Jew. I called her on the sabbath, which again I think was OK because the suggestions were big on catching up with old friends, and there was both a pandemic and a gulf between us.</p>
<p>Grace told me that studying the torah is all about getting together with a friend, reading the book to oneself (but in the presence of your friend who is reading the same part) and then interrupting your friend whenever an idea spurred by the text crosses your mind.</p>
<p>Sounds <em>cool.</em> So I called up my friend Andrew, who was the only person I could think of who’d be interested in such an arrangement. He was down, so we met up later that day at the cafe.</p>
<p>Since neither Andrew nor I were religious, we decided to pick a book more amenable to us, and we ended up on Richard Hamming’s <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/530415.The_Art_of_Doing_Science_and_Engineering">The Art of Doing Science and Engineering</a>. Hamming’s thing was <a href="https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/P5k3PGzebd5yYrYqd/the-hamming-question">asking people why they’re not working on the most important problems in their fields</a> — which probably didn’t make him very popular — but it seems like the sort of character trait that would lead to writing a book worth studying.</p>
<p>The result was pretty fucking fantastic. Both Andrew and I agreed we engaged with the book at a much deeper level than we would have alone, reading silently. And this makes sense — our first session was 3 hours long and we only made it through 20 pages.</p>
<p>I would <em>strongly</em> recommend this method of engaging with important texts. It’s fantastic.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, Andrew left town soon after, and I was left to fend for myself. I couldn’t find anyone else who wanted to “study the torah” with me, so I decided I would engage with the book by writing down quotes that I liked, and including my commentary on it. The remainder of this post is made of up such.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p65. This is typical of many citations. It is first necessary to prove beyond any doubt the new thing, device, method, or whatever it is, can cope with heroic tasks before it can get into the system to do the more route, and in the long run, more useful tasks.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Hamming is talking about computers here — the hardest problems he had to solve were on the worst computers, because they were the ones that couldn’t be solved by any other means.</p>
<p>I see elements of this in all of my open source projects. Consider <a href="https://haskellwingman.dev/">Wingman</a>, which is a general purpose tool for helping to writing code. But that’s a boring use case that nobody will get excited about. So instead, most of its features are to <em>divide what you want and write that code for you.</em> Like, way harder. There’s all of this potential to solve real, everyday problems for people, but nobody wants that because it’s too mundane.</p>
<p>This is food for thought in future projects; I keep forgetting about it and needing to pivot my project mid-way through. But what if it were in the game plan from the start?</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p66. Any innovation is always against such a barrier, so do not get discouraged when you find your new idea is stoutly, and perhaps foolishly, resisted. By realizing the magnitude of the actual task you can then decide if it is worth your efforts to continue, or if you should go do something else you can accomplish and not fritter away your efforts needlessly against the forces of inertia and stupidity.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Man, I feel like all of my ideas are stoutly and foolishly resisted. Especially when I was working on Polysemy, and everyone complained on every one of my progress reports saying it was a stupid project that was doomed to failure. But mainly I like this quote because “the forces of inertia and stupidity” is a great mental handle.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p73. As you go on your careers you should examine the applications which succeed and those which fail; try to learn how to distinguish between them; try to understand the situations which produce successes and those which almost guarantee failure.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Good advice that I’d like to remember. A big emphasis of the book is to make time to study one’s life, techniques and likely future. To put some time towards that, my attempts that usually succeed are things I can tackle by myself — I don’t usually play well with others. The things I usually <em>fail</em> on are projects in which I need to overcome the forces of inertia and stupidity; mostly because I just don’t have the patience for dealing with them.</p>
<p>See, that’s a fantastic thing to point out. I knew that, but I didn’t <em>know</em> it. And it’s timely — some friends and I are currently planning out a project that is both a team effort and against the forces of inertia and stupidity. Not a good setup, it sounds like. That’s not to say I don’t think it’s worth doing, but maybe that I should only sign up if we have a plan for how someone else can be in charge of the public relations.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p116. Generally speaking, the best design is pushing one or more of the parameters to their extreme—obviously you are on the surface of the feasible region of design!</p>
</blockquote>
<p>A great technique for engineering systems — jump straight to the pareto frontier and hill-climb from there.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p149. I had thus established the habit, after something of great or small importance was discovered, of going back and trying to trace the steps by which it apparently happened.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Another reminder to myself that I should make some time for this. As a matter of fact, I’ll put it on my calendar right now.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p150. Notice first this essential step happened only because there was a great deal of emotional stress on me at the moment, and this is characteristic of most great discoveries. Working calmly will let you elaborate and extend things, but the breakthroughs generally come only after great frustration and emotional involvement. The calm, cool, uninvolved researcher seldom makes really great new steps.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This happened to me while working on Polysemy. It was spurred on by an avoidable disaster at work, that I then staked my reputation on, and failed to pull off. My ego was bruised so I decided I was going to finish the project, even though I quit the job. And then people told me I was stupid every time I made progress. It was an <em>extremely</em> powerful motivator — though it also lead to some awful burnout.</p>
<p>I wonder if this can be harnessed more generally. Can I deliberately set up an environment that is hostile? Does it work if it’s artificial? Something to play with.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p152. Riding through north Jersey in the early morning is not a great sight.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Made me laugh.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p153. It pays to know more than just what is needed at the moment!</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The context: Hamming knew a bunch of theory in an unrelated field, and it helped me spot a new technique when a colleague asked for his help. This is something I strongly believe in; people are always asking “why is this useful?” and I never understand <em>why.</em> It’s useful because everything in the universe is coherent — even if it doesn’t directly help solve your problem today, learning cool things always pays off. Even if it’s just in building your appreciation of how coherent the universe really is.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p164. From the assumed continuity of the information measure, it follows the log is the only continuous solution to the functional equation from earlier.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is not how I think about math. Maybe it’s how I think about programming? But there is a thought process here that I don’t understand, and I would like to. Identifying thought processes that work for smart people, that you <em>don’t yet understand</em> is a very powerful tool: because these things are easily learned. The details, maybe less so, but the high-level approach is always easy to pin down. Future work for future Sandy.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p164. Put into other words, if you provide a capacity for some level of error correction, then for efficiency you must use this ability most of the time or else you are wasting capacity, and this implies a high number of errors corrected in each message sent.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>What an interesting way of thinking about system reliability. Hamming is saying the best messaging channel is one in which you add capacity until the noise is almost overwhelming, and then you error correct from there. It’s the opposite of what I would have thought — “obviously” you’d want a clear channel, with error correction in place as a last defense. But no he says, if you put it in, you damn well better use it!</p>
<p>I don’t know what this has to say about software, but I suspect it’s something very deep.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p176. It is traditional to accept, in the long run, that the definition we use actually defines the thing defined; but of course it only tells us how to handle things, and in no way actually tells us any meaning.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Context: Shannon pinned down information theory as a measure of surprise in a channel. But this is not <em>information!</em> It’s just a measure of surprise in a channel, which is a different thing. But because it’s called “information theory,” the name gets confused for the thing.</p>
<p>This one particularly resonates with me, because I <em>do</em> think about information as a measure of surprise. Like, I can’t even pretend to imagine it in any other way. The mathematical model has wormed its way into my understanding of the universe. That’s not necessarily a bad thing, but it’s an extremely interesting experience to notice that I am figuratively blind to seeing the world in any other way.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p179. In the first place I thought I knew very little about digital filters, and, furthermore, I was not really interested in them. But does one wisely ignore one’s VP, plus the cogency of one’s own observations? No!</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Damn. I see this when I look at climate change. It’s clearly a big problem, and (I think) I can see lots of good ideas that nobody else seems to be working on. But I’m disinterested in the field because it doesn’t let me use my comparative advantage of software.</p>
<p>It sounds hard to retrain myself in another field — which is an especially damming thought, because I have often thought to myself that anyone could get into software if they would just <em>try.</em></p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p186. I needed only a firm understanding of the aliasing effects due to sampling. It is another example of why you need to know the fundamentals very well; the fancy parts then follow easily and you can do things that they never told you about.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Again, this reminds me of a strong math education. If you only know how to run the formula maze, you’ll get stuck as soon as it’s posed as a word problem, or whatever permutation might hit you. This is a principle I try to live by, and I think I succeed.</p>
<p>Also, it’s a great quote that I am going to put in my book.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p196. When something is claimed to be new, do not be too hasty to think it is just the past slightly improved—it may be a great opportunity for you to do significant things.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>There is so much “new” technology these days. Blockchains, NFTs, machine learning. Every time I go to look at it I come away thinking it’s completely stupid. Part of me thinks “there’s no way SO MANY PEOPLE could be wrong about this stuff.” But the other part says “yeah, but you have significantly better fundamentals than most people in your field, and it’s your understanding of the fundamentals that makes this sound stupid.”</p>
<p>I genuinely can’t tell if this is confirmation bias or not. Someone help please.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p210. It must be your friends, in some sense, who make you famous by quoting and citing you,p and it pays, so I claim, to be helpful to others as they try to do their work. They may in time give you credit for the work, which is better than trying to claim it yourself.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I’ve definitely noticed this in my life. The more I try to call out people for their good ideas that I’ve learned from, the more often they call me back out in kind. There’s this interesting “infinite mirror” sort of effect, where we boost one another’s signal, by virtue of having our signal boosted in the first place. It’s something I’ve been staying cognizant of since the first time I read the book. Be generous with credit! It’s cheap, and pays significant dividends.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p218. Moral: when you know something cannot be done, also remember the essential reason why, so later, when the circumstances have changed, you will not say, “It can’t be done.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p><a href="/blog/brilliance/">This has bitten me before.</a> I would like to not be bitten by it again. Context: Hamming had published a book proving he knew everything he needed to know in order to invent the Fast Fourier Transform. But it’s called the FFT instead of the Hamming transform. That must have <em>stung.</em></p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p239. That is why I am suspicious, to this day, of getting too many solutions and not doing enough very careful thinking about what you have seen. Volume output seems to me to be a poor substitute for acquiring an intimate feeling for the situation being simulated.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Sounds like most programmers I know. I’m genuinely amazed at how often people say they check stackoverflow.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p241. An active mind can contribute to a simulation even when you are dealing with experts in a field where you are a strict amateur.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This one confirms my biases that smart outsiders can contribute to fields they don’t understand. Especially software people, whose key skill I see as being <em>understanding complicated things.</em> Outsiders see it as “pressing keys on the keyboard” or something, and are quick to dismiss my skills. <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/research/publication/composing-contracts-an-adventure-in-financial-engineering/">But Simon Peyton Jones can do it sucessfully</a>, so there is hope.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p245. An extreme case I had to solve because it was important to the Laboratories, and that meant, at least to me, I had to get the solution, no matter what excuses I gave myself it could not be done. There are always answers of some sort for important problems if you are determined to get them. They may not be perfect, but in desperation something is better than nothing—provided it is reliable!</p>
</blockquote>
<p>WHAT AN ATTITUDE. I have never had a job I cared that much about. Sometimes when my friends ask interesting software questions, but never at a job. This would be an extremely powerful skill to learn how to harness: <em>getting an answer at any cost.</em></p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p246. Why should anyone believe the simulation is relevant?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>A good question to ask myself when I try to convince people that I could automate things for them. Why should they believe me? I believe me, but how can I communicate that?</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p252. When I was occasionally asked to do some ecological simulation I quietly asked for the mathematically expressed rules for every possible interaction, for example given the amount of rain what growth of the trees would occur, what exactly were the constants, and also where I could get some real live data to compare some test runs. They soon got the idea and went elsewhere to get someone more willing to run very questionable simulations which would give the results they wanted and could use for their propaganda.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I’d never thought about sham science in this light before. Yeah, I know like the cigarette companies fund research on smoking. But I’d never considered honest academics might be fooling themselves into selecting colleagues based on whom they won’t be challenged by.</p>
<p>This is a harrowing thought. It’s likely not just scientists — I suspect everyone is guilty of this to some extent. Do I do this? Probably? But how do I find the instances, and how do I correct for it?</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p255. I made it easy to do the bookkeeping and the mechanics of the computer, but I refused to relieve them of the thinking part.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>cf. stackoverflow and Github Copilot, which take the thinking part of programming away. Jesus Christ that stuff scares me. Why are people <em>so</em> willing to give up thinking? How prevalent is this outside of software? A lot of the world makes a lot more sense under the lens that most people are actively trying to avoid thinking…</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p263. Does the pilot feel only the Fourier real frequencies, or maybe they also feel the decaying Laplace complex frequencies (or should we use wavelets?) Do different pilots feel the same kinds of things? We need to know more than we apparently now do about this important design criterion.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I’D NEVER CONSIDERED THIS. I have this bad habit of thinking the map is the territory, and would just find a big-O of the function and then trim it off. But yeah, obviously there would be physical effects corresponding to our mathematical models.</p>
<p>And yes, humans can “feel” acceleration and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jerk_%28physics%29">jerk</a>.<a href="#fn2" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref2" role="doc-noteref"><sup>2</sup></a> But do we have a perception of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fourth,_fifth,_and_sixth_derivatives_of_position#Fourth_derivative_(snap/jounce)">snap</a>? And if so, can we differentiate it from <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fourth,_fifth,_and_sixth_derivatives_of_position#Fifth_derivative_(crackle/flounce)">crackle</a>? I’m <em>very</em> curious about the answer here.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p266. My real contribution was: (1) the realization that we could simulate what had happened, which is now routine in all accidents but was novel then, and (2) the recognition that there was a convergent direction field so the initial conditions need not be known accurately.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Context: Hamming is discussing garbage-in-garbage-out as a concept, and saying it doesn’t hold. If you have attractors in your system, you will converge upon a good answer, even if your starting position is awful. A piece of conventional engineering that a) I believed, b) is clearly wrong, and c) I knew enough to determine for myself that it was clearly wrong, but didn’t.</p>
<p>I wonder how I can avoid mistakes like this in the future. What other false beliefs am I holding?</p>
<p>Jesus this book is a great exercise in humility.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p269. Good minds are still needed in spite of all the computing tools we have developed. But the best mind will be the one who gets the principle into the design methods taught so it will be automatically available for lesser minds!</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Popularizing excellent ideas is more important than having excellent ideas. This is a good thing. I’m reasonably adept at popularizing things. <strong>I should intentionally train this skill, because pedagogy is much easier to improve than raw brain power.</strong></p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p270. I had always claimed if the problem was important and properly posed, then I could get some kind of a solution. Therefore, I must find the solution; I had no escape if I were to hold onto my pride.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Just today I came to the conclusion that something was likely impossible in a system that I had made. It’s not the most important problem to solve, but I definitely would have tried harder if my life or job depended on it. And what’s worse is that it <em>feels</em> like there’s a solution; I just don’t know how to formulate the problem in order to find it.</p>
<p>This is definitely a tactic that can be deliberately invoked. I would like to get in the habit of making progress on hard problems. Again: get my ego involved. Precommit to making progress.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p277. Once I had decided to stay at the Labs and realized my poverty in the knowledge of practical electronics, I bought a couple of Heathkits and assembled them just for the experience.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Hamming realized he was lacking a skill, so he deliberately went out of his way to practice, even though he didn’t need the skill. But he figured it would be helpful in his understanding of the world. So he sunk his time and money into it!</p>
<p>I definitely do this with programming, and claim it’s why I’m as good as I am. Lots of silly exercises, just to develop new skills. But what about areas outside of programming?</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p278. Beware of the power of wishful thinking on your part—you would like it to be true, so you assume it is true!</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Fuck. I do this all the time.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p292. What you learn from others you can use to follow; what you learn for yourself you can use to lead.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>No real commentary on this one, but it feels true and it’s a good proverb.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p293. Kaiser is a very smart person, but his education had restricted his view of the use of what he had learned. The better we inculcate the basic idea with the pictures drawn by the professor, the more we prevent the student from later extending the ideas to completely new areas not thought of by the professor (and put into the graphic display).</p>
</blockquote>
<p>My reading of this is that maybe we shouldn’t necessarily try to aid understanding by way of metaphor. Because metaphors are inevitably leaky, and this will damage the student’s ability to understand at the periphery of the metaphor’s boundary. Maybe all those visual math primers I want to make are a bad idea.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p294. The students must master abstract pattern recognition if they are to progress and use mathematics later in their careers.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Another good quote for a book.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p302. It soon became evident to me that one of the reasons no theorem was false was that Hilbert “knew” the Euclidean theorems were “correct,” and he had picked his added postulates so this would be true. But then I soon realized Euclid had been in the same position; Euclid knew the “truth” of the Pythagorean theorem, and many other theorems, and had to find a system of postulates which would let him get the results he knew in advance. Euclid did not lay down postulates and make deductions as it is commonly taught; he felt his way back from “known” results to the postulates he needed!</p>
</blockquote>
<p>If you had asked me whether this was the case, I’d have said no. But if you asked me how I verify a new piece of mathematics, I’d tell you that I test it by throwing extreme examples at it that should simplify to some already well-known result. After all, there are lots of crazy new ideas, and if they don’t agree with existing results, either they’re wrong or you’ve got much bigger problems.</p>
<p>But if this is true — if all mathematicians are projecting earlier truths outwards, then the unreasonable effectiveness of mathematics is once again in question. Why in hell do all of these crazy abstractions correspond with reality?</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p304. The above example about Cauchy’s theorem illustrates my attitude that mathematics shall do what I want it to do.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This also feels true; formalizing ideas has a strong component of bending reality to your will. I don’t do a lot of math, but in programming, my god does this happen. I can invent abstractions on the spot that somehow make the computer do what I want it to — but exactly how I generate those is a mystery. It feels like lots of practice and analysis has gone into it, but none of that seems to matter when I go try and teach this stuff.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p313. Clearly Planck was led to crate the theory because the approximating curve fit so well, and had the proper form. I reasoned, therefore, if I were to help anyone do a similar thing, I had better represent things in terms of functions they believed would be proper for their field rather than in the standard polynomials.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In other words: “present ideas in the language of the audience, even if it isn’t the language most natural for the formulation of the ideas.” I run afoul of this all the time; it’s fine to do your thinking in a specialized language, but translating it to others goes much more smoothly if you can just teach some ideas, rather than a whole new language.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p315. There are smells you cannot smell, wavelengths of light you cannot see, sounds you cannot hear, all based on the limits of your sense organs, so why do you object to the observation that given the wiring of the brain you have, there can be thoughts you cannot think?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I hate this. Because he’s absolutely right, and it fills me with an existential dread. What if all the ideas we <em>really</em> need are wrapped up in the vacuum of unthinkable thoughts?</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p316. [The uncertainty principle] is a theorem in Fourier transformations—any linear theory must have a corresponding uncertainty principle, but among physicists it is still widely regarded as a physical effect from nature rather than a mathematical effect of the model.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Highlighted out of <em>extreme interest.</em> Is this true? If so, how many other physical “laws” fall out merely as byproducts of theorems?</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p317. Von Neumann… proved there were no hidden variables… but the proof was found to be fallacious, new proofs found, and in their turn found to be fallacious—the current situation being a toss-up as to what you want to believe.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>More extreme interest. Note to myself to go investigate this. My understanding is that <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bell%27s_theorem">Bell proved there are no hidden variables</a>, but that was in the 70s and this book was published in the 90s, and there is no way that Hamming hadn’t seen Bell’s work. I notice I am confused. I should remedy that.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p320. I have put the word “understand” in quotes because I do not even pretend to know what I mean by it. We all know what we mean by “understand” until we try to say explicitly just what it means—and then it sort of fades away!</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I disagree. Understanding is the ability to form a model of some phenomenon, and make predictions that correlate with the future of the phenomenon itself. I could draw a nice commutative diagram here, but the idea being that the following square should commute: <code>predict . understand = observe . wait</code>.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p321. Progress is making us face ourselves in many ways, and computers are very central in this process. Not only do they ask us questions never asked before, but they also give us new ways of answering them.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I get in trouble often by putting my foot in my mouth on things like this. I’ll ask people leading questions about introducing formal systems into their jobs, usually trying to automate away the boring things. People interpret this as me wanting to automate away the whole job, and, instead, seem to entirely shut their minds off to the possibility that their jobs <em>could</em> be automated away.</p>
<p>The relevance: a world we designed to solve all the problems that are solved today, but designed in a context of immense computation, would be a very different world than the one we currently live in. People are extremely eager to see byproducts of the current system as essential characteristics of the class of solutions. For example, democracy is a (bad) solution to a distrusted consensus-solving problem where agents can’t trust one another. It’s just trying to implement <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paxos_(computer_science)">Paxos</a>! But people get worried about representation, or avoiding corruption, or whatever when you try to suggest anything that isn’t democracy. But I digress.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p325. Creativity seems, among other things, to be “usefully” putting together things which were not perceived to be related before, and it may be the initial psychological distance between the things which counts most.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is a useful definition, and an actionable one too. I’m a firm believer in knowing about lots of things, and hoping that one of them will come in handy. It seems to work.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p327. This stage, moreover, requires your emotional involvement, your commitment to finding a solution, since without a deep emotional involvement you are not likely to find a really fundamental, novel solution.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Reiterating a point above.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p327. When stuck I often ask myself “If I had a solution, what would it look like?” This tends to sharpen up the approach, and may reveal new ways of looking at the problem you had subconsciously ignored but now see should not be excluded. What must the solution involve? Are there conservation laws which must apply? Is there some symmetry? How does each assumption enter into the solution, and is each one really necessary? Have you recognized all the relevant factors?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>More good thought patterns from a smart person that I’d like to emulate. I don’t have a dedicated process for finding solutions; I just sorta set my mind loose on the problem and hope something shakes out. After writing <a href="https://algebradriven.design/">Algebra-Driven Design</a> I’ve started approaching software design with the underlying question of “what laws should hold here?” and it’s been <em>enormously</em> fruitful. Throwing a few more “obvious things to check before diving in” sounds like it would pay dividends.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p329. When you learn something new, think of other applications of it, ones which have not arisen in your past but which might in your future.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Another thought pattern.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p330. We are, in a very real sense, the sum total of our habits, and nothing more; hence by changing our habits, once we understand which ones we should change and in what directions, and understand our limitations in changing ourselves, thence are on the path along which we want to go.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Inspiring. We are the sum of our habits. Habits are hard to change, and they change less often than we’d like to believe, but we all have examples of changing our habits.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p340. The second point I want to make is that many of you, in your turn, will become experts, and I am hoping to modify in you the worst aspects of the know-it-all expert. About all I can do is to beg you to watch and see for yourself how often the above descriptions occur in your career, and hope thereby you will not be the drag on progress the expert so often is.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Context: experts often get in the way, and science needs to wait for them to die before it can proceed. I see this in a lot of my programming communities. I don’t want to be a drag like this when I get to the top of my career.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p341. In my own case, I vowed when I rose to near the top that I would be careful, and as a result I have refused to take part in any decision processes involving current choices of computers. I will give my opinion when asked, but I do not want to be the kind of drag on the next generation I had to put up with from the past generation. Modesty? No, pride!</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The last three words here really change the tone. It’s not that Hamming didn’t think he was right, it’s that he was convinced that history wouldn’t agree with him. This is another good lens on our actions — how will history look back on us? If we can predict that, we might as well act only favorably along this metric.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p342. What you did to become successful is likely to be counterproductive when applied at a later date.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>You see this in a lot of well-meaning advice. When preparing for my first interview as a software <em>engineer</em>, my dad suggested that I fiddle with any nut and bolt that might be around. I was perplexed — what did that have to do with software? Why would there be a nut and bolt around? My dad very patiently explained that they wanted to see if I was predisposed to getting my hands on problems!</p>
<p>Clearly very good advice for engineering that is hands-on, but software is decidedly not! More generally, new techniques work well because the zeitgeist doesn’t know about them yet. But once they enter the collective experience, they get improved upon, and your old tool now solves the problem worse than the new ones!</p>
<p>The inventor of something knows the least about it!</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p345. “Why do you believe the test equipment is as reliable as what is being tested?” The answer I got convinced me he had not really thought about it.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I found a bug in <code>QuickCheck</code> last week, and <em>lots</em> of bugs in <code>quickspec</code> when writing Algebra-Driven Design. Those cost me a few hours, because your first thought is never that it’s the machinery that’s broken. And when the compiler has a bug, dear god. There goes your week.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p346. I had long ago argued at Bell Telephone Laboratories that we should form a life testing debarment whose job is to prepare for the testing of the next device which is going to be invented, and not just test after the need arises. I got nowhere, though I made a few, fairly weak suggestions about how to start. There was not time in the area of life testing to do basic research—they were under too much pressure to get the needed results tomorrow.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is just genuinely a really good idea. At Takt, in an uncharacteristically-smart move, the CEO spun up a task force of a few people to do R&amp;D into what our new platform would look like. They came up with a ton of excellent ideas in two weeks, and likely were too successful, because the CEO immediately shut down the team and said “this is what our new platform will look like!”</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p346. There is never time to do the job right, but there is always time to fix it later.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The motto of every software engineering job ever.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p351. Much of the reliability of the engineering guesses was transferred t the sum, and the uncertainty of the salesman’ guesses was ignored. That is not uncommon in big organizations. Careful estimates are combined with wild guesses, and the reliability of the whole is taken to be the reliability of the engineering part. You may justly ask why bother with making the accurate engineering estimates when they are to be combined with other inaccurate guesses, but that is widespread practice in many fields!</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I’ve seen this in my career, but never acknowledged it as such. I don’t know what to do about it, but it’s something to keep an eye on.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p352. Morgenstern points out that at one point DuPont Chemical held about 23% of the General Motors stock. How do you suppose this appeared when the gross national product (GNP) figure was computed? Of course it was counted twice!</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Of course it was. Makes you wonder just how inflated today’s economy is by false metrics. Does this apply to personal valuations as well?</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p353. Their reluctance to change the definitions of the economic indicators is based on the claim that a change, as indicated in the above paragraph, makes the past non-comparable to the present—better to have an irrelevant indicator than an inconsistent one, so they claim.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>So they claim. But having an irrelevant indicator is worse than having nothing; it will inspire you to do the wrong thing! How do we improve mathematical literacy?</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p354. Institutions, like people, tend to move only when forced to.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Pithy and sweet.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p354. Most economists are simply unwilling to discuss the basic inaccuracy of the economic data they use, and hence I have little faith in them as scientists. But who said economic science is a science? Only the economists!</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I was thinking about this today on the way home. I’m currently <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/40538538-goliath">reading a book on monopolies</a>, and am finding my perspective towards economics radically shifting. I’ve historically been very pro-libertarian/Chicago-school, basic it on little more than “it feels like the math checks out.” Of course, the author has his biases against these economics, but it’s a well-argued position I’d never heard before. Changing your mind is a confusing state of affairs!</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p356. Averages are meaningful for homogeneous groups (homogeneous with respect to the actions that may later be taken), but for diverse groups averages are often meaningless. As earlier remarked, the average adult has one breast and one testicle.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Underlined because I love the example.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p361. I also realized that under (2) and (3) one of my functions in the research departments was not so much to solve the existing problems as to develop the methods for solving problems, to expand the range of what could be done, and to educate others in what I had found so they could continue, extend, and improve my earlier efforts.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Develop new methods and educate people on it, rather than directly solving the problems. This completely aligns with my career trajectory, though not necessarily accidentally, since I was reading this book when I <a href="https://sandymaguire.me/blog/reaching-climbing/">quit my job.</a></p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p363. During my last two undergraduate college years when I was at the University of Chicago, the rule was that at the end you had to pass a single exam based on nine courses in your major field, and another exam based on six in your minor field, and these were mainly what mattered, not what grades you got along the way. I for the first time, came to understand what the systems approach to education means. While taking any one course, it was not a matter of passing it, pleasing the professor, or anything like that; it was learning it so that at a later date, maybe two years later, I would still know the things which should be in the course.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>OH MAN WHAT A GREAT WAY TO TEACH THINGS. WHY DON’T WE DO THIS? I came away from university knowing how to program, how to cut corners, and how to cram for tests. They tried to teach me a lot of things, but I was better at cutting corners and cramming than they at teaching.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p365. All the proposed reformations of the standard calculus course that I have examined, and there are many, never begin by asking, “What is the total mathematical education, and what therefore, should be in the calculus course?” They merely try to include computers, or some such idea, without examining the system of total mathematical education which the course should be a apart of.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>p365. Few people who set out to reform any system try first to find out the total system problem, but rather attack the first symptom they see. And, of course, what emerges is whatever it is, and is not what is needed.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>These two hit home. I fall victim to this when I look at existing systems, and say “why is this particular thing missing?” rather than “if I were to design this from scratch, what would my principles be?” Damn. Hamming making me think.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p367. I have stressed the importance of what currently is believed to be the fundamentals of various fields, and have deliberately neglected the current details, which will probably have a short lifetime.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I’m working on the second edition of a book right now, and this is a point I’m trying to focus on more directly. There are lots of techniques I could recommend today, but they’re only going to age the book. Fundamentals don’t go out of style, which techniques absolutely do.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p369. A second reason the systems engineer’s design is never completed is the solution offered to the original problem usually produces both deeper insight and dissatisfactions in the engineers themselves.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is a common characteristic that I notice in people I really like. Maybe it’s <em>the</em> common characteristic that I like. The absolute best programmers I know will build something a few times, because each time they get a solution they realize that what they’ve built is a solution to the wrong problem.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p377. In mathematics, and in computer science, a similar effect of initial selection happens. In the earlier stages of mathematics up through the calculus, as well as in computer science, grades are closely related to the ability to carry out a lot of details with high reliability. But later, especially in mathematics, the qualities needed to succeed change and it becomes more proving theorems, patterns of reasoning, and the ability to conjecture new results, new theorems, and new definitions which matter. Still later it is the ability to see the whole of a field as a whole, and not as a lot of fragments. But the grading process has earlier, to a great extent, removed many of those you might want, and indeed are needed at the later stage!</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Another point suggesting that outsiders can do far more good work than insiders, since they haven’t been accidentally selected out.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p388. It is hard work, applied for long years, which leads to the creative act, and it is rarely just handed to you without any serious effort on your part. Yes, sometimes it just happens, and then it is pure luck. It seems to me to be folly for you to depend solely on luck for the outcome of this one life you have to lead.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Inspiring words. My takeaway here is that it’s more important to be systematically building cool things than it is to be recognized for those things. Getting the right idea at the right time is likely largely a function of luck, but by building a habit of building cool things, you’re optimizing your chances of the luck striking.</p>
<p>Helpful for me, because I feel like I keep having great ideas that people just don’t seem to “get” — and it’s nice to have this as an excuse for why it’s OK.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p389. “Why are you not working on and thinking about the important problems in your area?”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I don’t know what are the important problems in software. P=NP I guess, and maybe then “what the hell do we do with all of this compute?” I’d like a better answer than “burn it mining shitty crypto” and “make graphics that look as good as real life.” What stupid applications of the most powerful tool the known universe has ever seen. Yeah, gun to my head, I’d say wise and effective use of software are the important problems of the future. So why am I not working on them? It’s not entirely clear where to start!</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p390. While playing chess Shannon would often advance his queen boldly into the fray and say, “I ain’t scared of nothing.” I learned to repeat it to myself when stuck, and at times it has enabled me to go on to a success. I deliberately copied a part of the style of a great scientist.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I ain’t scare of nothing! It has a good ring to it. Here’s me deliberately copying a great scientist in deliberately copying a great scientist.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p390. The courage to continue is essential, since great research often has long periods with no success and many discouragements.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This perfectly sums of Algebra-Driven Design. That book took 7x longer than my first one, a good chunk of which was spent rewriting it because I kept writing the wrong book! Endlessly frustrating and discouraging, but well-worth having pushed though.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p391. Not that you should merely work on random things, but on small things which seem to you to have the possibility of future growth.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Another good metric. You don’t have to work on big problems; small ones that seem promising are OK too.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p391. Thus what you consider to be good working conditions may not be good for you! There are many illustrations of this point. For example, working with one’s door closed lets you get more work done per year than if you had an open door, but I have observed repeatedly that later those with the closed doors, while working just as hard as others, seem to work on slightly the wrong problems, while those who have let their door stay open get less work done but tend to work on the right problems.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>My instinct is often to put in headphones and focus. I like getting work done in the short term. But I’ve been finding this to be more and more true. For example, I go to a weekly “open hack” where there are a lot of beginners talking about basic things! But once a week or so, someone says something that is absolutely brilliant, and it’s the sort of thing that could only have come from a beginner!</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p392. When stuck, often inverting the problem and realizing the new formulations is better represents a significant step forward. I am not asserting all blockages can be so rearranged, but I am asserting that many more than you might at first suspect can be so changed from a more or less routine response to a great one.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>More good strategies for solving problems. This sounds similar to “if I had a solution, what would it look like?”</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p393. I changed the problem from just getting answers to the realization I was demonstrating clearly for the first time the superiority of digital computers over the current analog computers, thus making a significant contribution to the science behind the activity of computing answers.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>It’s not enough just to do it well. It also needs to be done with style and flare, to help inspire lesser minds into seeing what the future could hold.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p394. At the urging of others, for some years I set aside Friday afternoons for “great thoughts.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Another reminder to myself. But I’ve already put it on my calendar, so there.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p396. Do you want to be a reformer of the trivia of your old organization or a creator of the new organization? Pick your choice, but be clear which path you are going down.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Fuck, this one hits me too. I spend so much time fighting in the Haskell world about stupid shit that nobody cares about. Is it “correct” that we remove <code>(/=)</code> from <code>Eq</code>? Absolutely. Does it matter? Not in the least. Dumb trivia.</p>
<p>A mantra I picked up from Sebastian Marshall is “don’t argue with peasants.” If there’s an idiot who’s wrong on the internet, don’t waste your energy trying to change their mind. Best case, you convince them, the world doesn’t change in any noticeable way, and you’ve wasted your energy.</p>
<p>“Don’t be a reformer of trivia” is another helpful mantra I could do well to pick up.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p397. I strongly suggest you adopt the habit of privately critiquing all presentations you attend and also asking the opinions of others. Try to find those parts which you think are effective and which also can be adapted to your style.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Erin often says I’m a good writer. I think she’s just being kind. All it feels like I’m doing is stealing the best bits of writing from my favorite authors and essayists. But maybe that’s all that being a good writer consists of?</p>
<p>However, I don’t apply this to other forms of media. I don’t analyze how stand-up comedians tell jokes, nor how good engineers give technical talks.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p397. Along the way you will generally have superiors who are less able than you are, so do not complain, since how else could it be if you are going to end up at the top and they are not?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Makes sense. If you’re going to end up at the top, you’re going to have to climb, and go past a bunch of idiots in the process. Which, counterintuitively, suggests it’s actually a <em>good</em> thing if your boss is an idiot — because it means you haven’t yet risen to your height.</p>
<hr />
<p>My first thought was to end the essay here, because I made it through all of the quotes. But I stole this format from an author I like, and in the spirit of analyzing good presentations, I’m going to take a moment and go see how he ends essays of this form.</p>
<p>Turns out he just ends them, without an afterward. But that feels like the wrong play, so instead I’ll tell you to go <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Art-Doing-Science-Engineering-Learning/dp/1732265178/ref=sr_1_1">buy a copy of The Art of Doing Science and Engineering</a>. It’s an excellent book, and you won’t be disappointed.</p>
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr />
<ol>
<li id="fn1" role="doc-endnote"><p>I realize this was against the letter of the law, but not the <em>spirit.</em><a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li>
<li id="fn2" role="doc-endnote"><p>It’s when you come to a complete stop in a car, and you get momentarily thrown forward. That’s a spike in the third derivative of your position.<a href="#fnref2" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li>
</ol>
</section>
        ]]>
      </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
      <title>TV is the Mind Melter</title>
      <id>blog/mind-melter/index.html</id>
      <link href='blog/mind-melter/index.html'/>
      <published>2021-09-06T14:53:00Z</published>
      <updated>2021-09-06T14:53:00Z</updated>

      <content type="html">
        <![CDATA[
        <p>For the last three years, I’ve been tracking <em>everything</em> I do on the computer. This is done for me automatically via a lovely program called <a href="https://arbtt.nomeata.de/#what">arbtt</a>, which records every window you have open, every minute. By watching which window is focused, and how the titles of the windows change, it’s possible to get an extremely good sense of what activity I was engaged in, at any moment in time, since 2018.</p>
<p>The original impetus here was to track exactly how much work I was doing per project. Having this sort of information around is wildly valuable in determining where your time is going, and whether it’s being put to good use.</p>
<p>Yesterday, on a whim, I decided to run a query against my last year of computer time: how much YouTube did I watch? I was expecting some embarrassingly large number, like maybe three or four days worth. To my intense dismay, the actual number was <em>30 days.</em> The horror! Holy shit — I was off by an <em>order of magnitude!</em></p>
<p>Not only is this a dreadful review on how good my internal sense of spending time is, it’s also a disgusting amount that I wasted last year. To put 30 days into perspective, that’s equivalent to 90 work days, or 9 biweekly pay-checks. At my current rates, this six-figures worth of productive time down the drain. Compared to my burn rates, that’s equivalent to about half a decade of expenses! Forget skipping the avocado toast, or sticking to a weekly budget, the amount of time I spent watching TV completely dwarves every other cost in my life — by at least an order of magnitude.</p>
<p>What the fuck.</p>
<p>Time spent watching TV isn’t even time I enjoyed. The majority of things I watch are <em>other people playing video games</em> that are 10-20 years old. Sure, there are the occasional math lecture in there, but actual <em>valuable</em> watching time is a tiny fraction of my total TV time. This is time that I’m not learning anything, that I’m not developing any skills, and that I’m not feeling better because of.</p>
<p>It wouldn’t even be fair to call this “wasted” time. This is simply <em>killed</em> time.</p>
<p>So, what to do about this shitty state of affairs? Life is too short to be killed like this — to be killed at all, really. The part of me that does long-term planning (“system 2”) — as opposed to system 1, which is good at following habits and seeking short-term gratification — recognizes that TV is a horrible addiction, one that should be purged with extreme prejudice.</p>
<p>The trick to breaking (psychological) addictions, is to convince system 1 that it doesn’t actually desire these things after all. But system 1 doesn’t speak the language of well-reasoned arguments! It only understands vague intuitions, wishy-washy feelings, and Pavlovian conditioning. So the strategy here is to communicate my system 2 distaste for TV via intuitions, feelings, and conditioning.</p>
<p>Last year, I read <a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B01EVMK0H0/">Allen Carr’s Easy Way to Stop Smoking</a>. It’s an excellent book, and I am not, nor have I ever been a smoker. My interesting in reading it was exactly for building intuitions on how to break addictions, and the book comes chocked full of lots of psychological tricks. The tricks are exactly what we’re looking for — convincing means of influencing how system 1 feels. They’re almost embarrassingly simple in how obvious they are — but yet they allegedly work anyway. And it’s not hard to see why.</p>
<p>For example, Carr never calls tobacco “tobacco.” Instead, he exclusively refers to it as “the evil weed.” He makes frequent analogies to how it chokes out the natural, beautiful garden of your body. He reminds you just how disgusting smoking is, by focusing on how much you hated it when you started, how it makes you feel powerless to addiction, to all of the cold nights you’ve spent alone, outside, exposed to the elements. How it makes food taste bland, and makes your teeth yellow, and he points out just how disgusting the stuff is that you produce from your smoker coughs.</p>
<p>It’s important to consider all of these downsides simultaneously. Individually, the cost of any one downside might be less than the pleasure one receives from smoking, and system 1 is liable to make the equivalent of the following comparisons:</p>
<ul>
<li>cost(feeling powerless) &lt; reward(smoking)</li>
<li>cost(cold nights) &lt; reward(smoking)</li>
<li>cost(bland food) &lt; reward(smoking)</li>
<li>cost(yellow teeth) &lt; reward(smoking)</li>
<li>cost(coughing) &lt; reward(smoking)</li>
</ul>
<p>System 1 looks at these comparisons and thinks to itself, “hey, since each comparison comes out in favor of smoking, I should continue smoking.” But, it’s important to remember that system 1 is really bad at math, and it’s cheated during its bookkeeping here. It’s incorrectly counted the reward from smoking multiple times, which is like if were to say “well the cost of this new laptop is $1 than my paycheck for the week, and the cost of these new speakers are $20 less than my paycheck for the week, so I can afford to buy both.”</p>
<p>The real comparison that system 1 should be doing is actually:</p>
<ul>
<li>cost(feeling powerless) + cost(cold nights) + cost(bland food) + cost(yellow teeth) + cost(coughing) ~ reward(smoking)</li>
</ul>
<p>If each of those earlier (incorrect) comparisons were barely in favor of smoking, then there is no way that the honest version will come out in the same direction. None of these downsides is unknown to the smoker, but often system 1 accidentally fudges the numbers, and the addiction seems much more persuasive than it actually is.</p>
<p>Of course, none of these techniques are smoking-specific. They are easily co-opted into convincing system 1 of anything. Like how much it hates watching TV for example — or should I say, how much it hates watching the <em>mind melter. While I sorta like having something to fill (read: kill) time when I’m feeling low energy, I recognize that my lethargic states aren’t </em>cured* by the mind melter —- in the long term, they’re caused by it!</p>
<p>Furthermore, watching old video games is a pathetic and ineffective way to attempt to recapture how I felt when I was young. It’s infantilizing — and no better than those adult children who cheer for every new (and inevitably terrible) Star Wars film.</p>
<p>Often I get pulled towards melting my mind when my wrists hurt — preventing me from working on valuable things. But my wrists are hurt by having bad ergonomics, usually when I’m slouching to melt my mind!</p>
<p>I think of the disgust I feel every time someone tells me about the latest and greatest show on Netflix that they binge-watched over the weekend. They inevitably sound like stupid programs (who <em>could possibly</em> care about tiger kings and octopus teachers???), and I silently judge these people. But I’m no better if I’m instead binge watching some guy play Mario for hours at a time. In fact, I might be worse, since Mario isn’t even novel.</p>
<p>What the fuck is wrong with me? How in hell did I waste a month of my waking life last year doing this shit?</p>
<p>All of these things sound harsh, and they probably are, but I can feel it working already. But system 1 also responds well to imagery. Here’s what should come to mind whenever I think about melting my mind:</p>
<center>
<img src="/images/tv.gif">
</center>
<p>This is an image from the fantastic music video for Blockhead’s song <em>The Music Scene.</em> I won’t link you to it for obvious reasons; you know how to find it if you want to.</p>
<p>So, I feel like I’ve successfully convinced system 1 that the mind melter sucks. But, as <a href="https://mindingourway.com/productivity-through-self-loyalty/">Nate Soares</a> says:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>A problem isn’t solved until it’s solved automatically, without need for attention or willpower.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In the spirit of this, I’ve also installed <a href="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/stayfocusd/laankejkbhbdhmipfmgcngdelahlfoji?hl=en">StayFocusd</a> to my browser, and have marked the mind melter as a forbidden site. By default it gives me 10 minutes a day across all of my forbidden sites, which is helpful in that it will let me scan videos for information, but isn’t enough time to get hooked. Furthermore, I’ve used <a href="/blog/reclaim-your-attention/">uBlock</a> to delete all of the recommendations on the mind melting site, so that even if I slip up, it will be hard to <a href="https://mindingourway.com/failing-with-abandon/">fail with abandon</a>.</p>
<p>Even though I’m pretty sure my new mindset around mind melting will be sufficient, it’s nice to have a backup plan.</p>
<p>Finally, it’s nice to have something to substitute this behavior with. If I’m still feeling burned out and low energy, I’m going to just pick up my book instead. It will scratch a similar itch, but at least I’ll have to exert some attention, and create some room for daydreaming.</p>
        ]]>
      </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
      <title>Enlightenment or: Music is to Language as Music is to Music</title>
      <id>blog/enlightenment/index.html</id>
      <link href='blog/enlightenment/index.html'/>
      <published>2021-02-24T22:24:00Z</published>
      <updated>2021-02-24T22:24:00Z</updated>

      <content type="html">
        <![CDATA[
        <blockquote>
<p>“The first principle is that you must not fool yourself – and you are the easiest person to fool.”</p>
<p>–Richard Feynman</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I had a small taste of enlightenment today.</p>
<p>When learning music, things like notes and scales and intervals are very often referred to as the “vocabulary” of music. The metaphor here has never been clear to me — I suppose they’re the boring things you need to learn and get good at before you can start expressing musical ideas? But I never took this metaphor <em>seriously.</em> Music might metaphorically be a “language,” but it’s clearly not <em>actually a language.</em></p>
<p>Except that I kept hearing this phrase, over and over. The notes and scales and intervals are the vocabulary of music. At least five books I’ve read on the topic have said so.</p>
<p>“That’s interesting,” I thought. All of these books must have gotten this language metaphor from the same place. It requires some suspension of disbelief, but it’s not impossible.</p>
<p>So, that’s where things stood.</p>
<p>This morning, I was tutoring a student in Haskell. We were working through some of the boring fundamentals — things that aren’t interesting in their own right, but absolutely need to be in place before you can even think about tackling big programming projects. It’s very, very, very easy to tell a programmer who has skipped the fundamentals; they can sort of run the problem-solving maze, but, lacking understanding of the basic building blocks, get stuck as soon as something is slightly out of place.</p>
<p>Anyway, we were working on this student’s fundamentals. And I caught myself using the “language” metaphor. “These things aren’t very interesting, but they’re the vocabulary we’ll need to express elegant thoughts later on.” Except, this time, it clearly <em>wasn’t a metaphor.</em> Having the exotic experience of needing to rewind my understanding in order to explain it to a beginner made me very aware of just how high a cloud of abstractions I work at on a daily basis.</p>
<p>In programming, the fundamentals <em>really are the vocabulary</em> of the language. And you need to wield them fluently in order to be able to focus on and express the vision. Every programming task requires writing case expressions, spinning up new types, and knowing exactly where to stick the monad. If this stuff doesn’t roll off your tongue, you can still sorta get work done, but it’s slow, and the vision never comes out quite right.</p>
<p>All of a sudden, music (and my last few years’ inability to make progress musically) made sense. This “metaphor” that everyone had been trying tell me turned out to not be a “metaphor” at all. At least, not in the literary way where we say “the night was a blanket.” Music isn’t <em>poetically</em> a language; it’s <em>actually</em> one.</p>
<p>The takeaway is very clear. I’ve been ignoring the fundamentals — things like knowledge of my bass’ fretboard, and practicing scales, and transposing things into different keys — because they felt boring and unrelated to the task I really wanted to be good at: playing music. But taking the language metaphor <em>seriously</em> and as <em>literally true,</em> everything makes sense. Yes, technique is boring and uninteresting, but it’s not unrelated to music; it’s the stuff that real musical prowess is gated behind.</p>
<p>At my heart, I’m a truly lazy man. You can see it in the <a href="https://github.com/isovector/everygoodboydeservesfruit.com/blob/master/site/posts/2019-02-18-manifesto.markdown">time I decided to try to learn how to get good at music as fast as possible</a>. There’s something dangerous about being smart; it’s that you learn that you can often find one weird trick that will <a href="http://www.paulgraham.com/lesson.html">get you the grades without doing the work.</a> That might work well enough if you’re just trying to wave your arms around and distract humans. But for skills with extremely observable artifacts — things like computer programs and music — it’s extremely hard to bullshit.</p>
<p>In my forever-quest to get good at music without doing the technique, I’ve been fooling myself. It’s not that technique is some side-channel skill that makes you better at music; as it it turns out, <em>technique is music</em> — or at least, it’s the stuff that music’s made of.</p>
<p>I don’t know how it’s taken me 30 years to realize this, but better late than never, I suppose.</p>
<p>Really makes you wonder what other metaphors you might not be taking seriously enough, doesn’t it?</p>
        ]]>
      </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
      <title>I Broke My New Years Resolution</title>
      <id>blog/broken-promises/index.html</id>
      <link href='blog/broken-promises/index.html'/>
      <published>2021-02-19T07:37:00Z</published>
      <updated>2021-02-19T07:37:00Z</updated>

      <content type="html">
        <![CDATA[
        <p>I broke one of my New Years Resolutions yesterday. And as an accountability mechanism, I promised that I’d publicly post the details of what happened. I’m embarrassed to share this, but it’s a small price to pay in service of convincing myself that I will do what I say I will.</p>
<p>But in an attempt to salvage some amount of dignity, the button below won’t work until you’ve read the post detailing my goals for the year, and pressed the new button on that page.</p>
<p>If I break the rules again, I’ll update this post. Consider myself warned.</p>
<script>
function rot13(str) {
  var input     = 'ABCDEFGHIJKLMNOPQRSTUVWXYZabcdefghijklmnopqrstuvwxyz';
  var output    = 'NOPQRSTUVWXYZABCDEFGHIJKLMnopqrstuvwxyzabcdefghijklm';
  var index     = x => input.indexOf(x);
  var translate = x => index(x) > -1 ? output[index(x)] : x;
  return str.split('').map(translate).join('');
}

function see_violations() {
  if (document.cookie.split('; ').find(row => row.startsWith('show_violations'))) {
    document.location = rot13("uggcf://jungnyrtraqtnzr.pbz/")
  } else {
    alert("You didn't read the post!")
  }
}
</script>
<button onclick="see_violations()">
View Website (2021-02-18)
</button>
        ]]>
      </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
      <title>Goals: A Retrospective and Look Forwards</title>
      <id>blog/2021-goals/index.html</id>
      <link href='blog/2021-goals/index.html'/>
      <published>2021-01-06T22:39:00Z</published>
      <updated>2021-01-06T22:39:00Z</updated>

      <content type="html">
        <![CDATA[
        <p>Today I want to talk about goals — both those of my last year, and looking forward into 2021. I don’t really want to talk about the first part, but <em>I guess I have to.</em> They say that if you can’t remember the last time you failed something, you must not be trying hard enough. And by that metric, 2020 was a resounding success! I failed most of my goals! So let’s quickly recap, think about what went wrong, and then talk about Olympic swimming.</p>
<h2 id="recap">Recap</h2>
<p>What were my goals for last year? The big one was to finish my book <a href="https://algebradriven.design/">Algebra-Driven Design</a>, which happened and has been both a financial and critical success. Nice one, Sando!</p>
<p>I was also going to go through all of <a href="https://portswigger.net/web-security">PortSwigger Web Academy</a>, which is an online sandbox for learning how to break into websites. I made it through all of the free lessons (some you need to buy specialized tools,) and found a genuine exploit in the wild on a Japanese-curry restaurant’s website. Victory!</p>
<p>Also I was going to exercise for 20 minutes a day. I think there were some weeks during lockdown in which I didn’t hit this target, but between swimming in the Andaman sea, skateboarding, riding a too-small bicycle, at-home swing-dancing lessons with Erin, a (very) brief foray into running, rock climbing, and eventually getting a gym membership, I’m counting this as a win. Though lack of explicit tracking my data puts an asterisk beside this one.</p>
<p>I wasn’t going to drink any alcohol in 2020 either. This one didn’t strictly happen, but in total I drank fewer than 15 beers, and had zero wine or spirits (but a little bailey’s on days that I found it hard to write.) I got drunk once, and it was for a good cause — my friend’s bachelor party. But importantly, alcohol is no longer a part of my life, and I’ve got a very healthy relationship these days. Occasionally I’ll feel like I want a beer, but when I get one, I’m never very happy about it and don’t end up finishing it.</p>
<p>So that’s the good stuff. Something I partially succeeded on was performing 2 hours of music. I played a 45 minute “concert” on my balcony in China town to a few vagrants and passersby, who clapped when I was done, so I’m counting in. But it’s less than half of what I’d wanted to do, and also I had a more “formal” setting in mind when I made the goal. <strong>C+.</strong></p>
<p>And uh, everything else went wrong. I was going to learn to love vegetables in 2020, and despite going vegetarian for a month, and a traumatizing French-onion soup incident, still do not love vegetables. I was going to compose 5 songs, learn a new programming language, volunteer for something, and only watch quality TV. Bad bad bad bad bad.</p>
<p>Also I was going to journal every week. Which stopped feeling so necessary once I had my life together. It would still come out when I had interpersonal things to work through, but all in all, I just didn’t need it as much as I had expected.</p>
<p>I was going to make a solid friend-group, and I hit the ground running when I returned from Thailand, ready to make that happen. Unfortunately, the GLOBAL PANDEMIC had other plans, and the exceptionally lawful denizens of my new home really weren’t willing to break the rules. I’m blaming my failure here on an act of god, moreso than anything I might have done.</p>
<p>Similarly, I was going to have set myself up in a strong community where I wanted to spend my next decade. While I moved somewhere, it’s been if not physically, at least spiritually, locked down the entire time. I have absolutely no idea if I like it here or not, because I haven’t really experienced it. But I made things happen with the love of my life, with whom I want to spend the rest of my life, so maybe that’s close enough.</p>
<p>So what went so horribly wrong? It’s tempting to blame it all on THESE UNCERTAIN TIMES, but that’s just not true. I mean it is, but it’s a cop out. What really went wrong, I think, is that I made a lot of non-SMART goals, that were output based, but came with no mechanism to ensure I stayed on top of them. And like, what does it even mean to “learn to love vegetables?” Idiotic play.</p>
<h2 id="the-mundanity-of-excellence">The Mundanity of Excellence</h2>
<p>Let’s change tack and talk about Olympic swimming for a bit.</p>
<p>One of my favorite papers of all time is <a href="http://djjr-courses.wdfiles.com/local--files/hcd%3Aarticles-and-excerpts/Chambliss-MundanityOfExcellence.pdf">Chambliss’ <em>The Mundanity of Excellence: An Ethnographic Report on Stratification and Olympic Swimmers.</em></a> Chambliss spends a few years following competitive swimmers across all skill levels, and analyzes what differentiates competitors of different skill levels. Its key results are that skill levels are discretely stratified — a competitor “may consistently qualify for the Junior Nationals, but not for the Seniors” or “may swim at the Olympics, and never return to Junior Nationals.” The claim is that this is not the effect of quantitative changes, but that swimming at the Senior Nationals is <em>fundamentally different</em> than at the Junior Nationals. Which is to say, that Olympic swimmers aren’t <em>faster</em> than their local swim-meet analogues; they are swimming <em>completely differently.</em> The discrete stratification of a natural result of this; being physically more fluid-dynamic than your peers might be an advantage to help you win at one level, but that’s a micro-optimization that is too small to bump you between strata.</p>
<p>Moving between these layers of skill, Chambliss argues, requires qualitative changes. In the swimming example, kicking harder than other people is a quantitative change that won’t excel you to greatness; but kicking <em>differently</em> will. Experts aren’t just “better amateurs.”</p>
<p>If generalizable, this has important ramifications for becoming excellent at your skill of choice. Playing to your strengths will help in the short term, but resign you to doing more of what you already are doing. Improving areas in which you’re weak will be more fruitful, in that it will unlock other areas for improvement — things that you’re currently unaware of due to mitigating your weaknesses.</p>
<p>To be concrete, I’ve been playing guitar for like six years now. And I’m embarrassingly bad at it for having played that long. For the vast majority of that time I didn’t really know what I was doing; I’d look up chords for a song I liked, ensure that it didn’t have any scary-looking ones, and then memorize that and strum the chords out whenever I had a guitar around. Often I chose ballad-type songs that were heavily singing-focused, so I could rely on being able to sing as a crutch for my bad guitar playing.</p>
<p>It sorta worked. I was “fine” at guitar. I had a few songs I could pull out and impress girls with. But I wasn’t good by any measure.</p>
<p>But then last year, someone played me a song by finger-picking her way through it. It was the first time I’d ever <em>seen someone do that.</em> It sounded really good, and it looked easy. So I spent the next week practicing that, and by god, my guitar playing got 10x better.</p>
<p>Two weeks after that, I called my friend Rory and we chatted about music for a while. I marveled to him about my newfound skills, and he showed me how barre chords are laid out on the fretboard. Not only that they are, but <em>what the pattern is.</em> It was a qualitatively different way of thinking about the fretboard, about learning patterns and landmarks, rather than trying to memorize what letter goes in every single one of the little boxes. So I studied and internalized this too. And again, my guitar playing got 10x better.</p>
<p>Three weeks is about 1% of the time I’ve spent playing guitar. Seeing a 100x skill improvement in such a short time, perfectly correlated with <em>trying new things</em> is good evidence in favor of Chambliss.</p>
<p>I see this a lot in programming too. There’s a stupid meme going around about whether some programmers are 10x better than the average. The masses shout “no,” but they’re wrong. I’m not sure if this is self-delusion or simply a selection bias, but the best programmers I know are easily 1000x better than the average. Maybe not in terms of <em>productivity,</em> but certainly in terms of problem solving. The best programmers aren’t people who have necessarily been doing it longer; they’re people who have been systematically tackling hard problems, and learning new tools, and most importantly, (gasp!) learning the underlying theory.</p>
<p>This is by no means a dig at the average programmers, nor an assessment of their worth. Most of the world’s problems are indeed <a href="/blog/brilliance">boring and require more tediousness than anything else.</a> Just because we have Dostoevsky doesn’t mean we don’t also need E. L. James — but it would be a mistake to say that these are two authors of the same caliber.</p>
<p>On this topic, however, Chambliss has some good news. Qualitative stratification is so important that it absolutely dwarfs the effect of “natural talent” or “hard work.”</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The top swimming coaches in America fall into the same prejudice, attributing success often to “hard work” or “talent.” Since they habitually, unreflectively, live at the top level (having spent almost their entire coaching career there), they never see what creates the differences between levels. The fact is, quantitative changes do bring success-but only within levels of the sport. 12 Doing more of the same pays off, but only in very limited, locally visible ways. One can achieve a slight advantage over peers by doing more without changing the quality of what is done.</p>
<p>Having seen that “more is better” within local situations, we tend to extrapolate. If I work this hard to get to my level, how hard must Olympic swimmers work? If I sacrifice this much to qualify for the State Championships, how much must they sacrifice? We believe, extrapolating from what we learn about success at our own level, that they must work unbelievably hard, must feel incredible pressure, must sacrifice more and more to become successful. Assuming implicitly that stratification in sports is continuous rather than discrete (that the differences are quantitative) we believe that top athletes do unbelievable things. In short, we believe that they must be superhuman.</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="looking-forwards">Looking Forwards</h2>
<p>So what’s the takeaway here? Systematically try new things when practicing. I made a list the other day of potential interventions for all of my hobbies — programming, electronics, math, fitness, music — and also just in how I conduct myself in my relationships and in life more generally. In <em>less than ten minutes,</em> I had at least five things for each activity, things that it was completely self-evident that adopting these things would drastically improve my performance. And it wasn’t even hard to come up with. My brain <em>already knew</em> all the stuff I should have been doing all along. It just felt like hard work, so I didn’t even try.</p>
<p>The trick, I think, is to prioritize the trying of new things over the supposed benefits they’ll bring. It’s much easier to fuck around on guitar than it is to DO EXERCISES THAT YOU DON’T WANT TO BUT KNOW WILL MAKE YOU A BETTER GUITAR PLAYER. Even though these two activities are the same thing. That’s not to say I’m allowed to slack off in my practice of these things, but I’m already good at that. What I’m not good at is introducing new ideas into my practice routine, which systematic diversification will help with.</p>
<p>So that’s my goal for 2021 — to “do things differently.” I’ve put together a spreadsheet that I can pull up with a single keystroke, and <em>solemnly swear</em> to update it every day with one thing that I did differently. There are no other restrictions here, I trust that I’ll move in the right direction if I take a step everyday. What a SMART goal.</p>
<p>Oh, and also, I’m going to stop watching pornography. It lowers my libido and makes me feel bad. So why do it? Great question. To keep myself accountable here, I am pre-committing to publicly post a link to any pornography I consume in 2021. That would be embarrassing as heck. If failure is really expensive, you simply won’t fail. But it’s scary! I’m tracking this on my spreadsheet as well.</p>
<p><strong>Edit 2021-02-19</strong> I broke this resolution yesterday. There’s a new post keeping myself accountable, but you need to press this button first:</p>
<script>
function set_violations() {
  document.cookie = "show_violations=true; path=/blog; expires=Fri, 31 Dec 9999 23:59:59 GMT";
  alert("OK")
  }
</script>
<button onclick="set_violations()">
Press to Enable Viewing My Broken Resolutions
</button>
<p>So those are my goals! Here’s to a much better year than the last.</p>
        ]]>
      </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
      <title>Thanks for a Great Year, 2020</title>
      <id>blog/thanks-2020/index.html</id>
      <link href='blog/thanks-2020/index.html'/>
      <published>2020-12-24T02:02:00Z</published>
      <updated>2020-12-24T02:02:00Z</updated>

      <content type="html">
        <![CDATA[
        <h2 id="southeast-asia">Southeast Asia</h2>
<p>What a weird year 2020 has been. It started in Bangkok, having gone all the way down to the busiest place I’ve ever been in my entire life to see some fireworks. And then, when we got there 10 minutes before the fireworks, we somehow decided to not go watch them. Whoops.</p>
<p>After one of the most amazing jazz concerts of my life to see Tran Manh Tuan, Natalia and I then headed to Saigon, where we spent a week bickering and went on a truly awful walking tour of the city. N said she hated cities, so we took a 19 hour train ride into the rural middle of Vietnam. And promptly promptly broke up when we got there. Somehow she convinced me to pay for her flight out of the country. As far as getting rid of exes, $60 isn’t such a bad deal, but I think she got the better end of it.</p>
<p>So I trundled back to Koh Lanta, the first place since Denver to felt like home. I was there for about two months, having found a villa apartment, and hanging out at the <a href="https://www.hostelworld.com/hosteldetails.php/Hub-of-Joys/Koh-Lanta/273529">Hub of Joys</a> — an amazing hostel on the island. I’d chosen the apartment (furnished!) because it came with a kitchen and I was feeling optimistic about cooking, despite not knowing how, not having a grocery store, and living in a country where a restaurant meal will set you back less $1. The extremely sassy manager of the apartments gave me a tour of the place, and it was exactly what I wanted.</p>
<p>My evenings were spent at the Hub, schmoozing with new people on the daily. For whatever reason, the Hub mainly attracts young, single, German women, so between that and nightly karaoke, I was pretty occupied. The day I was supposed to take possession of my apartment, I’d convinced one such German woman to come check it out with me. When we got there, it wasn’t at all the place the sassy manager had shown me! Instead of a glorious king-sized bed with an ocean view, I was instead saddled with five(!) single beds. The German woman wasn’t impressed, and went home.</p>
<p>After complaining to the sassy manager, two Thai men came <em>running</em> up the hill carrying a giant mattress. I think it might have been a show to make me feel bad, but knowing that didn’t make it feel less bad. While we waited for the staff to make a new bedroom right before my eyes. It happened impressively fast, but it was still slow as hell. The sassy manager hung out the whole time, and asked me to play a song on the guitar for her. I sang the first thing that came to mind, and she said “oh, a love song? no thanks” — it wasn’t — and we spent the rest of the time in uncomfortable silence.</p>
<p>My neighbors eventually came around to say hi. They were grandparents from Sweden, and were very suspicious of this young man who had come to live in their community. They’d somehow heard about the fuss I made about having a kitchen, and would regularly check up on me to see if I’d been using it.</p>
<p>In the mornings, I’d work on writing <a href="https://algebradriven.design/">my book.</a> The afternoons were spent swimming, lounging around on the beach, and playing guitar. And in the evening, back to the Hub to hone my social skills and inevitably try to persuade Germans to come to karaoke. It didn’t often work, but when it did, great nights always followed.</p>
<p>What a life of luxury I led.</p>
<p>After a few weeks of this, it came to my attention that I was <em>happy.</em> Ask anyone; that’s not a feeling I’m particularly familiar with. That’s not to say I’m depressed or sad or anything. My life is excellent, but I’d never really <em>felt</em> it before, viscerally. Partly it was just unwinding; after <a href="https://reasonablypolymorphic.com/erdos/">living on couches for four months</a> and <a href="https://sandymaguire.me/blog/burnout/">breaking down</a>, I really needed some “me” time. But also, for the first time in my life, I noticed how good I had become, socially.</p>
<p>For the vast majority of my life, I’d been a shy kid, who wasn’t particularly good at talking to new people, or dealing with social situations. I’d turned to alcohol as a crutch when I hit 19, but ten years later was now sober and, I realized, completely in control of social encounters. I could organize groups, change the energy level of the room, and get shy people engaged and opened-up. I could reliably get into deep, interesting conversations with people. And, amazingly to 16-year-old me, had women throwing themselves at me.</p>
<p>Somehow, I’d gotten really good at social situations, and hadn’t noticed it until early February. I think until then, I had been carrying around the memory of <em>the person I used to be,</em> while thinking it still applied. Shedding that false identity is the most powerful experience I’ve ever had. Funny that I needed to run to the other side of the world and play guitar and flirt with German girls in order to make that happen — it’s not exactly the hero’s journey.</p>
<p>Of the many incredible people I met and spent tie with, some exceptional ones were Liam, Tobi, Lucie and Katha — with whom I put more trust than I was comfortable, and was richly rewarded in the resulting interactions. I love you all, for our discussions about overthrowing governments, for our impromptu trip to Krabi Town, for using my head as a jenga platform, and just for your intellectual and emotional companionship.</p>
<p>In February, my old friend and occasional lover Erin came to visit. There are no words to describe the joy I experienced as she walked across the hotel lobby to come say hi. The next ten days were a flurry of terrible tourist islands, non-air-conditioned bungalows, witnessing a child bride be married off, never-ending intellectual discussions. Oh, and I kicked a sea urchin at some point, so also hobbling around and spending hours soaking my toes in vinegar held in an empty cup-noodles container.</p>
<p>After too many days on Koh Lipe, we decided to leave, and I brought Erin back to Koh Lanta. We got some excellent khao soi, some iffy sushi, and the karaoke performance of a lifetime. I introduced her to my Thai hostel family. Tong and Noisy knew there was something special about the way Erin and I felt about each other, and they presented us with chop sticks on our final goodbye — apparently a Thai wedding tradition. Portent.</p>
<p>Erin sugared us with fancy hotel rooms when we went to Phuket, but was unable to deal with it due to getting probably-covid. We’re not sure what it was exactly, but she was out of commission for a few days and we were both genuinely — though momentarily — concerned she might die. But she didn’t! And instead we shared a cab to the airport, where she headed back to Canada, and I made my way to Chiang Mai.</p>
<p>Chiang Mai was where my previous transformation happened, back in 2017, when I decided to <a href="https://sandymaguire.me/blog/reaching-climbing/">quit my job and retire.</a> Unfortunately, I came to the conclusion that it was the circumstances (and more importantly, the people) who made Chiang Mai magical the last time around. Without Sam, Job and Dan, the place just wasn’t the same. My week in Chiang Mai was lonely, but I did make some geo-tagging stickers of my face that I distributed to the random travelers I met. To date, they’ve been scanned in 18 different cities across the globe, and I still have like 500 in my closet to put up when the world reopens.</p>
<p>My Thai visa was about to expire, so my plan was to head to Korea and then to Japan. But COVID struck in full force, and both countries were closed to me. Due to lots of unsolicited advice from back home, I was convinced to return to Canada, but still had a week to kill. I spent it in a quiet hostel in Bangkok on Erin’s recommendation where I met some cute Thai nurses whom I liked (“you are very strong and handsome boy”), and a tech-bro-startup-dude that I didn’t. That week I made some incredible breakthroughs on my book, eventually stumbling across the eventual linchpin of the final product.</p>
<p>While I was there, I discovered a love for Japanese curry, and also discovered my first real security vulnerability in the website for Japanese curry. Mark one of my yearly goals off!</p>
<p>I ran into my ex-girlfriend Dana in Bangkok, who had been traveling continuously since we’d broken up (on good terms) in 2017. It was great to see her, and we had a few fun days bopping around the city and catching up. I was headed for the Canadian winter in two days, and she helped me put together a last-minute, weather-appropriate outfit for it.</p>
<h2 id="getting-settled">Getting Settled</h2>
<p>March 9th, and I whooshed back to Canada. I got into the country a few hours before they started telling people to self-quarantine at the border, so I get off scot free. The next few days were spent with my friend Andrew, who was kind enough to host a potentially deadly human on his couch. That night we got a few of the lads together and witnessed the genesis of the spectacular ∞-groupoid chat. I was <a href="https://sandymaguire.me/blog/best-place-to-live/">en-route for Victoria</a> During my stay, I convinced Andrew to move to Victoria with me, and we hit the island.</p>
<p>Victoria. My new home. But I didn’t yet have a place to live, so I hit the only hostel in town that was still open — the unfortunately named Hostelling Internation Victoria. And my god did HIV live up to its name. Without a doubt, it was the worst hostel I’ve ever stayed at. My dorm was full of 40 men, with the exact smell you’d expect from a dorm full of 40 semi-homeless men. There were bed-bugs, no community vibe whatsoever, and it was cold as shit. I was supposed to stay 14 days but only managed two; it was the man snoring at a record 78dB — louder than a vacuum cleaner. I know, because I measured it.</p>
<p>Instead I found a room in a shared airbnb apartment, run by some chill people. It would have been fine, but they smoked a loooot of weed, which I find exceptionally distracting. Although they didn’t say anything, I could tell they were uncomfortable having me there during the days of our GLOBAL PANDEMIC. It was nice base of operations while I recovered from the HIV, but it was time to move on and find a place of my own. Before I took off, my hosts set me up on a blind date because, and I quote, “you both like candy.” Needless to say, the date didn’t go well, nor was it helped by her grandfather dying earlier in the day.</p>
<p>I’d bought a skateboard since moving to Victoria, and the early days of the lockdown were amazing. There were no cars on the road, so I moved house by skating down the middle of the street, tugging my roller suitcase behind me. Sandy “King of the Road” Maguire.</p>
<p>What followed was an endless procession of airbnbs. There was a weird executive suite. A loft apartment with bad sound-proofing where all of the neighbors would complain if you had the audacity to go up to your loft. The very Chinese apartment, owned by a white man and his latina wife. I stayed at the last of these for a month, and used the opportunity to buy a piano as something to help keep me sane. I played an hour-long concert on my balcony, to the thunderous applause of three homeless people and one racist man.</p>
<p>Erin coincidentally lives in Victoria — so we started hanging out. Our history has been a long, twisted one, going back seven years. In all that time, we’d been interested in one another, but never simultaneously single and co-located. Possibly aided by the GLOBAL PANDEMIC, we ended up spending a lot of time together and, despite our best efforts, couldn’t manage to stay apart.</p>
<p>I finally found an apartment — unfurnished — at a bit of a steal; the landlord clearly couldn’t afford the mortgage, so I picked it up at well below rental prices. The neighborhood seemed really nice, lots of food options, a grocery store, a jazz bar, but everything was closed due to the GLOBAL PANDEMIC. Erin helped me move my one suitcase and piano across town on foot, and we spent a romantic evening on the floor of my empty apartment, eating burgers and singlehandedly keeping the Canadian potato farmers in business.</p>
<p>With an apartment lined up, all that was left were the necessities of modern living: furniture, a bed, wifi and a phone so I could buzz people into the building. Furniture was surprisingly easy; IKEA just dropped it off and I spent a few days pounding dowels, twirling Allen keys, and watching Jackie Chan movies. But the other three? <em>Very challenging.</em></p>
<p>All of the mattress stores were closed, which meant I was resigned to the dreaded bed-in-a-box internet shopping experience. After what felt like 10 hours of doing MATTRESS-RELATED RESEARCH, learning about what sort of sleeper I was, and where my sleep pressure points were, and what sort of hardness sleepers like me should, and what my pillow shams said about me as a person, I was ready to <em>do shopping.</em> I splurged and bought the best bed for me according to the internet. But supply chains were backed up, so it got lost in the mail. And then they kept trying to deliver it at 8 in the morning, but because of the combination of <em>not having a phone to buzz them in</em> (a forthcoming story in this saga) and <em>not sleeping at the apartment because I didn’t have a bed there,</em> they failed to deliver it for an additional four days. Let me tell you, after two weeks of sleeping on floors and couches, nothing has ever felt better than taking that damn mattress of it its box. Not even the realization that my research was for naught and it was ridiculously uncomfortable could sully my spirits.</p>
<p>Throughout all of this time, I didn’t even have internet to help. I’d called the internet people well in advance, but you know how they are. They can never show for a week. When the guy did, he hooked up some cables in the control room, and told me to go plug in the modem and see if it worked. Unfortunately the modem hadn’t yet arrived in the mail, so he left, assuming it would just work. The delivery company tried to deliver the modem, but <em>because my phone didn’t work</em> (still forthcoming,) they decided that instead of leaving it, they should drive it 100km away and leave a note telling me to pick it up at my earliest convenience. There was no “we will attempt redelivery” info, nor was there a website, nor did they actually say where they were holding my package. They didn’t pick up the phone for 45 minutes when I called on a borrowed phone.</p>
<p>Thankfully the telco <em>did</em> pick up the phone, and I berated them until someone bit the bullet and waited on hold for two hours to get in touch with the delivery company. When my modem finally arrived, it didn’t just work. Apparently my apartment wasn’t in fact wired for ADSL, but the modem didn’t come with a cable, so I had to run across town to pick one up before I could learn that. Tech support then refused to help me until I tried a different cable, so I had to go back across town to get <em>another</em> cable. It also didn’t work. The telco said they could send a guy in a week, but he’d probably have to cut holes in the wall to install it. Yeah right, pull the other one. It has bells on it.</p>
<p>So I called around, and finally found a cable reseller in town. Their office was a five minute walk away, but due to the GLOBAL PANDEMIC, I wasn’t allowed to go pick up a modem from them. Instead they’d have to mail one. Another week of waiting, and, guess what! It’s a lemon! For christ’s sake. Two excruciating hours on the phone with tech support where they ask me if I was <em>sure</em> that I’d turned it on. And that I’d plugged it in. Oh, and are you POSITIVE that it’s turned on? Maybe try wiggling the cable. Eventually I convinced them to send another modem. Thankfully there were no delivery issues this time, and it worked the first time I plugged it in.</p>
<p>And during this whole ordeal, I was trying to get a cheap cellphone, just something that the front door of my building could call to get buzzed in. But all of the phone companies were closed due to the GLOBAL PANDEMIC. “Did you know that most problems can be solved at our website?” Not this one, and even if it were, not without internet, you bastards. Eventually they opened up in person, so I biked across town to wait outside for an hour while they allowed <em>one person maximum</em> into the store. I convinced them no thank you, I wouldn’t like the latest iphone. Yes, that’s right, a $10 plan is sufficient. No, I don’t need data with that. The man looked dejected, but took my credit card, and sent me on my way. Blissfully, the phone worked without any issues.</p>
<p>I caved temporarily on the data front while I sat in my unfurnished, unconnected apartment, with the rest of the world closed, while I waited for all of the problems in my life to get ironed out. But I couldn’t add the data plan, because they couldn’t charge my credit card. This was mysterious; the card was fine. I had used it to buy the phone originally, it wasn’t blocked, and I could still use it to make purchases elsewhere. It turns out the telco doesn’t know the difference between billing and mailing addresses, and <em>always assume</em> that those are the same thing. But my billing address was still in America, and for whatever idiotic reason, their online system wouldn’t let you fill in an American postal code. So, they could accept my money in person, but the online system couldn’t handle it. After an hour talking to escalating tiers of managers, the eventual suggestion was to “change my billing address.” Thanks so much, guys. I don’t think this one ever got sorted out.</p>
<p>I’m sure the system works really well when you’re all set up, but MY GOD things shouldn’t have been this hard.</p>
<h2 id="routine-life">Routine Life</h2>
<p>In late April(?), Erin and I decided to “go steady.” We were already inseparable, but this made it official. Out of all the marvelous things that happened in 2020, this event tops the charts.</p>
<p>Now that I was back in Canada, I decided to go visit my parents, who lived only a breezy eight hours’ drive away. It sounds crazy, but that’s pretty damn proximate for Canada. I rented a car, and went up for a week. It was great to see them, but I left as a firm believer that familial relationships are much better with some distance. While I was there, I spent a few hours cutting and sanding styrofoam that I eventually <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zdkyGDqU7xA">turned into homemade speakers.</a> This was the beginning of what turned out to be quite an active year technically and electronically for me.</p>
<p>The rest of the summer passed without much ceremony. My cousins moved to town, and their parents followed them, and <em>their</em> daughter and fiance followed <em>them,</em> so all of a sudden I had lots of family in town. However, in SUCH UNCERTAIN TIMES, due to the GLOBAL PANDEMIC, we didn’t see much of one another. In fact, I didn’t see much of anyone. Of the fifteen people I knew in town, only one of them was willing to hang out with me with any sort of regular cadence (thanks Nash! you’re dope!) The others, whether it be due to GLOBAL PANDEMIC, social anxiety, or maybe just not liking me, refused.</p>
<p>In an attempt to stay social, I started calling old people from my life whom I’d really liked. At one point I was averaging over 20 hours of calls a week, It was fun reconnecting with great people. Some calls didn’t go so well, but others — like with Ehsaan — we went for five hours straight. After two weeks or so of this, I burned out on social activity, and curled up, putting the same amount of energy into writing a book. But this wasn’t the end of my social issues for the year.</p>
<p>It came to a head when I attempted to throw a joint house-warming/birthday party for myself, after extreme social isolation for five months. All I wanted was for my friends to come hang out with me. Only two people RSVP’d. It was one of the worst feelings of my life. Instead, Erin and my cousins took me out for korean BBQ — <em>more meat than our bodies had room for.</em> A nice consolation prize.</p>
<p>The birthday marked the beginning of my third decade. To celebrate, I decided to <em>finally</em> delete my Facebook account. Not just stop posting, like I’d done for the last year, but to actually delete the account and all of its associated data. At one point in my life I truly loved Facebook, but those days are no more. I haven’t regretted it, and it wasn’t hard for more than three days. Strongly recommended. I switched to Signal, updated everyone I cared to stay in touch with about my new info, and took the plunge. The result is that I talk to fewer people, but the ones I do stay in touch with are the people I really want to stay in touch with. Good trade.</p>
<p>To do a bit of time travel, in July, Erin and I and another couple went to see a band. Live music! Joyous occasion! In retrospect I don’t think the performance was amazing, but the circumstances of <em>being out in the world</em> and <em>hearing music</em> was enough to make any event memorable. I spent the entire show watching the bass player, and in particular, noticing both how good he sounded, and how little work he seemed to be doing. My infrequent musical gatherings always had me unpromptedly ending up playing a bass line on piano, which never really worked out. Combined with the fact that I wanted to play more music with people, and that everybody needs a bass player, the solution to both problems was obvious. The day after I went to buy a bass guitar (giant scale!) and an amp, and walk the hour home with them. Uncomfortable, but worth it.</p>
<p>On September 1st, I finished writing <a href="https://algebradriven.design/">my second book.</a> Taking an uncomfortable action, I decided to reach out to one of the pivotal researchers in the field, and ask him to write a foreword. This man is not only the creator of some core pieces of technology used in the book, he’s also a personal hero of mine, and approaching him was scary as hell. But he turned out to be super cool, and agreed to write the foreword so long as I gave him a few weeks of lead time. He returned with a beautifully-written foreword on September 10th, and having received it, my book immediately started sales. The response has been overwhelmingly positive, and the software I write has dramatically changed for the better. Thanks to everyone who’s helped support me throughout the writing process; each and every one of you is fantastic.</p>
<p>The rest of September was spent quietly, taking some time for myself. The book took a year to write, so it was nice to not have an overwhelming locus for my attention. But I couldn’t rest on my laurels, so I spent the month as a vegetarian. Just to try it, you understand. The goal was to learn to love vegetables, but what actually happened was that I just ate a lot of broccoli and tofu. Erin and I signed up for the gym, started going regularly, and in my case, started looking really good (she already did!)</p>
<p>Or maybe the vegetarian thing was in July. It’s hard to keep track sometimes.</p>
<p>October (or maybe September) was thankfully the end of being vegetarian, so on a whim, I decided to try being keto instead. I’m not much of a planner, so I sorta just dived in, eating lots of cauliflower and ground beef for the first two weeks. It was fine, until it wasn’t. I’m not convinced I really got into ketosis at any point, but I sure got the keto flu a lot, so maybe that was me going in and out of ketosis lots of times. Under that lens, my weird food experiment was <em>wildly</em> successful — I entered ketosis something like five times in a month!!</p>
<p>During my <a href="https://reasonablypolymorphic.com/erdos/">Erdos project</a>, James King had the idea of a new way to write software. It’s an amazing idea and has always stuck in my mind. I made some progress towards it last year, but the underling infrastructure simply wasn’t ready for the sorts of things we had in mind. But in October, I read a blog post that suggested the technology was now ready for what we had in mind. I enlisted the help of my friend Reed, and we went heads down. By the end of the month, we had a working <a href="https://reasonablypolymorphic.com/blog/towards-tactics/">tactics plugin</a> for the Haskell language server, It’s now out in the hands of a few thousand people, and I hear a few times a week how much people love it.</p>
<p>My time lines are all screwy from here on out. During my month of keto, I realized my energy levels had completely leveled out. I used to take a giant nap every afternoon, thinking that I just got tired in the afternoon. But this didn’t happen while on keto. What was happening in fact was I was experiencing a massive sugar crash, and weathered it out by taking a nap. No sugar, no crash, no naps. So I spent a month just not eating sugar. It was amazing how good I felt, though I did have nightly dreams of skittles. These days I’m back on the sugar, but only in the evening, when I want to crash anyway.</p>
<p>I also bought a 3D printer sometime around here. It was an impulse purchase, but I thought it would be fun to have a way of turning software ideas into reality. That’s always been my biggest qualm with software: it’s hard to show normies what it is you do. There are no tangible products of an elegant algorithm other than the algorithm itself, which most people simply <em>can’t</em> appreciate. Thankfully my ego and vanity are both huge so I can appreciate it for them for me, but all in all, it’s been really cool to be able to make physical things.</p>
<p>In November I decided to take on a hard project and <a href="https://sandymaguire.me/blog/mastery-skateboard/">make a self-balancing skateboard.</a> I failed pretty miserably on this front, but in my defense, it’s now late December and I still haven’t received the GIANT SELF-DRIVING WHEEL that is a linchpin in the project. If I were truly dedicated to the idea, I probably could have made one myself, but I wasn’t and I didn’t. I still plan to build this thing, but I’m hoping the parts will come in first.</p>
<p>For December, I decided to make a roomba for Erin. It was my first true foray into CAD, and I immediately realized that I hated all of the CAD software. Of course, there’s a nascent Haskell library for doing CAD, so I picked that up and started trying to model the roomba. It was a much better experience than any of the other software, but it still crashed all the time. I made friends with the maintainer, and have spent a good chunk of my waking time since then contributing to the project with whatever things I find in the course of making the roomba.</p>
<p>Getting the robot to suck has been a surprisingly challenge; did you know not all fans are made equal? I think I bought three or four before I found one that does the job, and then I immediately wasted it by designing a bad intake system. Turns out fans move a constant volume of air, not a constant mass, and so, contrary to first thought, you actually lose a lot of suction if you have internally small pipe cross-sections. The software for the roomba was pretty trivial, and he wanders around the house and doesn’t bump into things. It’s cute to watch. The goal was to have him finished for 2021, but a few of the last parts I need will arrive in January.</p>
<p>All in all, it’s been a spectacular year. I’m feeling truly self-actualized; like the principled teenage-me, but with the confidence I was <em>sorely</em> lacking. I learned a lot of new skills, from security pen-testing, to algebra-driven design, to electronics and fan design, to the acoustics of what you want in a speaker. I wrote an excellent book, and nailed a few cool software projects. I’ve been sober for a year. I started dating the love of my life, and have set a lot of serious relationship milestone records with her.</p>
<p>In the words of Moist — <em>I love my life; it’s getting better every day.</em></p>
        ]]>
      </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
      <title>For Social Networks, Worse Is Better</title>
      <id>blog/facebook-vs-linkedin/index.html</id>
      <link href='blog/facebook-vs-linkedin/index.html'/>
      <published>2020-11-26T11:20:00Z</published>
      <updated>2020-11-26T11:20:00Z</updated>

      <content type="html">
        <![CDATA[
        <p>Some time ago, I deleted Facebook. Maybe it was for New Years? Maybe not — it turns out to not have been a very memorable affair. At the time, I had set up an alternative messaging platform whose philosophy I agreed with, and gave my contact information to the few people I actively stayed in contact with. For the most part, it’s been a smooth transition.</p>
<p>But something I’ve realized since then is that this strategy ignores the long tail of friendship. It doesn’t help me stay in touch with my coworkers from a few jobs back, nor from old classmates, nor my downstairs neighbor when I was 22. I mean, it’s not really a problem; these aren’t people I need to contact frequently. But I have a habit of reaching out to people whenever I think of them; it’s a nice way to reacquaint with cool people from the past.</p>
<p>Facebook is really good at these sorts of interactions. But Facebook isn’t free. It comes with the twenty thousand of some of the world’s smartest engineers trying working full-time to maximize the amount of time you spend on the platform. Its clustering algorithms are good at aggressively polarizing people and turning everyone into an extremist. Messenger and events are really the only good parts of Facebook. And until recently, the fact that you could expect everyone to have an account; although there’s been a marked engagement exodus of people under 50.</p>
<p>What Facebook is really good at is the network effect. But the rest of the platform is such an overwhelmingly bad experience that it spoils the broth. Somehow we’d all find ourselves scrolling through the newsfeed for the tenth time that day, seeing no new content, but <em>desperately hoping</em> for something new we could “like.”</p>
<p>And besides. I don’t really need instant messaging with my old colleague who now lives in India. We probably are never awake at the same time. What I really need from Facebook is a convenient way of contacting him.</p>
<p>Contrast all of this to LinkedIn. Maybe five years ago, LinkedIn was doing absolutely everything in its power to copy the Facebook recipe for success. They completely plagiarized the layout, although they were careful to make the blue of their design slightly more blue. After all, you need to differentiate yourself somehow! They stole the newsfeed, and added likes and reactions. But it never really worked. The content on LinkedIn doesn’t have the fake veneer of “important life events from people you care about.” It’s just virtue signaling about jobs and shit. I’ve <em>tried</em> to mindlessly scroll on LinkedIn, and I just don’t give a fuck.</p>
<p>Here’s the catch. LinkedIn has the same network effects Facebook does. Everybody is on LinkedIn — probably more of the people in my real life than on Facebook — if for no other reason than people forget that they have a LinkedIn account and so they don’t delete it. Unless you’re actively hunting for a job, nobody checks LinkedIn more than once a month.</p>
<p>By virtue of being so terrible, I think LinkedIn might actually be the perfect social network. We’re all on it, but we don’t engage with it. It’s a reliable place to find people I want to reconnect with. But by virtue of it being a “reconnect,” there is no need for immediacy in this. So I’ll send a message to someone on LinkedIn, and on average, they’ll reply in about two weeks. Which I’ll see two weeks after that. There is enough bandwidth here to negotiate a faster means of communication, but reconnecting with a school mate just doesn’t necessitate anything faster than pen pals.</p>
<p>And the (bad) network effect here is self-reinforcing. Because people take so long to reply on LinkedIn, I have no incentive to check it often. Which makes me take a long time to reply, and a) keeps the mean response tie high, and therefore b) keeps LinkedIn a terrible platform. And because it’s a terrible platform in terms of experience, it’s actually an excellent social media network. It sounds paradoxical, but the thing I like about LinkedIn is how non-addictive it is by virtue of being shitty.</p>
<p>Worse is better.</p>
        ]]>
      </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
      <title>Month to Mastery: One Wheel Skateboard</title>
      <id>blog/mastery-skateboard/index.html</id>
      <link href='blog/mastery-skateboard/index.html'/>
      <published>2020-11-01T12:11:00Z</published>
      <updated>2020-11-01T12:11:00Z</updated>

      <content type="html">
        <![CDATA[
        <h2 id="the-project">The Project</h2>
<p>Now that Algebra-Driven Design is done, I’ve been looking to branch out of my traditional skill-set. With the exception of a little break at the end of last year, I’ve been programming continuously since 2003, and have gotten pretty good in that space. For the last five years, learning Haskell has been my primary intellectual endeavor, but these days I feel like I’ve learned about as much as it has to teach me. It’s time to tackle something new.</p>
<p>Looking for inspiration, I came across the wonderful <a href="https://medium.com/@maxdeutsch">Max Deutsch</a>, whose <a href="https://medium.com/@maxdeutsch/m2m-day-1-completing-12-ridiculously-hard-challenges-in-12-months-9843700c741f">Month to Master</a> project had him pick up and conquer one ridiculously difficult project per month. These weren’t things like “learn to play Wonderwall,” but were “learn to draw photo-realistic self-portraits” and “build a self-driving car.” At the beginning of each month he’d introduce the project, and then write daily microblogs describing the day’s progress. I love this idea, and have decided I’m going to follow in Max’s footsteps and aggressively tackle my own exciting projects.</p>
<p>Today, November 1, 2020, is the first day of the project. My intention for November is to <em>build a self-balancing, one-wheel skateboard.</em> I used to have a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=XNqOU4jx62I">OneWheel</a>, which was the most fun sport I’ve ever engaged in. When I <a href="/blog/burnout/">ran away from Ottawa</a>, I left it behind, and have regretted it ever since. But these bastards are expensive, and, having fixed it myself a few times, not overwhelmingly complicated.</p>
<p>I have no idea how to build such a thing, but I’m confident I can figure it out in a month. I built some lego robots in university, and once soldered together a clock, but that’s the extent of my hardware knowledge.</p>
<p>My plan is to build a model-scale skateboard, in order to test my engineering prowess, and ensure I have sufficient understanding of the control systems. Doing it with full-sized hardware is a stretch-goal, though the parts are quite expensive, so I’d like some assurance that I’m on the right path before investing in them. If the month ends with only a robust, working scale prototype, I’ll consider it a success if the only hurdle towards productionizing is one of economics.</p>
<p>I’m off to get started. Will report back, editing this post, with my progress each day.</p>
<h3 id="section">2020-11-01</h3>
<p>Today was less productive than I was expecting. I found a tutorial on <a href="https://circuitdigest.com/microcontroller-projects/arduino-based-self-balancing-robot">making a self-balancing robot</a>, and started working on it. I’ve got the electronics prototyped out, but when 3D printing the chassis, my printer started running into extruder problems. (I think) I’ve got that sorted out now, and tried to print the chassis again; this time somehow my bed had gotten out level, making the print extremely stuck to the print bed. When wrestling it off, the PLA snapped. I’m trying again with a re-calibrated, hopefully better-extruding system, but the chassis is a four hour print. If I don’t have a sturdy piece by lunch tomorrow, I’m going to macguyver something together out of cardboard and hot glue.</p>
<h3 id="section-1">2020-11-02</h3>
<p>My recalibrated 3D prints went well; I seem to have solved the brittleness and adhesion problems. But I didn’t realize the pieces needed to be bolted together. Three trips to different hardware stores and two hours later, I hadn’t managed to find the right bolts. I knew I needed 3mm diameter bolts, but they don’t sell them by diameter. Instead they have meaningless designations like #7, #6 and especially confusingly, #6-32. The #6-32s were the smallest I could find, so I picked those up. But they’re actually 4.5mm, which is TOO BIG. Covid has the industrial supply store closed, so if I want to find these pieces locally, it’s going to take a minimum of two days. Instead I bought a big collection of random bolts on Amazon and paid the express delivery fee to have them before end of tomorrow.</p>
<p>I was vaguely aware of this eventuality; that building things in meat-space require parts that I can’t just magic up by downloading a library. I <em>knew</em> this, but I didn’t <em>feel</em> it until now.</p>
<p>Feeling underwhelmed by my progress, I familiarized myself with the PID controller libraries, and how my accelerometer works at a high level. I think I have a good understanding of these thins, and verified it by seeing that the PID equations can be implemented in 6 lines of Haskell. I also confirmed that my Arduino environment and build-chain is working, so that I’m ready to go as soon as tomorrow’s chassis is built. Disappointing day, though.</p>
<h3 id="section-2">2020-11-03</h3>
<p>My partner last night asked “why didn’t you just 3D print some bolts?” Gotta admit, that idea never occurred to me. Apparently I’m not yet used to having a mini factory in my house. So I tried that this morning, but my tolerances aren’t good enough, and the resulting nuts didn’t thread successfully. Thankfully my Amazon delivery happened in the morning, so I set back to building.</p>
<p>My new bolts are the right diameter, but are TOO SHORT for what I need them to do. Fuck. So I just started hot-gluing things, and that worked well enough. A careful hour later (the PLA chassis still feels very brittle), I had everything assembled, hot-glued, rewired, and soldered together. Time to get to balancing.</p>
<p>Some combination of “bad tutorial” and “bad engineer following said tutorial” resulted in me not calibrating the accelerometer while it’s on flat ground, so instead I just tried to balance the robot and run the calibration there. I have no idea how important this step is, but it’s something I’ll do when working on my skateboard proper.</p>
<p>After 30 minutes of tuning parameters, I got the robot balancing somewhat well. I’d accidentally soldered the drive motors backwards, so the first time around it would be actively trying to fall over. Whoops. Thankfully this was easy to fix in software. When everything was turning in the right direction, I found that my wheels stopped spinning when the desired delta got too big. Suspect: too low amperage on my batteries. Something to investigate tomorrow.</p>
<p>Also! I only fastened down the accelerometer with a single bolt (the chassis print apparently didn’t have a plan for mounting any of these things?) This lead to all sorts of instability in my measurements, so I eventually bit the bullet and just hot-glued the fucker. I don’t know if I’ll regret that when I want to reuse the accelerometer, but that’s a problem for future me.</p>
<figure>
<img src="/images/m2m/robot.jpg" alt="" /><figcaption>I built something!</figcaption>
</figure>
<h3 id="section-3">2020-11-04</h3>
<p>Major success! I got the thing balancing!</p>
<video width="558" height="327" controls>
<source src="/images/m2m/balancing.webm" type="video/webm">
</video>
<p>After a bunch of troubleshooting, I realized that my power supply was completely fine. The motors would cut out when asked to spin too fast. Since these are boring DC motors, they operate via PWM — essentially, sending an oscillating square wave whose ratio of high-to-low duration allows you to effectively drive the motor at less than full speed. The problem I thought was the Arduino’s pins; perhaps there was a hardware flaw and they were unable to emit the same signal.</p>
<p>I split out the circuit and ran an LED on the signal (much easier to play with than spinning parts,) and I observed the same behavior there. Because there’s no way that a single LED is overloading my power supply, the issue must be somewhere else. I wrote a quick Arduino program to just modulate the LED at 100%, and, to my surprise, it worked just fine. Which means it’s thankfully not a hardware issue.</p>
<p>Returning to the self-balancing code, I realized the original author had multiplied an expected negative value by <code>-1</code>, rather than calling <code>abs</code>. In his code, it worked fine, but I had originally wired the motors backwards, and had mindlessly swapped the <code>DriveForward</code> and <code>DriveBackwards</code> calls. Works great, except that now the values were negative when the code didn’t expect them to be. So it would negate my values in an attempt to fix them, which resulted in asking the motors to spin at a <em>negative percentage!</em> Thus the weird behavior I was seeing yesterday.</p>
<p>Fixing the logic resulted in the excellent balancing you see in the video above — on my first try! Apparently yesterday’s careful calibration against a completely-broken implementation was more than good enough for a working one.</p>
<p>So, that’s the first step towards my skateboard goal. I’ve managed to put together (and mostly understand) a self-balancing robot. That’s the major hurdle. All that’s left is to change the form-factor into something more amenable to humans. Which means it’s time to focus on design.</p>
<p>After watching a few tutorials on FreeCAD, I figured I was ready to get started. Rather than diving into a skateboard, I thought I’d start on something easier. My alarm clock is currently some nixie tubes connected to a bare circuit board, so I thought this would be a good opportunity to make a proper enclosure. It’d be boxy, but have some interesting angles and holes.</p>
<p>Four hours later, I was yelling at FreeCAD for having the world’s worst UI. Conceptually I have a great mental model of how to build what I want, but the tool doesn’t make it easy. I think I have a working enclosure, so it’s currently printing. Tomorrow I’m going to take the Haskell-based <a href="http://www.implicitcad.org/">ImplicitCAD</a> for a spin, which seems like it will better play to my strengths.</p>
<p>All in all, I’m feeling great about the project today!</p>
<h3 id="section-4">2020-11-05</h3>
<p>I spent today traveling, so got less done than I’d hoped. But nevertheless, got a good two hours in looking at ImplicitCAD. As a library, I’m sure it’s excellent, but my god is it missing the everyday Haskell usability. ImplicitCAD suffers from the usual problem of mathematics — namely that there are no types and all numbers, regardless of purpose, are just the reals. Positions? Reals. Rotations? Reals. Curvatures? Reals. Worse, there is no indication of what the axes are. It was a frustrating experience, made more frustrating by the fact that I don’t really understand the domain I’m working in. I’m going to spend tomorrow also working with Implicit, as I think I’ve sussed out enough to be able to get some real work done. But if that doesn’t turn out to be the case, I’m going to cut my losses and use some other CAD tool.</p>
<h3 id="section-5">2020-01-06</h3>
<p>Today I gave ImplicitCAD another go, and made some solid progress on it. I learned that the default camera is facing the front of the object, and that the coordinate space is <code>(width, depth, height)</code>. After thinking very hard yesterday about how to construct the objects I wanted, I managed to put together a parametric version of the enclosure for my alarm clock, and the result is significantly easier to manipulate. I think I’m going to move forwards with ImplicitCAD as my modeling software.</p>
<p>Tomorrow all of the traveling should have died down, and I plan to get in a good session with my father, the king of batteries and building weird machines. It’ll be good to pick his brain on the feasibility of a full-sized skateboard, now that I’m reasonably confident this thing is doable.</p>
<h3 id="section-6">2020-01-07</h3>
<p>Spent the day discussing the project with my dad, who had some great ideas about how to go about actually manufacturing this thing. He also showed me some good places to look for parts, and we found some promising wheel/motor hubs. Furthermore, regenerative braking appears to be something I’ll get for free.</p>
<p>I also started CAD modeling the board. I’ve got its frame all modeled parametrically, so I can fill in real values when I get the real parts measured. I’m still missing the electronics and battery compartments on my model, but it’ll be easy to get that figured out tomorrow.</p>
<h3 id="section-7">2020-01-08</h3>
<p>PANIC.</p>
<p>Today I spent a lot of time looking into what it would take to actually get this thing built in full size. I started looking at specific hub motors, and what sorts of power they’d require. After a few hours, I was panicking and physically unable to continue thinking about it.</p>
<p>Some problems.</p>
<p>First: I have no idea what I’m doing. The difficulty curve just of the theoretical engineering of this thing is already a significant challenge and learning experience. Physically manufacturing it is an even steeper one that I’m trying to tackle at the same time. The result is what feels like an impenetrable wall of understanding and difficulty, that I’m doubting my ability to overcome.</p>
<p>Second: economically, this thing is starting to look very expensive. Which is discouraging if I’m not convinced I can pull it all off. A few hundred bucks for the hub motor, the same again for the batteries, and then probably half as much again to have someone manufacture the chassis for me. Which feels like cheating, but which brings me to my next point:</p>
<p>Third: I don’t have access to any of the tools I’d need. I could buy them, but I don’t have the physical space required to store or use any of them, and this would dramatically increase my costs. No go. A maker space would be perfect, but there isn’t one in town.</p>
<p>Fourth: time pressure. I’m fully confident I could pull this all off in six months, given time to work out solutions to the earlier problems. Right now I’m further worried about shipping times; most of the pieces seem to be only sold from Chinese vendors, meaning a best case delivery of 10 days, but more likely closer to two weeks. That’s skirting the line pretty close if I were to order today, and I am in no state to be ordering today.</p>
<p>All in all, things are looking pretty grim. I’m not sure where to go from here, but I’ll sleep on it and hopefully things will look brighter tomorrow.</p>
<h3 id="section-8">2020-01-09</h3>
<p>Slightly less panic. I asked around today on some local forums, and found the Victoria Tool Library, which rents out tools. That’s a big pillar of problems knocked down. All that’s left now is to find some space, and I’ll be happy committing financially to the project. I’m not convinced it’ll get done in November, but the deadline is just all make believe anyway. Not a lot done today, but maybe I’ll work out a bill of materials tomorrow.</p>
<h3 id="section-9">2020-01-10</h3>
<p>I bit the bullet today, and bought a hub motor. It’s happening. Assuming shipping happens before the end of the month, I’m committed to making this thing happen. I also invested in a car share, which will make getting tools much easier than trying to heave a spot-welder around town on my bike. And I learned that there is a metal supply store in town that can cut things to whatever length I need, with no minimum order. It’s feeling possible.</p>
<p>Furthermore, I found a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=65Tv4kycUSg&amp;list=PLiYCRuOFm1MNj5a5LCCYhqoHpRu8Sc1Fx">Youtube channel</a> of some guys building the same skateboard. Today I went through all of their videos, and that gave me a much more realistic idea of what’s necessary to do. I’ve decided to outsource building a battery pack, because it sounds like a great way to explode my apartment. With that and the metal cutting sorted out, I think everything should fit in my apartment.</p>
<p>We gucci, baby.</p>
<p>Home tomorrow, and I’ll start engineering exactly what the frame should look like, so I can get the parts cut as soon as possible.</p>
<h3 id="section-10">2020-01-11</h3>
<p>Travel day, so not much progress. I bought a motor controller, pilfered lots of great stuff from my dad’s workshop, and realized I already have the right gauge of wire to carry the wicked amount of current I’m going to need. Tomorrow I plan to sort out the design of the frame, and get that sent off for fabrication. I’m feeling good about the whole project.</p>
<h3 id="section-11">2020-01-12</h3>
<p>Recovery and errand day after traveling. Did some more part shopping, and figured out the WolframAlpha keyword for figuring out if my intended aluminum rails will bend with my bodyweight: “beam deflection.” Looks like they won’t, so I’m good. Tomorrow I’m going to suss out if anyone in town builds battery banks, and ask if any of my friends have a drill press they’re not using.</p>
<h3 id="section-12">2020-01-13/14</h3>
<p>No progress these days, just waiting for parts to come in.</p>
<h3 id="section-13">2020-01-18</h3>
<p>So the wheel hasn’t even shipped yet, and it’s coming from China. I’m going to put this project on hiatus until I get word it’s actually on its way. Updates when I have them!</p>
        ]]>
      </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
      <title>Algebra-Driven Design</title>
      <id>blog/algebra-driven-design/index.html</id>
      <link href='blog/algebra-driven-design/index.html'/>
      <published>2020-09-10T16:55:00Z</published>
      <updated>2020-09-10T16:55:00Z</updated>

      <content type="html">
        <![CDATA[
        <p>Wondering where I’ve been lately?</p>
<p>After almost a year of work, I’m <em>thrilled</em> to announce the completion my new book, <a href="https://algebradriven.design">Algebra-Driven Design</a>. It’s the culmination of two rewrites, and comes with a beautiful foreword written by John Hughes, the inventor of QuickCheck.</p>
<p>In the book, we take a fundamentally different approach to the software design process, focusing on deriving libraries from equations, algebraic manipulation and well-studied mathematical objects. The resulting code is guaranteed to be free of abstraction leaks, and in many cases, actually writes itself.</p>
<p>If that sounds like the sort of software you’d like to write, I’d highly encourage you to <a href="https://algebradriven.design">give it a read</a>.</p>
<center>
<a href="https://algebradriven.design"><img src="/images/add.png" alt="Algebra-Driven Design"></a>
</center>
<p>Back to regular blogging sometime soonish.</p>
        ]]>
      </content>
    </entry>
</feed>

