<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">
<channel>
  <title>We Can Solve This</title>
  <link>http://sandymaguire.me</link>
  <atom:link href="http://sandymaguire.me/feed.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
  <description>Musings on effective life strategies</description>
  <category>Life</category>
  <copyright>2018 Sandy Maguire</copyright>
  <pubDate>2022-08-13T14:18:00Z</pubDate>
  <language>en-us</language>
  <image>
      <url>http://sandymaguire.me/images/favicon.png</url>
    <title>Sandy Maguire</title>
    <link>http://sandymaguire.me</link>
  </image>
  <item>
      <title>Sandy Maguire Escapes the Room: Lost in Space</title>
      <author>sandy@sandymaguire.me (Sandy Maguire)</author>
      <link>http://sandymaguire.me/blog/escape-room-lost-in-space/index.html</link>
      <guid>http://sandymaguire.me/blog/escape-room-lost-in-space/index.html</guid>
      <pubDate>2022-08-13T14:18:00Z</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[
        <p>For my birthday, Erin and I headed to a local (literally across the street) escape-room in Vancouver called Exit Gastown, where we played <a href="https://e-exit.ca/escape/games/lost-in-space-ecape-room/">Lost in Space</a> with just the two of us.</p>
<p>Online the difficulty is three stars, but I swear in person it was labeled as four. It’s always hard to get a sense of the actual difficulty between companies, so we went in expecting to escape. We didn’t. By the end of our 45 minutes, we were on the last clue — figure out a lot of math for teleporter coordinates — but nowhere near solving it. Alas.</p>
<p>Erin and I are very new to the world of escape rooms. This was her second, and my fifth, and neither of us came away very impressed with the puzzles. The concept is pretty great, but the execution left a lot to be desired. Let me explain.</p>
<p>LOST IN SPACE. You’re on a space ship that has crash-landed. The lights are off, so you need to get the power back on, and then find the teleporter room and teleport home. Or something. The crash-landing stuff was (very) briefly mentioned in the beginning dialog, and the only other clue to it is a window painted onto the wall that looks cracked. OK fine, except that this is a critical clue in teleporting away; you need not only decipher the coordinate system, but you also need to remember where you are in the solar system. And if you don’t remember from the initial briefing, well, good luck!</p>
<p>A few other dings. I liked the idea that the lights are off, but you’re given only one flashlight, which means your group can’t parallelize any solving. You start the game with an “engineering” binder explaining all the subsystems, and roughly how to go about accomplishing them. One of the things to do is to get the ship’s power system on emergency batteries, and then eventually running again, but accomplishing neither of them turns the lights back on! They’re just off, for 45 minutes.</p>
<p>The better design here is that the lights come on to 10-20% brightness after you get onto emergency power, and then turn on in full when the generators are running again. It’s an interesting gimmick that you need to get the power back on, but it needs to be rewarded, rather than being an arbitrary key to ungate progress.</p>
<p>Half way through, you do get a second flashlight. But the batteries were (unintentionally) half-dead and died before the end of the game. I had to leave the room to get new ones, which ate a few minutes out of our failed escape.</p>
<p>Most egregious, however, was the binder’s engineering list of “spare parts.” There are three spare parts listed: a set of jumper cables, a spare battery, and a wiring diagram. We found the jumper cables first, and five minutes later found the spare battery. So we were primed to think about the spare parts as literal objects that could be picked up. But then the wiring diagram doesn’t fit the pattern. It’s drawn onto the wall behind the puzzle, and is presented as the wiring itself.</p>
<p>The puzzle is that you need to shine a light into four holes in the right order. We fucked around with it for a while, following the obvious route implied by the wiring on the wall. At each step, the thing beeps at you. But if you hold your light on a little too long (we’re talking half a second or so), it beeps again, and that is the system resetting itself. Our progress was hampered by this for probably ten minutes before we asked for a hint — we could neither find the wiring diagram, nor could we brute force the puzzle. But there was no wiring diagram, and our understanding of the thing was entirely correct, it’s just that the mechanism was incorrectly resetting our progress.</p>
<p>Very annoying.</p>
<p>I’ll also ding the room for having several unintentional typos in the manual; usually things like these are secret clues, or something to decipher. Nope, here they’re just someone not using spellcheck, which doesn’t inspire a great deal of confidence that the game designer is a person of care.</p>
<p>There were some things I liked about this room though; the system to get the power back on was interesting. You need to find some jumper cables, put them into the right place, and then identify that the battery is broken, and find a better one that won’t short out the circuit. I like puzzles that require disparate pieces to be solved, rather than being one-key-one-lock deals.</p>
<p>Despite my complaints, I liked that the lights were off at the beginning. It was thematically interesting, but overstayed its welcome.</p>
<p>Overall though, I wasn’t very impressed with Lost in Space. Progress was entirely linear, and at no point did were we required to use information we’d learned somewhere else. Puzzles like these are frustrating: if you get stuck on something, you’re just stuck with no recourse. Oh well. This one is a nice case study in how to not structure an escape room.</p>
<p>Two out of five stars.</p>
      ]]></content:encoded>
  </item>
  <item>
      <title>The Cruise Facade</title>
      <author>sandy@sandymaguire.me (Sandy Maguire)</author>
      <link>http://sandymaguire.me/blog/cruising-facade/index.html</link>
      <guid>http://sandymaguire.me/blog/cruising-facade/index.html</guid>
      <pubDate>2022-05-08T05:21:00Z</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[
        <p>Warning: snooty and written at 5AM. Am I becoming my mother?</p>
<p>I’ve been out of contact lately; consider that a symptom of being in the middle of the Atlantic ocean on a Cruise. The idea was merely that it’d be cool to cross an ocean like our forefathers did, and a Cruise just happened to be the easiest way to make that happen. My mom, when hearing of this plan, said (rather disappointedly) “oh… I didn’t think you were Cruise People.”</p>
<p>And my god, are we not.</p>
<p>There are two good things I’ll say about the experience. It’s relaxing to spend all day in the pool and not need to worry about food. And, we have <em>clearly</em> managed to get outside of our filter bubble.</p>
<p>Cruising People are a peculiar bunch. Primarily American. BIG Americans. The sailing has 2500 passengers, of whom 40 are under 18, and easily 50% are over 65. I’d say there are maybe 50 people in our extremely permissive 20-40 age cohort, and a good chunk of those are families.</p>
<p>The on-board entertainment knows its audience, and it is not us.</p>
<p>For example, early on, we went to a stand-up comic’s set. The bits ranged from “you know how when you call the airline to make a booking, you need to navigate a lot of phone menus? AND THEN WHEN YOU GET THROUGH, IT’S NOT EVEN TO AN AMERICAN!!!!” all the way to “I sure am glad I’m not old!!”<a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"><sup>1</sup></a></p>
<p>There are shows and activities every hour. Bachata classes, karaoke night, lots of <em>easy</em> trivia<a href="#fn2" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref2" role="doc-noteref"><sup>2</sup></a>. The dance classes are nearly empty, the karaoke nights are full but non-participatory, and Frank Sinatra is chosen more than every other artist combined.</p>
<p>But Beatles Night is always packed, and is by far the liveliest thing on the ship. Those boomers be shimmying!</p>
<p>There are “Enrichment Seminars” on topics like <em>romantic comedies of the ’90s,</em> and <em>things you didn’t know about John Wayne.</em> That is, anything someone on the boat could plausibly talk about for 20 minutes. There was a (technically amazing) cabaret consisting of lots of flashy dance moves, without any coherent story or theme. There was an (also technically amazing) “theatre production” consisting of lots of flashy dance moves, without any coherent story or theme, but set to pop music that you’ve familiar with.</p>
<p>I have lots to say here. The ship clearly knows its audience, so we can work backwards from the shows to figure out who that audience must be. The entire cruise experience is an excellent example of [premium medicre]<a href="#fn3" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref3" role="doc-noteref"><sup>3</sup></a> — that is, “exclusive” without actually excluding anyone. Night 2 was a “black-tie formal night”, and they let my jeans-and-a-button-down-in-sneakers backpacking ass right in without a second glance. But it <em>feels</em> exclusive: it must be, because they keep saying so!</p>
<p>Over the first few days, we kept meeting cruisers who seemed genuinely shocked to hear it’s our first cruise.<a href="#fn4" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref4" role="doc-noteref"><sup>4</sup></a> “Oh you’ll <em>just love it!</em>” they would keep telling us. And clearly they did indeed love it; cruisers keep telling us about their loyal program; we’ve met many people who have spent more than 365 days of their life cruising. And we met one guy who has spent over 720.</p>
<p>So, who is this cruise for? The entire experience is a weird facade; lots of stuff with no actual substance behind. It’s an experience that feels classy, without actually being classy. Cruisers can point to the cabaret and theatre and enrichment lectures and feel like they’re living a refined life. They know that these are the sorts of activities that high-status people enjoy, and are delighted to find that they too like these high-status activities!</p>
<p>I have never seen a cabaret before, and thus didn’t know what to expect. I quite liked what I got, because it was well-choreographed and technically impressive (there were six robotic arms that were in motion the whole time, and never once bashed into one another!) But Erin was unimpressed; “that wasn’t a cabaret” she said.</p>
<p>Here’s what I think is happening. Take 250 fit, sexy, twenty-something dancers and give them a week to choreograph and rehearse a bunch of dances to pop music. Take the resulting three minute pieces, and stitch them together with the barest amount of thread to pass it off as a work of high-culture. Set it in “another world” to lampshade any issues in continuity or theming, and voila, you have a cabaret, or a musical, or a hip-hop dance class, or whatever you want!</p>
<p>What you’ve come up with is something easily palatable. It’s got flashy dance moves and songs that you’ve heard before. If you call it a cabaret, it must be. And someone (like me) who might not be familiar with the intricacies of cabaret can come away being impressed, both with the show, and with the fact that I am the sort of person who likes cabarets. I too, must be high-class.</p>
<p>The whole ship feels like that. Which is weird, because all the talent is genuinely amazing. The musicians we’ve met are all very accomplished session players. The ones we haven’t met are also fantastic. We met one of the costumers, who made a dress for Lady Gaga. We’ve yet to meet any dancers, but my guess is that they’re equally accomplished. But there’s a creative flare missing, and I’d wager that’s intentional.</p>
<p>And then there are the art collecting lectures. The first three days had enrichment lectures on how to <em>appreciate,</em> and, subsequently, <em>value</em> art. Funnily enough, the next day there was an art auction. How about that? I overheard a woman saying she spent $5000 on art: “I’ve never really paid much attention to art before, I guess because I wasn’t really grown up enough. But now I’m ready to start collecting.” Did I mention there isn’t any internet on the ship? Well, there is, if you’re willing to pay a years’ worth of internet bills for a week. I haven’t worked out whether or not most people footed that bill, but I suspect they aren’t using it to get a second opinion before buying <em>priceless</em> art prints.</p>
<p>The average person on this cruise clearly considers themselves to be on an adventure. They are traveling! And seeing the world! We’ve been told we’re very brave for making a trans-Atlantic cruise our first one; it has almost no stop-overs, did you know!</p>
<p>Yeah, OK.</p>
<p>The staff, however, are much more clearly our people. Millennials, working weird-ass jobs in order to sail around the world and send money back home. People who are interesting and adventurous enough to pack up their lives for a few months at a time. From them we’ve learned all sorts of juicy gossip; that the entirety of the 3rd floor is off-access not because of ongoing maintenance like they say, but because it’s the covid quarantine floor. And <em>everyone</em> is sick. Or, how five old people die every cruise, and how the ship has a special morgue freezer to keep them in. The staff recognize how ridiculous the entire experience is, and it’s a refreshing reminder that we’re not crazy.</p>
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr />
<ol>
<li id="fn1" role="doc-endnote"><p>This from a comic who was easily in his 70s, and not looking the better for it.<a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li>
<li id="fn2" role="doc-endnote"><p>eg. From which film is the line “may the force be with you?”<a href="#fnref2" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li>
<li id="fn3" role="doc-endnote"><p>https://www.ribbonfarm.com/2017/08/17/the-premium-mediocre-life-of-maya-millennial/<a href="#fnref3" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li>
<li id="fn4" role="doc-endnote"><p>And our last, but we are savvy enough to hold our tongues about that part.<a href="#fnref4" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li>
</ol>
</section>
      ]]></content:encoded>
  </item>
  <item>
      <title>Be a Lighthouse</title>
      <author>sandy@sandymaguire.me (Sandy Maguire)</author>
      <link>http://sandymaguire.me/blog/be-a-lighthouse/index.html</link>
      <guid>http://sandymaguire.me/blog/be-a-lighthouse/index.html</guid>
      <pubDate>2022-04-13T23:25:00Z</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[
        <p>A few times a year I’m asked by people what’s the value in maintaining a blog. To their eyes, a blog is a liability. Not only is it extracurricular work, it also, (they say) limits personal growth, since the old things you’ve said stick around. Furthermore, in today’s age of hyper-cancellation, keeping old ideas around is downright dangerous. Who knows what ideas will be out of vogue next week?</p>
<p>None of these problems bother me. I like writing — attempting to serialize ideas into prose acts as an excellent forcing-function. Writing it out makes clear the bits which are weak, and ideas get fleshed out as I try to glue together the disparate pieces. Often, a second essay will be born from the digressions that happen while writing the first.</p>
<p>Furthermore, I’m OK saying I was wrong and stupid in the past. Its a necessary part of growth, and of intellectual honesty — which itself contributes to getting smarter. After all, learning is really hard if you are lying to yourself about what you already know.</p>
<p>As for being cancelled, well, fuck it. If it happens, it happens. But I’m a small target with no audience to speak of. I’m about as uncancellable as can be, and I guess I’ll worry about it if it ever becomes an issue.</p>
<p>So those are some reasons why to not not have a blog. But, as we know, the law of the excluded middle is bupkis. So, why have a blog?</p>
<p>Blogging acts as a lighthouse.</p>
<p>Lighthouses are famously easy things to spot. They broadcast their presence far and wide. It’s their only function. Being a lighthouse makes you easier to find, which is to say, it helps advertise your existence to the sort of people you’d like to find.</p>
<p>Once a month or so I get a cold email from someone who has found my blog and liked it so much they wanted to get in touch. Almost by definition, these are my people. They are people from all around the world, who are thinking about and trying to solve the same problems I am. And that’s a magical gift that I wouldn’t be able to find any other way.</p>
<p>Being a lighthouse is the most important piece of advice I have that isn’t already in the mainstream spotlight. Importantly, it transcends any particular tactics. You don’t need to blog to be a lighthouse. Putting stickers of things you like on your laptop makes you a lighthouse at the coffee shop. Starting (and advertising) a local club for one of your interests makes you a lighthouse.</p>
<p>Niche things, by definition, are hard to find community for. So do your part by organizing enough neg-entropy around you that members of your desired tribe will recognize you when they see you.</p>
<p>Be a lighthouse! You never know what marvelous people might find you.</p>
      ]]></content:encoded>
  </item>
  <item>
      <title>Pillars of the Community</title>
      <author>sandy@sandymaguire.me (Sandy Maguire)</author>
      <link>http://sandymaguire.me/blog/pillars-of-the-community/index.html</link>
      <guid>http://sandymaguire.me/blog/pillars-of-the-community/index.html</guid>
      <pubDate>2022-03-31T05:43:00Z</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[
        <p>I managed to wake myself up at 4 in the morning with an insight, and figured I should write it down. As you might imagine, I haven’t been sleeping well lately, so I don’t know whom to credit with this idea — apologies. I’ve been wandering around in a bit of an exhausted zombie funk the last few weeks, and apparently not forming as many short-term memories as one would like.</p>
<p>But, anyway, someone and I were talking about community, and how to find it. Erin and I often say that community is the people you don’t necessarily like, but whom you have a reason to see over and over again. For better or worse, you’re stuck with them.</p>
<p>This seems true, but it doesn’t feel like the whole story. For example, when you think of the term “pillar of the community,” who comes to mind? For me it’s people like small business owners, religious leaders, club organizers, mail delivery people, voracious volunteers, the bartender at the local pub, and the like.</p>
<p>None of these people are best differentiated by being “not necessarily liked,” though they do have a reason to be seen over and over again. But I also see Sideways Man<a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"><sup>1</sup></a> on the street maybe once a week, and I wouldn’t describe him as a pillar of the community.</p>
<p>My interlocutor had a different idea of what it meant to be part of a community.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>A community is a group of people who can depend on one another.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This lens connects the dots. The mail person does a great service for the immediate area, as does the small-pub bartender. But, not only this. We can also expect the mail person to come with great regularity; neither rain nor sleet, you know. If you’re feeling down and need a dispassionate ear, this is a service offered by the bartender. And, importantly, the bar is always open.</p>
<p>What about small business owners? These are people who’ve strongly invested in the area. Their personal livelihood is attached not only to the neighborhood, but, importantly, to the ongoing success of the neighborhood. Business owners are necessarily among the most-invested in their community, since putting food on the table is linked to making and maintaining relationships. When you are looking to buy something expensive, it’s probably worth buying from someone you can keep an ongoing relationship with; someone you can depend on to still be around in a year if something goes sour.</p>
<p>Religion likewise. I suspect the bit about “religious leader” is a cached meme in the 21st century, but places of worship definitely do their part for the community. Name a choir or support-group that doesn’t depend on a church for a place to meet. Or, Erin points out, consider <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Langar_(Sikhism)">langar</a>, the Sikh practice of a “community kitchen” where anyone can show up for a meal.</p>
<p>On a personal level, this checks out with my experience. I felt significantly more involved in my community when I decided to <a href="/blog/neighborhoods">meet everyone in the neighborhood</a>. All of a sudden, I was going out of my way to talk to people I’d see on a regular basis. They didn’t depend on me for any service, but they could depend on me to say hi.</p>
<p>Likewise in Victoria, where I’ve been trying to put together a functional programming meetup. The local tech scene hasn’t been scratching my itches, so I figured I’d just take matters into my own hands. So, every two weeks, I’ve been hanging out at the same place at the same time. People can depend on me being there, and thus can swing by on the spur of the moment. We’re getting lots of repeat attendees, which suggests the meetup group is serving some need.</p>
<p>Where does this leave us? Is this an idea we can exploit to get closer to the good life? What courses of action does it suggest?</p>
<p>The most obvious is that if you’re feeling like you’re lacking community, put yourself in a position of being required. An easy starting point is to just regularly show up at a local meetup. Half the battle is showing up, after all. Offer to help organize things.</p>
<p>At an intermediate level, get involved with a group of people who create things, and then help them create that thing. It could be a choral performance, or an art exhibit or whatever. Something with a deadline. Everyone involved is going to want the thing to be as good as possible, and will thus be depending on you (and you, them) to put in as much as you can afford.</p>
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr />
<ol>
<li id="fn1" role="doc-endnote"><p>You’d understand if you saw him.<a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li>
</ol>
</section>
      ]]></content:encoded>
  </item>
  <item>
      <title>Excellence Orbits</title>
      <author>sandy@sandymaguire.me (Sandy Maguire)</author>
      <link>http://sandymaguire.me/blog/excellence-orbits/index.html</link>
      <guid>http://sandymaguire.me/blog/excellence-orbits/index.html</guid>
      <pubDate>2022-03-17T23:42:00Z</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[
        <p>Thailand is known as a place that has Figured Out Tourism. Not only is it a great place for a week holiday, it’s also a widely touted as a fantastic choice for first-time backpackers. These things are all true, and Thailand is in fact a blast. But it’s <em>mostly</em> a blast if you’re 18 and looking to get drunk and party. Which I am not.</p>
<p>And so, for me, Thailand was this nice tropical place, full of first-time traveling teenagers looking to get drunk and party. Not that there’s anything wrong with that, but I’ve been there and done that, and don’t need to do more of it. Thus, when I ran off to Thailand after my <a href="/blog/burnout/">breakdown</a>, I was underwhelmed. I was looking for young, driven, idealists, who had identified Thailand as a great place to escape from societal norms while they worked on building something cool. What I got instead was a lot of nights at the bar with whomever I happened to meet, talking mainly about nothing. But there sure was a lot of partying!!!!</p>
<p>A guy I had met once on a fateful night a few years back had mentioned he was heading to Koh Lanta, a nice quiet island to go hang out and do diving. It Sounded better than getting drunk and partying, so I hopped on a boat and arrived later that afternoon. I ended up staying for three months.</p>
<p>Koh Lanta is an island nestled-in between three giant party spots in Thailand — Koh Phi Phi, Ao Nang, and Phuket. As a result, anyone in the area who wanted to get drunk and party ended up at one of those spots, and meant the only travelers on Koh Lanta were the ones who were looking for something else. By virtue of being in the orbit of big party spots, Koh Lanta filtered out the big party people.</p>
<p>Does this idea generalize? Can we find the other Koh Lantas in spirit? What notable features should we be searching for?</p>
<p>Andrew McKnight helped me come up with some other examples. Continuing on with the travel example, the Baltics are a lovely place, but aren’t known for their tourism. As a result, the only people who travel to the Baltics are the experienced backpackers; the ones who have been everywhere else, and who want to continue exploring. Travelers who successfully escape Southeast Asia’s gravity field are almost immediately filtered for being interesting and well-traveled.</p>
<p>It’s a poorly-kept secret that at any tech conference, the “real conference” goes on in the hallway while most people are listening to scheduled talks. The people who aren’t going to talks are the ones who don’t want to go there, either because they aren’t interested, already know the material, or have something better to do. In any case, those are the people you should be hanging out with — they either have better taste than the mainstream, more knowledge than the mainstream, or have also identified that the hallway track is the place to be. People who escape the (focused) mass appeal of the talks are immediately filtered for being knowledgeable.</p>
<p>Or consider wine bars. Wine bars are notoriously more classy than sports bars. One way this plays out is that they don’t have TVs on the wall, which means if you’re going to the wine bar, you’re not there to mindlessly drink. You’re probably out with some friends, deliberately going to an environment where you can interact with one another. People who escape the attractor basin of sports bars are immediately filtered for interpersonal interactions.</p>
<p>Something like 99% of AI funding is going into deep learning. Though they don’t get much publicity, there are tons of other subfields. Things like robotics, expert systems, fuzzy logic, decision algorithms, search methods. What’s keeping people in those subfields, when they could easily switch to deep learning and make bank? Presumably they know something the rest of us don’t; it’s hard to believe that the people working on AI are all idiots. People who escape the attractor basin of money are immediately filtered for having some principles.</p>
<p>What do all of these examples have in common? The defining characteristic seems to be that within some special interest group (vacationers, travelers, conference attendees, drinkers, researchers), there exist strong attractors in the field which capture most of the interest-mass. The worthwhile things we’ve identified exist in the same space, but are robust enough to avoid being captured by the bigger attractor.</p>
<p>This makes a lot of sense. Someone loosely interested in a field will immediately discover its strongest attractors, and will likely be pulled in. That means the population around a strong attractor will be disproportionately newbies, weak affiliates, and “lifers” — people who were pulled in, and have never explored the space other than around the first attractor they found.</p>
<p>Gravity makes an excellent metaphor here, thus the term “attractor.” Imagine you’re traveling through space and accidentally end up in our solar system. If you end up sticking around, it’s probably because you got caught in the sun’s gravity well; everything else is too small to have any likelihood of grabbing you. Circling around the sun is better than careening through space — at least it’s warm. But, all things considered, the sun is the least interesting thing you could be orbiting in the whole solar system. Left to chance, you will probably stay orbiting the sun for the rest of your life, being warm but lacking any deep sense of purpose or belonging.</p>
<p>Now consider how much better it would be to be in Earth’s orbit. You would have to dodge the neverending launch of cube sats. You’d see all sorts of interesting developments happening on the surface. You’d probably be curious enough to put some brain cycles towards figuring out how get out of orbit and onto the planet. All of a sudden you’d have purpose, intrigue, direction. So many cool things — much better than just going around the sun every 30 years or whatever — but you’d be completely unaware of all of it if you just stayed around the big attractor in the system. The one that catches things by default.</p>
<p>The more I think about this, the more it seems obviously true. A central tenet of mine for a long time was “<a href="/blog/comfort-zones/">the best things in life are outside your comfort zone</a>,” but reality seems even weirder. In fact, if all this stuff about attractors is true, the best things in life are outside our <strong>awareness entirely.</strong> But, this gives us an algorithm for finding them: look for proximate attractors that haven’t yet pulled in. That’s where the interesting stuff is going on.</p>
      ]]></content:encoded>
  </item>
  <item>
      <title>What I Have Resolved To Do</title>
      <author>sandy@sandymaguire.me (Sandy Maguire)</author>
      <link>http://sandymaguire.me/blog/2022-goals/index.html</link>
      <guid>http://sandymaguire.me/blog/2022-goals/index.html</guid>
      <pubDate>2022-01-09T17:50:00Z</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[
        <p>2022 is here, and I’m very determined to kick its ass. My best years have been those which I came to with a specific, scary plan. I’ve had sloppy, weak plans for a few years in a row, and the years turned out pretty sloppy and weak as a result. NOT THIS YEAR, BABY.</p>
<p>One big issue I’ve had with the last two years is that I haven’t had enough to fill my (copious) time, and because of that I fell back on traditional (and stupid) ways of killing time: scrolling dumb websites, watching TV and playing video games. That’s no way to be spending my golden years of retirement. If I’m going to be wasting my time, I might as well be getting paid to do it. Instead, the plan is to say “YES!” to enough cool projects that I don’t have time to spare.</p>
<p>Before getting to the actual goals, I have a mantra for the year that I’d like to focus on:</p>
<p><strong>Brook no excuses for suboptimality.</strong> This is my mantra for the year. Whatever I do, I will do it with gusto. This is not to say that every essay needs to be ruthlessly edited, but it does mean that every essay must accomplish my goal for it. It means I will go the two minutes out of my way to fold my laundry, or to get rid of the unused, uncomfortable chair gathering dust in the corner. It means actively working towards making everything in my life better. I’m retired with infinite time and effectively infinite money; I have no excuses for living a suboptimal life. And this mantra is to help me remember that.</p>
<p>My goals for the year, in no particular order:</p>
<p>In 2022, I am going to <strong>read and engage with 52 papers on topics that I find interesting.</strong> The engagement part is critical — it’s easy enough to “read” a paper but moving your eyes over it. However, the purpose here is to rapidly inject ideas and methods into my head. Engagement here means I need to produce some sort of artifact as a result of working through the paper: something that proves I understand the ideas in it. I’ve already done <a href="https://reasonablypolymorphic.com/blog/adders-and-arrows/">one</a>, which should give you a sense of what it means to engage.</p>
<p>A common failure mode I see in myself is engaging in suboptimal behavior due to a lack of easily-discovered knowledge. For example, I put off playing piano pieces in Gb for like a decade because I didn’t know what notes were in that scale — even though when I sat down to think it through, it took less than 2 minutes to do. Thus, be it resolved that I will <strong>spend 2 hours a week this year researching high-value topics.</strong></p>
<p>One of the things I have been consistently putting off is learning how to feel good in my body. My body is a weak programmer body, and it gets hurt all the time when I try to exercise. Getting hurt all the time really kills any sort of fitness momentum I have. So this year I will <strong>get fit, or at least get to a point where I understand my body well enough to not get hurt when doing fitness.</strong></p>
<p>This year, I am not going to go to bed until <strong>my living and work spaces are tidy.</strong> This includes the kitchen.</p>
<p>I will <strong>compose and publish 12 original songs</strong> this year.</p>
<p>In 2022, I resolve to <strong>not be a curmudgeon.</strong> This means that when things annoy me, I will calmly go and discuss the issue with the first parties. Whenever that isn’t an option, I will come up with some other pro-social solution to the problem, possibly including just deciding to not be bothered by it.</p>
<p>Relatedly, this year I will <strong>not attempt telekinesis.</strong> Attempting telekinesis is when you try to solve a problem by wishing really hard that it would go away. Like, when someone is bothering you but doesn’t realize it, and instead of solving the problem you just sit there smoldering — in essence, hoping that if you concentrate hard enough you could make their head explode. Similar to above, I will either go calmly attempt to solve the problem, or stop being bothered by it.</p>
<p>During 2022, I will <strong>publish 100k words</strong>. They do not necessarily need to be in text format.</p>
<p>My biggest takeaway from the Elon Musk book is that Elon is significantly more willing than most people to invest in himself financially. I recognized that fact when I read it, but didn’t do anything with it. So this year, I’m going to <strong>spend $10,000 of my own money on my own projects.</strong> Not only will this help my projects, it will also help me burn my runway cash, which should get me off of resting on my laurels.</p>
<p>Similarly, I am earmarking <strong>another $5,000 for solving trivial problems in my life.</strong> I don’t like spending money on things, even when that money would pay off in big dividends, and this is a current failure on my part.</p>
<p>On the community front, this year I will <strong>reach out cold to one cool person a week.</strong> I figure that even if only 5% of them respond, that will be two new excellent humans I’ll have created new relationships with.</p>
<p>Something I did during 2018 that aggressively changed how I felt about my city was to <a href="/blog/neighborhoods/">actively meet people.</a> This was one of the best exercises I’ve ever done, but I’ve fallen out of the habit and find myself pining for the results. So in 2022, I will <strong>meet two new people a day.</strong></p>
<p>Playing music with other people is one of my most cherished hobbies, and I barely do any of it. By the end of the year, I will be a member of a musical community in the same way I am a member of many programming communities. I realize this is not a very SMART goal but I don’t know how to make it into one and it’s very important to me regardless. Please get in touch if you have some ideas!</p>
<p>I don’t have enough good friends in my life. By the end of the year I will <strong>have five really good friends.</strong> Musicians from the above goal are allowed to count towards this. The SMARTer version of this goal is that I will <strong>spend quality time with three friends a week</strong> on average this year.</p>
<hr />
<p>Whew! What a lot of things to track. I’m fully aware that when I make goals, I usually completely miss the ballpark on what I’ll think of as important a few months down the line. So instead of just weaseling out, this year I am allowed to <strong>cancel one of these goals</strong>, and <strong>adjust the parameters on another two.</strong> I hope to not need to do these things, but they’re available if I need to.</p>
      ]]></content:encoded>
  </item>
  <item>
      <title>Looking Back on 2021</title>
      <author>sandy@sandymaguire.me (Sandy Maguire)</author>
      <link>http://sandymaguire.me/blog/looking-back-2021/index.html</link>
      <guid>http://sandymaguire.me/blog/looking-back-2021/index.html</guid>
      <pubDate>2022-01-01T07:28:00Z</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[
        <p>Well, 2021 is over. I’ve been dreading writing this retrospective blog post for a few weeks, because every time I tried to think about what happened last year, I couldn’t come up with anything. The GLOBAL PANDEMIC of yesteryear has shown modest signs of abatement, but life remains pretty weird. Personally I’ve stopped caring about the GLOBAL PANDEMIC and would be happy to just get the thing and have it over and done with, but I appear to be in the minority on this one. I digress.</p>
<p>So what happened in 2021? It’s a little hard to remember, as my specific memories are usually attached to weird places I found myself, people I was hanging out with, or particular projects I was working on. Due to UNCERTAIN TIMES, most of those hooks are unavailable, so this post comes with no promises that it is comprehensive. But that’s OK.</p>
<p>Erin and I rang in the new year in my old apartment. We’d gone out for fancy cocktails, but previously unbeknownst to us, the bar started the new years countdown at 7:30pm. Why? Bonnie had announced at the eleventh hour that new years was canceled, and that all establishments had to be closed by 8. So we took our fancy cocktails, and spent the rest of the night at my place, in rather low spirits. To celebrate the new year, we screamed “fuck 2020” off the balcony, and most of the nearby apartment blocks joined us in our fury. It was the closest thing to “community” I’d felt in Victoria up to that point.</p>
<p>January was spent trying to <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8vWaawiUteM">emulate George Hotz</a> and throw knowledge of computation at a field that was explicitly non-computational. My target was Canadian case law, trying to mine as much insight out of the field without knowing anything about it. <a href="https://reasonablypolymorphic.com/blog/exploring-case-law/">I wrote about the process</a>.</p>
<p>In 2020, Erin had also expressed interest in having me build a robot for her. I decided to make an (ill-fated) roomba. <a href="https://reasonablypolymorphic.com/blog/roomba/">It wasn’t the world’s best robot,</a> but I learned a lot about how to not build robots for next time. There hasn’t yet been a next time though, and for good reason.</p>
<p>In February, my alma matter reached out, asking if I wanted to be a mentor for Women In Engineering. I get a few weird invitations like this every year, usually from people incorrectly assuming I’m a woman based on my name. I replied saying I’d be interested to mentor a Woman In Engineering, so long as they were OK with me not <em>being</em> a Woman In Engineering. Surprisingly they said yes, and so I was matched with Rebecca, a biomedical engineering student, who clearly thought about me as a boomer. We spent the year doing biweekly calls, with me ostensibly doing Mentoring, but all things considered I don’t think I did a very good job of it. Regardless, it was cool watching Rebecca’s growth over the year, and I don’t mind taking credit for it — even though she did way more work than I did!</p>
<p>Also in February, someone started paying me to tutor them in Haskell! It was a cool experience, but ultimately fizzled out. I learned a lot about teaching, and about learning, and perhaps most importantly about the value of setting expectations. It was lots of fun, and I’d love to do more of this! Feel free to hit me up if you’re interested and diligent.</p>
<p>I did <a href="https://blubrry.com/sessions_by_se/73979973/from-silicon-valley-to-digital-nomad-sandy-maguire/">two</a> <a href="https://haskellweekly.news/episode/39.html">podcasts</a> in March, one for the University of Waterloo Software Engineering podcast, and another for Haskell Weekly. Both were tons of fun, and briefly amplified my message — lots of really cool people reached out to me to chat about life.</p>
<p>Erin got a fancy job at a fancy law firm in Vancouver for the summer, so we made plans to move to Vancouver. We both gave up our apartments, and immediately after her law firm informed everyone that the job would be remote due to THE GLOBAL PANDEMIC. Rude. We spent a huge amount of energy house hunting in Vancouver, and found a great place, which fell through a few days before we were supposed to move in. Assuming the whole thing was cursed, we decided to stay in Victoria, and found a great place a few blocks away from my old place. We moved in together, and it was by far the best change in my life of the last year.</p>
<p>While we were still house hunting in Vancouver, Erin and I accidentally crossed paths with a world-famous Youtube celebrity. Erin was mortified when I called her over and asked “excuse me, but are you a world-famous Youtube celebrity?”</p>
<p>THE GLOBAL PANDEMIC had me down, so I decided to join a “rock band class” at the royal conservatory. I wasn’t sure what to expect, but I thought it would be nice to play music with people, since playing bass by oneself sorta defeats the point. Whatever I was expecting, it wasn’t what I got. What I got was to paired up with a handful of super boomers. There was Bill and Mike, Rob and Bob, and John and Mustafar. They were all pushing 70, and only wanted to play Herman’s Hermits. And they already had a bass player, and he was better than I was. We had to play behind GIANT PLEXI-GLASS SHEETS, and the entire experience was just terrible.</p>
<p>At the time, I was reading an excellent book about orthodox Jews, and somehow got myself all excited to celebrate the Sabbath. Erin and I started taking Saturday off, avoiding work and technology, trying to make time and space for friends and family. I started studying “how to study the Torah”, which <a href="/blog/hamming/">turned into a fantastic reading club</a> of Hamming with my friend Andrew. It was a blast of a time, even though we got through like one page an hour.</p>
<p>Relatedly, one time we were studying the “Torah” (read: Hamming) in the park, when a crazy man started harassing some poor woman. We intervened, the thing turned into a fracas, and ended with us dodging a gallon projectile of orange juice hurled directly at us.</p>
<p>Sometime in March, I decided to grab the GLOBAL PANDEMIC by its ugly horns. There’s a project called <a href="https://radvac.org/">RaDVaC</a>, which is an open-source vaccine project. It was unclear how much longer the (official) vaccines were going to take, and I figured I had some idle capital to throw at weird projects. Two of my friends were interested in collaborating, and we figured we could make 500 doses at a little less than $300 each. Unfortunately, it seems quite hard to get peptide synthesized in Canada, and nobody got back to me. Still, I think this was a worthwhile way to spend a few weeks. I want to train my “protagonist” muscles, and get into a headspace where the next time a big world-scale problem comes along, I won’t just give up two years of my life without <em>trying.</em></p>
<p>Erin and I decided we’d avoid a lot of marriage-like-relationship problems if we just hired someone to clean our apartment, rather than doing it ourselves. We hired an agency, who sent a man that I googled immediately before his arrival. Turns out he was recently acquitted from a giant sexual-abuse scandal. Acquitted is a good thing, but it didn’t make us feel particularly good about the whole affair. We sat down and had a discussion about what sort of citizens we wanted to be — do we trust in the legal system to have done its job properly? And even if it didn’t, what should society do about people like this? We decided to keep him, but after a few disappointing cleans, the moral quandary was put behind us and we hired a friend of a friend who did a much better job.</p>
<p>In June, I applied for a super-cool sounding job involving making specialized hardware for accelerating machine learning. It sounded right up my alley, and was a pretty unique fit for my skills, so I was keen! But the interviewer didn’t show up. It took a week to reschedule, during which time I remembered that “machine learning” is just a code word for “AI that doesn’t work very well” and I remembered that <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/AI_control_problem">I don’t actually want to speed up bad AI</a>. Also there was probably something in there about not wanting to have a job. But a big chunk of it was the “don’t help cause the apocalypse” thing. Shame, really.</p>
<p>Concurrently, Erin and I got into a giant fight. Neither of us are sure what it was about, but man was it rough. Erin can be actively passive aggressive when she’s angry, and that wasn’t a very pleasant few days. I thought it would be funny if I got us a plaque memorializing the end of our fight, but didn’t actually do it. When our fight was over, I mentioned this idea to Erin, who thought it was hilarious. And so thus was born the “Sarin Board of Relationship Growth and Development” award. To this day there is only the single fight engraved on it, and we’d like to keep it that way. To avoid meta-fights, we’ve decided that the fights are remembered only by their dates: they don’t come with a title, so we can’t disagree about what the fights were about. Also, I get the odd numbered fights engraved, and Erin does the even ones. It’s a smooth system.</p>
<p>Since wrapping up my book last year, my main intellectual project for the year was <a href="https://haskellwingman.dev/">Wingman</a>. I was invited to <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=S0HvfXq3454">give a talk on it at ZuriHac</a>, which was a nice culmination of all of my work. It garnered a lot of attention, and felt good to finally show off in full glory.</p>
<p>My parents came to visit in July. It was fantastic to see them, and in an attempt to show them a good time, I bought us tickets to a Cuban music concert. But the restaurant I took them to beforehand had a mouse running around (they thought it was less charming than Erin and I did), and then I misread the starting time of the concert so got us there 90 minute early. And then the Cubans started 45 minutes late, so by the time they got started everyone was already tired and cranky. The show itself was a marvel of modern art. The musicians did a bit about how they were just practicing for a big show, and every song was punctuated with a 5 minute intermission with bad acting. It was not the hit for my parents that I was hoping.</p>
<p>After last year’s underwhelming birthday party, I wanted to make this year special, so I reached out to everyone I’d ever met, and invited them to A BIG SHINDIG. The turnout was OK, but special props to Malcolm, Sarah, and Eric for taking a ferry to come! THE GLOBAL PANDEMIC was not kind to everyone’s partying skills — we’d all sorta forgotten how to do it. Thankfully Erin peer pressured us all into shotgunning beers, which helped get the energy restarted!</p>
<p>Erin’s summer was rough. We canceled something like four weekend vacations because the workload was overwhelming. So when it was over, we decided to take a two-week vacation to the UK to visit her family. But the UK required a 10 day quarantine, which was going to aggressively eat up our vacation time. So we booked tickets to go to Texas, but then there was a huge GLOBAL PANDEMIC outbreak in Texas. So then we booked tickets to go to New Orleans, but it was hit with a hurricane. So then we booked tickets to Guatemala.</p>
<p>But Guatemala kinded sucked. It was soured by our stress levels, and wasn’t helped by all the stories we heard about just how dangerous Guatemala is. The guys walking around at every street corner with giant shotguns didn’t improve things. And the air quality was bad, and there were no sidewalks. Rough!</p>
<p>It wasn’t all bad — we went to visit our friends Christian and Paula, who had just left Canada to live in Guate. It was great to see them, and they took us to some pretty incredible places, including the most amazing beach house. The beach house was custom designed by two architects, in a crescent shape around a giant tree, complete with a cook and a guy whose job it was to drive us around in the boat. And the house was hidden behind a fake wall in the middle of a field outside of the sketchiest town I’ve ever seen. On one of our boat outings we met a woman who lived in the forest and who is “you, and you, and you.” We didn’t exactly get along.</p>
<p>Erin signed us up to hike up a damn (dormant) volcano. I was expecting like, a Canada-level hike. But this wasn’t that. It was six hours of steep, muddy climbing, carrying six liters of water in tow, through wet cloud cover. The Europeans (Erin included) gracefully leaped up the mountain like gazelles, while a few Middle Eastern men, some extremely unprepared Americans, and I trudged up, bonding in our shared misery.</p>
<p>We had been promised stellar views of active volcanoes when we reached the top, but all we got was thick clouds. It was damp and cold and there was nothing to see and the guides were unable to make a fire because it was too damp and cold, which didn’t add much to the damp/cold problem. But all sins were forgotten when in a magical moment, the cloud cover disappeared, and the crack of a nearby volcano erupting shook our (dormant) volcano. To date, it was one of the most magical sights I’ve ever seen, and might have been worth the cold, the damp, the almost dying from hypothermia overnight, the aggressive wildlife that tried to break into our cabin, the mouse that ate all of our food, and the searing pain in my knees by the time we got to the bottom.</p>
<p>But I also got to see an Austrian law professor squirm when I asked about his favorite administrative decision maker. “We don’t do that in Austria” he said.</p>
<p>After a week in Guatemala, we decided to cut our losses and head to Mexico. My cousin had recommended a place called San Cristobal de la Casas, citing it as a magical place. So we packed up and arrived there on a Friday night. The city was fully alive, with music on every corner, and more tacos and street merchants than you could shake a stick at. What a delightful change of pace after two years of THE GLOBAL PANDEMIC. I asked a local if there were any GLOBAL PANDEMIC restrictions and she laughed at me — “if they tried to stop us from dancing we would revolt.” Sentiments I wished my countrymen shared.</p>
<p>Erin and I took an awkward cooking class while in SCdlC. She went to the market to help buy ingredients, but I ducked in half way through. Erin greeted me at the door and whispered “we’ve made a huge mistake.” But the food was great, even if our compatriots’ conversational skills weren’t.</p>
<p>With our vacation time up, Erin headed for home. But I decided to stick around for another week or so, since I had nowhere to be and SCdlC was good for the soul. I spent the week exploring the city, hitting up cool jazz bars, reading lots of books, and generally reorganizing my life trying to get over an existential crisis. While in retrospect I didn’t solve it, I made great progress and came back raring to go.</p>
<p>While in SCdlC, I negotiated a contract for my newly-created business, and took on my first work as an independent contractor. The task was to help a business port their system to use one of my open-source libraries. It was fun work for a while, but I ran out of steam for the project due to some logistical problems. The result was less-than-stellar work on my part, and I’m mortified about the whole thing. I’m still trying to figure out how to sort everything out.</p>
<p>Also while in SCdlC, I applied to join an entrepreneur incubator. Essentially they pay your room and board to come spend three months meeting cool people and forming companies with a fixed investment for any good idea that comes through. It seemed like low risk (and I was the new owner of a new business) so I figured I’d give it a go. I got in, but ultimately turned it down because it was in Toronto and I couldn’t bear the thought of spending 3 months without Erin. More on this later.</p>
<p>Back in Victoria, I decided to try to make the most of the GLOBAL PANDEMIC. I took up improv classes, and Erin and I started taking swing dancing classes. Both were a blast, in completely different ways. Swing has continued to be awesome, but improv fizzled out. Erin and I have been having a blast with swing — it’s so cool how a particular lead on my end <em>forces her to twirl</em> without either of us understanding the dynamics. The art form itself has internalized lots of rules of physics that I can exploit as a lead. I can see how people get really into dance.</p>
<p>Mid-October I hopped on a plane to go visit some friends in Ontario. I was reunited with the excellent Jonathan Lorimer, and we pushed out a cool software package over the weekend — very reminiscent of my Erdos project. I took a “train” to Waterloo, but it turned out to be a bus that happened to be driven by a train conductor. We were like two hours behind schedule, and then the bus went rogue and went right past the terminal stop. For like 20 minutes. But Austin was waiting to pick me up when the dust settled, and I got to hang out with him and his partner whom I was ostensibly there to vet before they got married. I’m happy to report that Rosie passed with flying colors, and would make a great match for my heterosexual life-partner Austin.</p>
<p>While in Waterloo, I got to spend a few days on the university campus, haunting the old stomping grounds, and made friends with some of the baby software engineering students. It was a blast, and I tried to impart lots of good wisdom onto them. They didn’t care and went on with their homework, as is exactly the right response to old people butting in with advice. God knows I did the same.</p>
<p>I also ran into Alec Strong while in Waterloo, whom I have always really liked, but never known that well. We caught up over beers, and the night was one of the highlights of my year.</p>
<p>November came. Or more specifically, it didn’t, because on a whim I decided to participate in No-Nut November. Which is an online meme where you go for a month without having any orgasms. I made a valiant effort, but was thwarted in the final days by a brilliant ploy on Erin’s part. All in all it was great fun, and I’d strongly recommend NNN to everyone.</p>
<p>Some other stuff happened, like trying to volunteer for the local jazz bar. But I only made it a few shifts in because it was a horrible experience, impressively managing to not only give me no training, but also to schedule a bunch of new, untrained people to have a shift together, and also to write a really aggressive email when it predictably didn’t go well. It was a nice thought. But this is a long enough post already, so the remainder of the year’s anecdotes will stay mysteries.</p>
<h2 id="quantified-stuff">Quantified Stuff</h2>
<p>I read 49 books in 2021. Lots of them were light fiction, which I like reading before bed because otherwise my brain gets too engaged and I sleep poorly. But of the 49, five especially stood out:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/524985.The_Brothers_Ashkenazi">The Brothers Ashkenazi</a> — it’s hard to pin down exactly what I liked about this book, but it’s probably the best fiction I’ve ever read. The experience feels a lot like The Unbearable Lightness of Being, which is also a hard book to pin down why it’s as good as it is.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/18834806-art-fear">Art and Fear</a> — musings on how to be artistic, and how to actually get art done. Most of art is pouring your soul into things and having it be misunderstood or ignored. This book really resonated with me as an independent researcher, where I feel like most of the things I pour my soul into get misunderstood and ignored.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/17930467-the-fourth-phase-of-water">The Fourth Phase of Water</a> — water is way more interesting than anyone thinks. It has all of these funky physical properties, like you can use it as a battery. Sounds crazy, except that this is exactly how cells work. Reading this book really changed my everyday experience, and inspired a huge amount of wonder whenever I interacted with water.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/13036014-endless-forms-most-beautiful">Endless Forms Most Beautiful</a> — like the above, except about life forms. The idea is “what can we learn when we start treating biology quantitatively?” Like, if you classify families of life by what percentage of DNA they share, rather than what things seem to be the same, you can all of a sudden start tracking the evolutionary timeline. What tools in the toolkit of life developed when? Which things evolved repeatedly? For example, animal wings happened three times in three flavors: “arm wings” for birds, “hand wings” for bats, and “finger wings” for pterodactyls. Fascinating stuff.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/42036377-where-is-my-flying-car">Where’s My Flying Car?</a> — some boomer grew up in the golden age of science fiction, and took all of its promises to heart. This book is him trying to figure out where it all went wrong and why all of the predictions from the 50s didn’t shape out. It’s an inspiring book, if only to get a sense of what the future might look like if we set our sights higher than “our phones might be faster.”</li>
</ul>
<p>In addition to reading books, I also sold a bunch of books in 2021. Last year I sold 209 copies of Thinking with Types, and 266 copies of Algebra-Driven Design. If you put those numbers together, I sold more than one book a day, which is a pretty cool passive income stream. At time of writing, I’m 13 sales away from 1000 copies of Algebra-Driven Design sold. Go buy some!</p>
<p>Over the last year, I did 963 hours of deep, focused work, 294 of which were spent on Wingman.</p>
<p>I spent 737 hours watching TV which is about 2h a day and a disgusting amount and I am ashamed. I will do better next year.</p>
<p>I spent 285 hours playing video games, mostly in the form of Civilization, which I have since uninstalled and unpurchased because it’s not even fun.</p>
<p>I also spent 163 hours breaking my new years resolution, which is not so good, but also I think the resolution might have been missing judicious thought.</p>
<p>I made 1208 commits last year and published 30,422 words.</p>
<p>I listened to 23,920 songs, and my favorite new artist of the year is <a href="https://open.spotify.com/artist/6RhsbxbsDk5ypSXFkS41J5">Marlowe</a>.</p>
<h2 id="wrapping-up">Wrapping Up</h2>
<p>When I started out to write this post, I was feeling quite glum about the whole year. But having written everything out, I’m actually quite pleased with how it went and how much I grew during it.</p>
<p>My feelings were that I didn’t accomplish much during the year, but this isn’t true. While no, I didn’t publish a new book or anything, I did make a really fucking cool piece of technology. More importantly however, I realized that my crowning achievement of 2021 was the relationship I’ve built with Erin. That’s where the majority of my energy went, and it shows. I’ve never been so happy with anyone ever before. Not by a long shot.</p>
<p>However you want to cut it, 2021 was a good year and 2022 is going to be much better again.</p>
      ]]></content:encoded>
  </item>
  <item>
      <title>An Open Letter on Banning Uber From Operating in BC</title>
      <author>sandy@sandymaguire.me (Sandy Maguire)</author>
      <link>http://sandymaguire.me/blog/open-letter-uber/index.html</link>
      <guid>http://sandymaguire.me/blog/open-letter-uber/index.html</guid>
      <pubDate>2021-12-23T11:17:00Z</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[
        <p>Mrs. Allevato,</p>
<p>I am the owner of a small, local, technology-focused business in Victoria, and was shocked and dismayed to hear your recent ruling blocking the operations of Uber in BC. The ruling is clearly anti-competitive, and reeks of rampant corruption. The meteoric rise of passengers choosing to use Uber and other ride-sharing apps is clear evidence that they <em>prefer</em> Uber over taxi services.</p>
<p>Perhaps you haven’t ridden in a taxi recently, but it is an awful experience. Last week I took a cab to the airport. The vehicle was smelly, rundown, and extremely uncomfortable due to a broken seat and seat-belt. This is not an outlier in my biweekly taxi usage. Of course taxi cabs will be in this state. They are rented by drivers who have no incentive to keep the vehicles well maintained. The cab companies have a monopoly, meaning that they can afford to keep their cab fleet in awful condition, since there is no competition to improve.</p>
<p>Worse, it cost $65 to get to the airport, when an Uber would have cost roughly half of that.</p>
<p>I can’t overstate this point: every cab ride I have ever taken in Victoria has been an awful experience. This sentiment is shared by many of my colleagues and friends.</p>
<p>Contrast this with ride-sharing apps, where drivers use their own vehicles, and have their cleanliness and behavior moderated by a convenient rating system. The drivers thus have an incentive to offer excellent cleanliness and service — first in that they are using their own personal property, and second in that their livelihood will be threatened by bad ratings otherwise.</p>
<p>None of these feedback mechanisms exist in the taxi industry.</p>
<p>Furthermore, not only is Uber a better experience for riders, it is also better for drivers. Your decision quotes the following passage from the report:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>during an ongoing driver shortage, it is possible that taxi company margins will be squeezed by fixed meter rates to the point where they cannot retain drivers even though taxi demand justifies it. The drivers will then tend to move to TNS where the hourly earnings are higher because of the higher average rates and the high customer demand.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>which makes the very clear claim that drivers would prefer to work for TNS than for taxi companies. I have lived in many cities with ride-sharing, and this sentiment resonates with my experience — every single TNS driver has told me they make much more money than they ever would working for a taxi company.</p>
<p>Compare this against the cab system, where drivers must rent a cab from the taxi company for a 12 hour shift at a fixed rate. A 12 hour shift is too long for any human to safely perform a high-focus activity, but the incentive structure of the taxi industry encourages drivers to work as many hours as possible, regardless of whether it’s safe to do so. My most recent cab ride to the airport was at 5am. The driver was barely awake and couldn’t keep his eyes on the road. I was genuinely afraid for my life, but, crucially, <em>had no other alternatives.</em></p>
<p>Ride-sharing apps don’t suffer these problems. The driver rating system incentivizes safe driving, and because they work on their own schedule, drivers aren’t punished financially for stopping when they are tired.</p>
<p>It is clear that ride-sharing apps are better for both the rider and the driver. Your decision has thus sold out to the taxi cartels at the expense of local people on both sides who long for a better system. The decision states:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>In the Board’s view, existing licensees should have the opportunity to start up and be successful in their business without additional competition which may be harmful.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The entire purpose of competition is to force better behavior from incumbents. Taxis exist to get people from one place to another. They exist to provide society a service. Society does not owe taxi companies the right to exist if they are worse on every front than a superior competitor — and taxis are.</p>
<p>Given these reasons, it is unconscionable to protect the taxi cartel, and corruption is the only logical explanation why the Passenger Transportation Board would do so.</p>
<p>I urge you to reconsider your decision to ban Uber from operating in BC. It is unconscionable and serves only to protect a parasitic drain on society.</p>
<p>Yours, Sandy Maguire</p>
      ]]></content:encoded>
  </item>
  <item>
      <title>Notes from My Copy of the Art of Doing Science and Engineering</title>
      <author>sandy@sandymaguire.me (Sandy Maguire)</author>
      <link>http://sandymaguire.me/blog/hamming/index.html</link>
      <guid>http://sandymaguire.me/blog/hamming/index.html</guid>
      <pubDate>2021-11-17T01:02:00Z</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[
        <p>Sometime during the summer I had a religious experience. My girlfriend and I decided that we needed one day off technology and work every week, and we jokingly called it the sabbath.</p>
<p>On the first sabbath, I didn’t know what to do with myself, so I started googling for “what to do on the sabbath?”<a href="#fn1" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref1" role="doc-noteref"><sup>1</sup></a> I went through several listicles, with some good ideas and lots of bad ones. But one thing came up again and again: <em>study the torah.</em></p>
<p>What the hell did that mean? What does it mean to <em>study</em> a book that isn’t about math? I called Grace, my only friend who is a practicing Jew. I called her on the sabbath, which again I think was OK because the suggestions were big on catching up with old friends, and there was both a pandemic and a gulf between us.</p>
<p>Grace told me that studying the torah is all about getting together with a friend, reading the book to oneself (but in the presence of your friend who is reading the same part) and then interrupting your friend whenever an idea spurred by the text crosses your mind.</p>
<p>Sounds <em>cool.</em> So I called up my friend Andrew, who was the only person I could think of who’d be interested in such an arrangement. He was down, so we met up later that day at the cafe.</p>
<p>Since neither Andrew nor I were religious, we decided to pick a book more amenable to us, and we ended up on Richard Hamming’s <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/530415.The_Art_of_Doing_Science_and_Engineering">The Art of Doing Science and Engineering</a>. Hamming’s thing was <a href="https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/P5k3PGzebd5yYrYqd/the-hamming-question">asking people why they’re not working on the most important problems in their fields</a> — which probably didn’t make him very popular — but it seems like the sort of character trait that would lead to writing a book worth studying.</p>
<p>The result was pretty fucking fantastic. Both Andrew and I agreed we engaged with the book at a much deeper level than we would have alone, reading silently. And this makes sense — our first session was 3 hours long and we only made it through 20 pages.</p>
<p>I would <em>strongly</em> recommend this method of engaging with important texts. It’s fantastic.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, Andrew left town soon after, and I was left to fend for myself. I couldn’t find anyone else who wanted to “study the torah” with me, so I decided I would engage with the book by writing down quotes that I liked, and including my commentary on it. The remainder of this post is made of up such.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p65. This is typical of many citations. It is first necessary to prove beyond any doubt the new thing, device, method, or whatever it is, can cope with heroic tasks before it can get into the system to do the more route, and in the long run, more useful tasks.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Hamming is talking about computers here — the hardest problems he had to solve were on the worst computers, because they were the ones that couldn’t be solved by any other means.</p>
<p>I see elements of this in all of my open source projects. Consider <a href="https://haskellwingman.dev/">Wingman</a>, which is a general purpose tool for helping to writing code. But that’s a boring use case that nobody will get excited about. So instead, most of its features are to <em>divide what you want and write that code for you.</em> Like, way harder. There’s all of this potential to solve real, everyday problems for people, but nobody wants that because it’s too mundane.</p>
<p>This is food for thought in future projects; I keep forgetting about it and needing to pivot my project mid-way through. But what if it were in the game plan from the start?</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p66. Any innovation is always against such a barrier, so do not get discouraged when you find your new idea is stoutly, and perhaps foolishly, resisted. By realizing the magnitude of the actual task you can then decide if it is worth your efforts to continue, or if you should go do something else you can accomplish and not fritter away your efforts needlessly against the forces of inertia and stupidity.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Man, I feel like all of my ideas are stoutly and foolishly resisted. Especially when I was working on Polysemy, and everyone complained on every one of my progress reports saying it was a stupid project that was doomed to failure. But mainly I like this quote because “the forces of inertia and stupidity” is a great mental handle.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p73. As you go on your careers you should examine the applications which succeed and those which fail; try to learn how to distinguish between them; try to understand the situations which produce successes and those which almost guarantee failure.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Good advice that I’d like to remember. A big emphasis of the book is to make time to study one’s life, techniques and likely future. To put some time towards that, my attempts that usually succeed are things I can tackle by myself — I don’t usually play well with others. The things I usually <em>fail</em> on are projects in which I need to overcome the forces of inertia and stupidity; mostly because I just don’t have the patience for dealing with them.</p>
<p>See, that’s a fantastic thing to point out. I knew that, but I didn’t <em>know</em> it. And it’s timely — some friends and I are currently planning out a project that is both a team effort and against the forces of inertia and stupidity. Not a good setup, it sounds like. That’s not to say I don’t think it’s worth doing, but maybe that I should only sign up if we have a plan for how someone else can be in charge of the public relations.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p116. Generally speaking, the best design is pushing one or more of the parameters to their extreme—obviously you are on the surface of the feasible region of design!</p>
</blockquote>
<p>A great technique for engineering systems — jump straight to the pareto frontier and hill-climb from there.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p149. I had thus established the habit, after something of great or small importance was discovered, of going back and trying to trace the steps by which it apparently happened.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Another reminder to myself that I should make some time for this. As a matter of fact, I’ll put it on my calendar right now.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p150. Notice first this essential step happened only because there was a great deal of emotional stress on me at the moment, and this is characteristic of most great discoveries. Working calmly will let you elaborate and extend things, but the breakthroughs generally come only after great frustration and emotional involvement. The calm, cool, uninvolved researcher seldom makes really great new steps.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This happened to me while working on Polysemy. It was spurred on by an avoidable disaster at work, that I then staked my reputation on, and failed to pull off. My ego was bruised so I decided I was going to finish the project, even though I quit the job. And then people told me I was stupid every time I made progress. It was an <em>extremely</em> powerful motivator — though it also lead to some awful burnout.</p>
<p>I wonder if this can be harnessed more generally. Can I deliberately set up an environment that is hostile? Does it work if it’s artificial? Something to play with.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p152. Riding through north Jersey in the early morning is not a great sight.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Made me laugh.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p153. It pays to know more than just what is needed at the moment!</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The context: Hamming knew a bunch of theory in an unrelated field, and it helped me spot a new technique when a colleague asked for his help. This is something I strongly believe in; people are always asking “why is this useful?” and I never understand <em>why.</em> It’s useful because everything in the universe is coherent — even if it doesn’t directly help solve your problem today, learning cool things always pays off. Even if it’s just in building your appreciation of how coherent the universe really is.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p164. From the assumed continuity of the information measure, it follows the log is the only continuous solution to the functional equation from earlier.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is not how I think about math. Maybe it’s how I think about programming? But there is a thought process here that I don’t understand, and I would like to. Identifying thought processes that work for smart people, that you <em>don’t yet understand</em> is a very powerful tool: because these things are easily learned. The details, maybe less so, but the high-level approach is always easy to pin down. Future work for future Sandy.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p164. Put into other words, if you provide a capacity for some level of error correction, then for efficiency you must use this ability most of the time or else you are wasting capacity, and this implies a high number of errors corrected in each message sent.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>What an interesting way of thinking about system reliability. Hamming is saying the best messaging channel is one in which you add capacity until the noise is almost overwhelming, and then you error correct from there. It’s the opposite of what I would have thought — “obviously” you’d want a clear channel, with error correction in place as a last defense. But no he says, if you put it in, you damn well better use it!</p>
<p>I don’t know what this has to say about software, but I suspect it’s something very deep.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p176. It is traditional to accept, in the long run, that the definition we use actually defines the thing defined; but of course it only tells us how to handle things, and in no way actually tells us any meaning.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Context: Shannon pinned down information theory as a measure of surprise in a channel. But this is not <em>information!</em> It’s just a measure of surprise in a channel, which is a different thing. But because it’s called “information theory,” the name gets confused for the thing.</p>
<p>This one particularly resonates with me, because I <em>do</em> think about information as a measure of surprise. Like, I can’t even pretend to imagine it in any other way. The mathematical model has wormed its way into my understanding of the universe. That’s not necessarily a bad thing, but it’s an extremely interesting experience to notice that I am figuratively blind to seeing the world in any other way.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p179. In the first place I thought I knew very little about digital filters, and, furthermore, I was not really interested in them. But does one wisely ignore one’s VP, plus the cogency of one’s own observations? No!</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Damn. I see this when I look at climate change. It’s clearly a big problem, and (I think) I can see lots of good ideas that nobody else seems to be working on. But I’m disinterested in the field because it doesn’t let me use my comparative advantage of software.</p>
<p>It sounds hard to retrain myself in another field — which is an especially damming thought, because I have often thought to myself that anyone could get into software if they would just <em>try.</em></p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p186. I needed only a firm understanding of the aliasing effects due to sampling. It is another example of why you need to know the fundamentals very well; the fancy parts then follow easily and you can do things that they never told you about.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Again, this reminds me of a strong math education. If you only know how to run the formula maze, you’ll get stuck as soon as it’s posed as a word problem, or whatever permutation might hit you. This is a principle I try to live by, and I think I succeed.</p>
<p>Also, it’s a great quote that I am going to put in my book.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p196. When something is claimed to be new, do not be too hasty to think it is just the past slightly improved—it may be a great opportunity for you to do significant things.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>There is so much “new” technology these days. Blockchains, NFTs, machine learning. Every time I go to look at it I come away thinking it’s completely stupid. Part of me thinks “there’s no way SO MANY PEOPLE could be wrong about this stuff.” But the other part says “yeah, but you have significantly better fundamentals than most people in your field, and it’s your understanding of the fundamentals that makes this sound stupid.”</p>
<p>I genuinely can’t tell if this is confirmation bias or not. Someone help please.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p210. It must be your friends, in some sense, who make you famous by quoting and citing you,p and it pays, so I claim, to be helpful to others as they try to do their work. They may in time give you credit for the work, which is better than trying to claim it yourself.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I’ve definitely noticed this in my life. The more I try to call out people for their good ideas that I’ve learned from, the more often they call me back out in kind. There’s this interesting “infinite mirror” sort of effect, where we boost one another’s signal, by virtue of having our signal boosted in the first place. It’s something I’ve been staying cognizant of since the first time I read the book. Be generous with credit! It’s cheap, and pays significant dividends.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p218. Moral: when you know something cannot be done, also remember the essential reason why, so later, when the circumstances have changed, you will not say, “It can’t be done.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p><a href="/blog/brilliance/">This has bitten me before.</a> I would like to not be bitten by it again. Context: Hamming had published a book proving he knew everything he needed to know in order to invent the Fast Fourier Transform. But it’s called the FFT instead of the Hamming transform. That must have <em>stung.</em></p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p239. That is why I am suspicious, to this day, of getting too many solutions and not doing enough very careful thinking about what you have seen. Volume output seems to me to be a poor substitute for acquiring an intimate feeling for the situation being simulated.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Sounds like most programmers I know. I’m genuinely amazed at how often people say they check stackoverflow.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p241. An active mind can contribute to a simulation even when you are dealing with experts in a field where you are a strict amateur.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This one confirms my biases that smart outsiders can contribute to fields they don’t understand. Especially software people, whose key skill I see as being <em>understanding complicated things.</em> Outsiders see it as “pressing keys on the keyboard” or something, and are quick to dismiss my skills. <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/research/publication/composing-contracts-an-adventure-in-financial-engineering/">But Simon Peyton Jones can do it sucessfully</a>, so there is hope.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p245. An extreme case I had to solve because it was important to the Laboratories, and that meant, at least to me, I had to get the solution, no matter what excuses I gave myself it could not be done. There are always answers of some sort for important problems if you are determined to get them. They may not be perfect, but in desperation something is better than nothing—provided it is reliable!</p>
</blockquote>
<p>WHAT AN ATTITUDE. I have never had a job I cared that much about. Sometimes when my friends ask interesting software questions, but never at a job. This would be an extremely powerful skill to learn how to harness: <em>getting an answer at any cost.</em></p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p246. Why should anyone believe the simulation is relevant?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>A good question to ask myself when I try to convince people that I could automate things for them. Why should they believe me? I believe me, but how can I communicate that?</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p252. When I was occasionally asked to do some ecological simulation I quietly asked for the mathematically expressed rules for every possible interaction, for example given the amount of rain what growth of the trees would occur, what exactly were the constants, and also where I could get some real live data to compare some test runs. They soon got the idea and went elsewhere to get someone more willing to run very questionable simulations which would give the results they wanted and could use for their propaganda.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I’d never thought about sham science in this light before. Yeah, I know like the cigarette companies fund research on smoking. But I’d never considered honest academics might be fooling themselves into selecting colleagues based on whom they won’t be challenged by.</p>
<p>This is a harrowing thought. It’s likely not just scientists — I suspect everyone is guilty of this to some extent. Do I do this? Probably? But how do I find the instances, and how do I correct for it?</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p255. I made it easy to do the bookkeeping and the mechanics of the computer, but I refused to relieve them of the thinking part.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>cf. stackoverflow and Github Copilot, which take the thinking part of programming away. Jesus Christ that stuff scares me. Why are people <em>so</em> willing to give up thinking? How prevalent is this outside of software? A lot of the world makes a lot more sense under the lens that most people are actively trying to avoid thinking…</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p263. Does the pilot feel only the Fourier real frequencies, or maybe they also feel the decaying Laplace complex frequencies (or should we use wavelets?) Do different pilots feel the same kinds of things? We need to know more than we apparently now do about this important design criterion.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I’D NEVER CONSIDERED THIS. I have this bad habit of thinking the map is the territory, and would just find a big-O of the function and then trim it off. But yeah, obviously there would be physical effects corresponding to our mathematical models.</p>
<p>And yes, humans can “feel” acceleration and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jerk_%28physics%29">jerk</a>.<a href="#fn2" class="footnote-ref" id="fnref2" role="doc-noteref"><sup>2</sup></a> But do we have a perception of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fourth,_fifth,_and_sixth_derivatives_of_position#Fourth_derivative_(snap/jounce)">snap</a>? And if so, can we differentiate it from <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fourth,_fifth,_and_sixth_derivatives_of_position#Fifth_derivative_(crackle/flounce)">crackle</a>? I’m <em>very</em> curious about the answer here.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p266. My real contribution was: (1) the realization that we could simulate what had happened, which is now routine in all accidents but was novel then, and (2) the recognition that there was a convergent direction field so the initial conditions need not be known accurately.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Context: Hamming is discussing garbage-in-garbage-out as a concept, and saying it doesn’t hold. If you have attractors in your system, you will converge upon a good answer, even if your starting position is awful. A piece of conventional engineering that a) I believed, b) is clearly wrong, and c) I knew enough to determine for myself that it was clearly wrong, but didn’t.</p>
<p>I wonder how I can avoid mistakes like this in the future. What other false beliefs am I holding?</p>
<p>Jesus this book is a great exercise in humility.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p269. Good minds are still needed in spite of all the computing tools we have developed. But the best mind will be the one who gets the principle into the design methods taught so it will be automatically available for lesser minds!</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Popularizing excellent ideas is more important than having excellent ideas. This is a good thing. I’m reasonably adept at popularizing things. <strong>I should intentionally train this skill, because pedagogy is much easier to improve than raw brain power.</strong></p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p270. I had always claimed if the problem was important and properly posed, then I could get some kind of a solution. Therefore, I must find the solution; I had no escape if I were to hold onto my pride.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Just today I came to the conclusion that something was likely impossible in a system that I had made. It’s not the most important problem to solve, but I definitely would have tried harder if my life or job depended on it. And what’s worse is that it <em>feels</em> like there’s a solution; I just don’t know how to formulate the problem in order to find it.</p>
<p>This is definitely a tactic that can be deliberately invoked. I would like to get in the habit of making progress on hard problems. Again: get my ego involved. Precommit to making progress.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p277. Once I had decided to stay at the Labs and realized my poverty in the knowledge of practical electronics, I bought a couple of Heathkits and assembled them just for the experience.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Hamming realized he was lacking a skill, so he deliberately went out of his way to practice, even though he didn’t need the skill. But he figured it would be helpful in his understanding of the world. So he sunk his time and money into it!</p>
<p>I definitely do this with programming, and claim it’s why I’m as good as I am. Lots of silly exercises, just to develop new skills. But what about areas outside of programming?</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p278. Beware of the power of wishful thinking on your part—you would like it to be true, so you assume it is true!</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Fuck. I do this all the time.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p292. What you learn from others you can use to follow; what you learn for yourself you can use to lead.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>No real commentary on this one, but it feels true and it’s a good proverb.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p293. Kaiser is a very smart person, but his education had restricted his view of the use of what he had learned. The better we inculcate the basic idea with the pictures drawn by the professor, the more we prevent the student from later extending the ideas to completely new areas not thought of by the professor (and put into the graphic display).</p>
</blockquote>
<p>My reading of this is that maybe we shouldn’t necessarily try to aid understanding by way of metaphor. Because metaphors are inevitably leaky, and this will damage the student’s ability to understand at the periphery of the metaphor’s boundary. Maybe all those visual math primers I want to make are a bad idea.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p294. The students must master abstract pattern recognition if they are to progress and use mathematics later in their careers.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Another good quote for a book.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p302. It soon became evident to me that one of the reasons no theorem was false was that Hilbert “knew” the Euclidean theorems were “correct,” and he had picked his added postulates so this would be true. But then I soon realized Euclid had been in the same position; Euclid knew the “truth” of the Pythagorean theorem, and many other theorems, and had to find a system of postulates which would let him get the results he knew in advance. Euclid did not lay down postulates and make deductions as it is commonly taught; he felt his way back from “known” results to the postulates he needed!</p>
</blockquote>
<p>If you had asked me whether this was the case, I’d have said no. But if you asked me how I verify a new piece of mathematics, I’d tell you that I test it by throwing extreme examples at it that should simplify to some already well-known result. After all, there are lots of crazy new ideas, and if they don’t agree with existing results, either they’re wrong or you’ve got much bigger problems.</p>
<p>But if this is true — if all mathematicians are projecting earlier truths outwards, then the unreasonable effectiveness of mathematics is once again in question. Why in hell do all of these crazy abstractions correspond with reality?</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p304. The above example about Cauchy’s theorem illustrates my attitude that mathematics shall do what I want it to do.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This also feels true; formalizing ideas has a strong component of bending reality to your will. I don’t do a lot of math, but in programming, my god does this happen. I can invent abstractions on the spot that somehow make the computer do what I want it to — but exactly how I generate those is a mystery. It feels like lots of practice and analysis has gone into it, but none of that seems to matter when I go try and teach this stuff.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p313. Clearly Planck was led to crate the theory because the approximating curve fit so well, and had the proper form. I reasoned, therefore, if I were to help anyone do a similar thing, I had better represent things in terms of functions they believed would be proper for their field rather than in the standard polynomials.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In other words: “present ideas in the language of the audience, even if it isn’t the language most natural for the formulation of the ideas.” I run afoul of this all the time; it’s fine to do your thinking in a specialized language, but translating it to others goes much more smoothly if you can just teach some ideas, rather than a whole new language.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p315. There are smells you cannot smell, wavelengths of light you cannot see, sounds you cannot hear, all based on the limits of your sense organs, so why do you object to the observation that given the wiring of the brain you have, there can be thoughts you cannot think?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I hate this. Because he’s absolutely right, and it fills me with an existential dread. What if all the ideas we <em>really</em> need are wrapped up in the vacuum of unthinkable thoughts?</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p316. [The uncertainty principle] is a theorem in Fourier transformations—any linear theory must have a corresponding uncertainty principle, but among physicists it is still widely regarded as a physical effect from nature rather than a mathematical effect of the model.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Highlighted out of <em>extreme interest.</em> Is this true? If so, how many other physical “laws” fall out merely as byproducts of theorems?</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p317. Von Neumann… proved there were no hidden variables… but the proof was found to be fallacious, new proofs found, and in their turn found to be fallacious—the current situation being a toss-up as to what you want to believe.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>More extreme interest. Note to myself to go investigate this. My understanding is that <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bell%27s_theorem">Bell proved there are no hidden variables</a>, but that was in the 70s and this book was published in the 90s, and there is no way that Hamming hadn’t seen Bell’s work. I notice I am confused. I should remedy that.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p320. I have put the word “understand” in quotes because I do not even pretend to know what I mean by it. We all know what we mean by “understand” until we try to say explicitly just what it means—and then it sort of fades away!</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I disagree. Understanding is the ability to form a model of some phenomenon, and make predictions that correlate with the future of the phenomenon itself. I could draw a nice commutative diagram here, but the idea being that the following square should commute: <code>predict . understand = observe . wait</code>.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p321. Progress is making us face ourselves in many ways, and computers are very central in this process. Not only do they ask us questions never asked before, but they also give us new ways of answering them.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I get in trouble often by putting my foot in my mouth on things like this. I’ll ask people leading questions about introducing formal systems into their jobs, usually trying to automate away the boring things. People interpret this as me wanting to automate away the whole job, and, instead, seem to entirely shut their minds off to the possibility that their jobs <em>could</em> be automated away.</p>
<p>The relevance: a world we designed to solve all the problems that are solved today, but designed in a context of immense computation, would be a very different world than the one we currently live in. People are extremely eager to see byproducts of the current system as essential characteristics of the class of solutions. For example, democracy is a (bad) solution to a distrusted consensus-solving problem where agents can’t trust one another. It’s just trying to implement <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paxos_(computer_science)">Paxos</a>! But people get worried about representation, or avoiding corruption, or whatever when you try to suggest anything that isn’t democracy. But I digress.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p325. Creativity seems, among other things, to be “usefully” putting together things which were not perceived to be related before, and it may be the initial psychological distance between the things which counts most.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is a useful definition, and an actionable one too. I’m a firm believer in knowing about lots of things, and hoping that one of them will come in handy. It seems to work.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p327. This stage, moreover, requires your emotional involvement, your commitment to finding a solution, since without a deep emotional involvement you are not likely to find a really fundamental, novel solution.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Reiterating a point above.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p327. When stuck I often ask myself “If I had a solution, what would it look like?” This tends to sharpen up the approach, and may reveal new ways of looking at the problem you had subconsciously ignored but now see should not be excluded. What must the solution involve? Are there conservation laws which must apply? Is there some symmetry? How does each assumption enter into the solution, and is each one really necessary? Have you recognized all the relevant factors?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>More good thought patterns from a smart person that I’d like to emulate. I don’t have a dedicated process for finding solutions; I just sorta set my mind loose on the problem and hope something shakes out. After writing <a href="https://algebradriven.design/">Algebra-Driven Design</a> I’ve started approaching software design with the underlying question of “what laws should hold here?” and it’s been <em>enormously</em> fruitful. Throwing a few more “obvious things to check before diving in” sounds like it would pay dividends.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p329. When you learn something new, think of other applications of it, ones which have not arisen in your past but which might in your future.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Another thought pattern.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p330. We are, in a very real sense, the sum total of our habits, and nothing more; hence by changing our habits, once we understand which ones we should change and in what directions, and understand our limitations in changing ourselves, thence are on the path along which we want to go.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Inspiring. We are the sum of our habits. Habits are hard to change, and they change less often than we’d like to believe, but we all have examples of changing our habits.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p340. The second point I want to make is that many of you, in your turn, will become experts, and I am hoping to modify in you the worst aspects of the know-it-all expert. About all I can do is to beg you to watch and see for yourself how often the above descriptions occur in your career, and hope thereby you will not be the drag on progress the expert so often is.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Context: experts often get in the way, and science needs to wait for them to die before it can proceed. I see this in a lot of my programming communities. I don’t want to be a drag like this when I get to the top of my career.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p341. In my own case, I vowed when I rose to near the top that I would be careful, and as a result I have refused to take part in any decision processes involving current choices of computers. I will give my opinion when asked, but I do not want to be the kind of drag on the next generation I had to put up with from the past generation. Modesty? No, pride!</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The last three words here really change the tone. It’s not that Hamming didn’t think he was right, it’s that he was convinced that history wouldn’t agree with him. This is another good lens on our actions — how will history look back on us? If we can predict that, we might as well act only favorably along this metric.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p342. What you did to become successful is likely to be counterproductive when applied at a later date.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>You see this in a lot of well-meaning advice. When preparing for my first interview as a software <em>engineer</em>, my dad suggested that I fiddle with any nut and bolt that might be around. I was perplexed — what did that have to do with software? Why would there be a nut and bolt around? My dad very patiently explained that they wanted to see if I was predisposed to getting my hands on problems!</p>
<p>Clearly very good advice for engineering that is hands-on, but software is decidedly not! More generally, new techniques work well because the zeitgeist doesn’t know about them yet. But once they enter the collective experience, they get improved upon, and your old tool now solves the problem worse than the new ones!</p>
<p>The inventor of something knows the least about it!</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p345. “Why do you believe the test equipment is as reliable as what is being tested?” The answer I got convinced me he had not really thought about it.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I found a bug in <code>QuickCheck</code> last week, and <em>lots</em> of bugs in <code>quickspec</code> when writing Algebra-Driven Design. Those cost me a few hours, because your first thought is never that it’s the machinery that’s broken. And when the compiler has a bug, dear god. There goes your week.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p346. I had long ago argued at Bell Telephone Laboratories that we should form a life testing debarment whose job is to prepare for the testing of the next device which is going to be invented, and not just test after the need arises. I got nowhere, though I made a few, fairly weak suggestions about how to start. There was not time in the area of life testing to do basic research—they were under too much pressure to get the needed results tomorrow.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is just genuinely a really good idea. At Takt, in an uncharacteristically-smart move, the CEO spun up a task force of a few people to do R&amp;D into what our new platform would look like. They came up with a ton of excellent ideas in two weeks, and likely were too successful, because the CEO immediately shut down the team and said “this is what our new platform will look like!”</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p346. There is never time to do the job right, but there is always time to fix it later.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The motto of every software engineering job ever.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p351. Much of the reliability of the engineering guesses was transferred t the sum, and the uncertainty of the salesman’ guesses was ignored. That is not uncommon in big organizations. Careful estimates are combined with wild guesses, and the reliability of the whole is taken to be the reliability of the engineering part. You may justly ask why bother with making the accurate engineering estimates when they are to be combined with other inaccurate guesses, but that is widespread practice in many fields!</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I’ve seen this in my career, but never acknowledged it as such. I don’t know what to do about it, but it’s something to keep an eye on.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p352. Morgenstern points out that at one point DuPont Chemical held about 23% of the General Motors stock. How do you suppose this appeared when the gross national product (GNP) figure was computed? Of course it was counted twice!</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Of course it was. Makes you wonder just how inflated today’s economy is by false metrics. Does this apply to personal valuations as well?</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p353. Their reluctance to change the definitions of the economic indicators is based on the claim that a change, as indicated in the above paragraph, makes the past non-comparable to the present—better to have an irrelevant indicator than an inconsistent one, so they claim.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>So they claim. But having an irrelevant indicator is worse than having nothing; it will inspire you to do the wrong thing! How do we improve mathematical literacy?</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p354. Institutions, like people, tend to move only when forced to.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Pithy and sweet.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p354. Most economists are simply unwilling to discuss the basic inaccuracy of the economic data they use, and hence I have little faith in them as scientists. But who said economic science is a science? Only the economists!</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I was thinking about this today on the way home. I’m currently <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/40538538-goliath">reading a book on monopolies</a>, and am finding my perspective towards economics radically shifting. I’ve historically been very pro-libertarian/Chicago-school, basic it on little more than “it feels like the math checks out.” Of course, the author has his biases against these economics, but it’s a well-argued position I’d never heard before. Changing your mind is a confusing state of affairs!</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p356. Averages are meaningful for homogeneous groups (homogeneous with respect to the actions that may later be taken), but for diverse groups averages are often meaningless. As earlier remarked, the average adult has one breast and one testicle.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Underlined because I love the example.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p361. I also realized that under (2) and (3) one of my functions in the research departments was not so much to solve the existing problems as to develop the methods for solving problems, to expand the range of what could be done, and to educate others in what I had found so they could continue, extend, and improve my earlier efforts.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Develop new methods and educate people on it, rather than directly solving the problems. This completely aligns with my career trajectory, though not necessarily accidentally, since I was reading this book when I <a href="https://sandymaguire.me/blog/reaching-climbing/">quit my job.</a></p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p363. During my last two undergraduate college years when I was at the University of Chicago, the rule was that at the end you had to pass a single exam based on nine courses in your major field, and another exam based on six in your minor field, and these were mainly what mattered, not what grades you got along the way. I for the first time, came to understand what the systems approach to education means. While taking any one course, it was not a matter of passing it, pleasing the professor, or anything like that; it was learning it so that at a later date, maybe two years later, I would still know the things which should be in the course.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>OH MAN WHAT A GREAT WAY TO TEACH THINGS. WHY DON’T WE DO THIS? I came away from university knowing how to program, how to cut corners, and how to cram for tests. They tried to teach me a lot of things, but I was better at cutting corners and cramming than they at teaching.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p365. All the proposed reformations of the standard calculus course that I have examined, and there are many, never begin by asking, “What is the total mathematical education, and what therefore, should be in the calculus course?” They merely try to include computers, or some such idea, without examining the system of total mathematical education which the course should be a apart of.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>p365. Few people who set out to reform any system try first to find out the total system problem, but rather attack the first symptom they see. And, of course, what emerges is whatever it is, and is not what is needed.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>These two hit home. I fall victim to this when I look at existing systems, and say “why is this particular thing missing?” rather than “if I were to design this from scratch, what would my principles be?” Damn. Hamming making me think.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p367. I have stressed the importance of what currently is believed to be the fundamentals of various fields, and have deliberately neglected the current details, which will probably have a short lifetime.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I’m working on the second edition of a book right now, and this is a point I’m trying to focus on more directly. There are lots of techniques I could recommend today, but they’re only going to age the book. Fundamentals don’t go out of style, which techniques absolutely do.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p369. A second reason the systems engineer’s design is never completed is the solution offered to the original problem usually produces both deeper insight and dissatisfactions in the engineers themselves.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is a common characteristic that I notice in people I really like. Maybe it’s <em>the</em> common characteristic that I like. The absolute best programmers I know will build something a few times, because each time they get a solution they realize that what they’ve built is a solution to the wrong problem.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p377. In mathematics, and in computer science, a similar effect of initial selection happens. In the earlier stages of mathematics up through the calculus, as well as in computer science, grades are closely related to the ability to carry out a lot of details with high reliability. But later, especially in mathematics, the qualities needed to succeed change and it becomes more proving theorems, patterns of reasoning, and the ability to conjecture new results, new theorems, and new definitions which matter. Still later it is the ability to see the whole of a field as a whole, and not as a lot of fragments. But the grading process has earlier, to a great extent, removed many of those you might want, and indeed are needed at the later stage!</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Another point suggesting that outsiders can do far more good work than insiders, since they haven’t been accidentally selected out.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p388. It is hard work, applied for long years, which leads to the creative act, and it is rarely just handed to you without any serious effort on your part. Yes, sometimes it just happens, and then it is pure luck. It seems to me to be folly for you to depend solely on luck for the outcome of this one life you have to lead.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Inspiring words. My takeaway here is that it’s more important to be systematically building cool things than it is to be recognized for those things. Getting the right idea at the right time is likely largely a function of luck, but by building a habit of building cool things, you’re optimizing your chances of the luck striking.</p>
<p>Helpful for me, because I feel like I keep having great ideas that people just don’t seem to “get” — and it’s nice to have this as an excuse for why it’s OK.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p389. “Why are you not working on and thinking about the important problems in your area?”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I don’t know what are the important problems in software. P=NP I guess, and maybe then “what the hell do we do with all of this compute?” I’d like a better answer than “burn it mining shitty crypto” and “make graphics that look as good as real life.” What stupid applications of the most powerful tool the known universe has ever seen. Yeah, gun to my head, I’d say wise and effective use of software are the important problems of the future. So why am I not working on them? It’s not entirely clear where to start!</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p390. While playing chess Shannon would often advance his queen boldly into the fray and say, “I ain’t scared of nothing.” I learned to repeat it to myself when stuck, and at times it has enabled me to go on to a success. I deliberately copied a part of the style of a great scientist.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I ain’t scare of nothing! It has a good ring to it. Here’s me deliberately copying a great scientist in deliberately copying a great scientist.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p390. The courage to continue is essential, since great research often has long periods with no success and many discouragements.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This perfectly sums of Algebra-Driven Design. That book took 7x longer than my first one, a good chunk of which was spent rewriting it because I kept writing the wrong book! Endlessly frustrating and discouraging, but well-worth having pushed though.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p391. Not that you should merely work on random things, but on small things which seem to you to have the possibility of future growth.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Another good metric. You don’t have to work on big problems; small ones that seem promising are OK too.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p391. Thus what you consider to be good working conditions may not be good for you! There are many illustrations of this point. For example, working with one’s door closed lets you get more work done per year than if you had an open door, but I have observed repeatedly that later those with the closed doors, while working just as hard as others, seem to work on slightly the wrong problems, while those who have let their door stay open get less work done but tend to work on the right problems.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>My instinct is often to put in headphones and focus. I like getting work done in the short term. But I’ve been finding this to be more and more true. For example, I go to a weekly “open hack” where there are a lot of beginners talking about basic things! But once a week or so, someone says something that is absolutely brilliant, and it’s the sort of thing that could only have come from a beginner!</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p392. When stuck, often inverting the problem and realizing the new formulations is better represents a significant step forward. I am not asserting all blockages can be so rearranged, but I am asserting that many more than you might at first suspect can be so changed from a more or less routine response to a great one.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>More good strategies for solving problems. This sounds similar to “if I had a solution, what would it look like?”</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p393. I changed the problem from just getting answers to the realization I was demonstrating clearly for the first time the superiority of digital computers over the current analog computers, thus making a significant contribution to the science behind the activity of computing answers.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>It’s not enough just to do it well. It also needs to be done with style and flare, to help inspire lesser minds into seeing what the future could hold.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p394. At the urging of others, for some years I set aside Friday afternoons for “great thoughts.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Another reminder to myself. But I’ve already put it on my calendar, so there.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p396. Do you want to be a reformer of the trivia of your old organization or a creator of the new organization? Pick your choice, but be clear which path you are going down.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Fuck, this one hits me too. I spend so much time fighting in the Haskell world about stupid shit that nobody cares about. Is it “correct” that we remove <code>(/=)</code> from <code>Eq</code>? Absolutely. Does it matter? Not in the least. Dumb trivia.</p>
<p>A mantra I picked up from Sebastian Marshall is “don’t argue with peasants.” If there’s an idiot who’s wrong on the internet, don’t waste your energy trying to change their mind. Best case, you convince them, the world doesn’t change in any noticeable way, and you’ve wasted your energy.</p>
<p>“Don’t be a reformer of trivia” is another helpful mantra I could do well to pick up.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p397. I strongly suggest you adopt the habit of privately critiquing all presentations you attend and also asking the opinions of others. Try to find those parts which you think are effective and which also can be adapted to your style.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Erin often says I’m a good writer. I think she’s just being kind. All it feels like I’m doing is stealing the best bits of writing from my favorite authors and essayists. But maybe that’s all that being a good writer consists of?</p>
<p>However, I don’t apply this to other forms of media. I don’t analyze how stand-up comedians tell jokes, nor how good engineers give technical talks.</p>
<hr />
<blockquote>
<p>p397. Along the way you will generally have superiors who are less able than you are, so do not complain, since how else could it be if you are going to end up at the top and they are not?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Makes sense. If you’re going to end up at the top, you’re going to have to climb, and go past a bunch of idiots in the process. Which, counterintuitively, suggests it’s actually a <em>good</em> thing if your boss is an idiot — because it means you haven’t yet risen to your height.</p>
<hr />
<p>My first thought was to end the essay here, because I made it through all of the quotes. But I stole this format from an author I like, and in the spirit of analyzing good presentations, I’m going to take a moment and go see how he ends essays of this form.</p>
<p>Turns out he just ends them, without an afterward. But that feels like the wrong play, so instead I’ll tell you to go <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Art-Doing-Science-Engineering-Learning/dp/1732265178/ref=sr_1_1">buy a copy of The Art of Doing Science and Engineering</a>. It’s an excellent book, and you won’t be disappointed.</p>
<section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr />
<ol>
<li id="fn1" role="doc-endnote"><p>I realize this was against the letter of the law, but not the <em>spirit.</em><a href="#fnref1" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li>
<li id="fn2" role="doc-endnote"><p>It’s when you come to a complete stop in a car, and you get momentarily thrown forward. That’s a spike in the third derivative of your position.<a href="#fnref2" class="footnote-back" role="doc-backlink">↩︎</a></p></li>
</ol>
</section>
      ]]></content:encoded>
  </item>
  <item>
      <title>TV is the Mind Melter</title>
      <author>sandy@sandymaguire.me (Sandy Maguire)</author>
      <link>http://sandymaguire.me/blog/mind-melter/index.html</link>
      <guid>http://sandymaguire.me/blog/mind-melter/index.html</guid>
      <pubDate>2021-09-06T14:53:00Z</pubDate>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[
        <p>For the last three years, I’ve been tracking <em>everything</em> I do on the computer. This is done for me automatically via a lovely program called <a href="https://arbtt.nomeata.de/#what">arbtt</a>, which records every window you have open, every minute. By watching which window is focused, and how the titles of the windows change, it’s possible to get an extremely good sense of what activity I was engaged in, at any moment in time, since 2018.</p>
<p>The original impetus here was to track exactly how much work I was doing per project. Having this sort of information around is wildly valuable in determining where your time is going, and whether it’s being put to good use.</p>
<p>Yesterday, on a whim, I decided to run a query against my last year of computer time: how much YouTube did I watch? I was expecting some embarrassingly large number, like maybe three or four days worth. To my intense dismay, the actual number was <em>30 days.</em> The horror! Holy shit — I was off by an <em>order of magnitude!</em></p>
<p>Not only is this a dreadful review on how good my internal sense of spending time is, it’s also a disgusting amount that I wasted last year. To put 30 days into perspective, that’s equivalent to 90 work days, or 9 biweekly pay-checks. At my current rates, this six-figures worth of productive time down the drain. Compared to my burn rates, that’s equivalent to about half a decade of expenses! Forget skipping the avocado toast, or sticking to a weekly budget, the amount of time I spent watching TV completely dwarves every other cost in my life — by at least an order of magnitude.</p>
<p>What the fuck.</p>
<p>Time spent watching TV isn’t even time I enjoyed. The majority of things I watch are <em>other people playing video games</em> that are 10-20 years old. Sure, there are the occasional math lecture in there, but actual <em>valuable</em> watching time is a tiny fraction of my total TV time. This is time that I’m not learning anything, that I’m not developing any skills, and that I’m not feeling better because of.</p>
<p>It wouldn’t even be fair to call this “wasted” time. This is simply <em>killed</em> time.</p>
<p>So, what to do about this shitty state of affairs? Life is too short to be killed like this — to be killed at all, really. The part of me that does long-term planning (“system 2”) — as opposed to system 1, which is good at following habits and seeking short-term gratification — recognizes that TV is a horrible addiction, one that should be purged with extreme prejudice.</p>
<p>The trick to breaking (psychological) addictions, is to convince system 1 that it doesn’t actually desire these things after all. But system 1 doesn’t speak the language of well-reasoned arguments! It only understands vague intuitions, wishy-washy feelings, and Pavlovian conditioning. So the strategy here is to communicate my system 2 distaste for TV via intuitions, feelings, and conditioning.</p>
<p>Last year, I read <a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B01EVMK0H0/">Allen Carr’s Easy Way to Stop Smoking</a>. It’s an excellent book, and I am not, nor have I ever been a smoker. My interesting in reading it was exactly for building intuitions on how to break addictions, and the book comes chocked full of lots of psychological tricks. The tricks are exactly what we’re looking for — convincing means of influencing how system 1 feels. They’re almost embarrassingly simple in how obvious they are — but yet they allegedly work anyway. And it’s not hard to see why.</p>
<p>For example, Carr never calls tobacco “tobacco.” Instead, he exclusively refers to it as “the evil weed.” He makes frequent analogies to how it chokes out the natural, beautiful garden of your body. He reminds you just how disgusting smoking is, by focusing on how much you hated it when you started, how it makes you feel powerless to addiction, to all of the cold nights you’ve spent alone, outside, exposed to the elements. How it makes food taste bland, and makes your teeth yellow, and he points out just how disgusting the stuff is that you produce from your smoker coughs.</p>
<p>It’s important to consider all of these downsides simultaneously. Individually, the cost of any one downside might be less than the pleasure one receives from smoking, and system 1 is liable to make the equivalent of the following comparisons:</p>
<ul>
<li>cost(feeling powerless) &lt; reward(smoking)</li>
<li>cost(cold nights) &lt; reward(smoking)</li>
<li>cost(bland food) &lt; reward(smoking)</li>
<li>cost(yellow teeth) &lt; reward(smoking)</li>
<li>cost(coughing) &lt; reward(smoking)</li>
</ul>
<p>System 1 looks at these comparisons and thinks to itself, “hey, since each comparison comes out in favor of smoking, I should continue smoking.” But, it’s important to remember that system 1 is really bad at math, and it’s cheated during its bookkeeping here. It’s incorrectly counted the reward from smoking multiple times, which is like if were to say “well the cost of this new laptop is $1 than my paycheck for the week, and the cost of these new speakers are $20 less than my paycheck for the week, so I can afford to buy both.”</p>
<p>The real comparison that system 1 should be doing is actually:</p>
<ul>
<li>cost(feeling powerless) + cost(cold nights) + cost(bland food) + cost(yellow teeth) + cost(coughing) ~ reward(smoking)</li>
</ul>
<p>If each of those earlier (incorrect) comparisons were barely in favor of smoking, then there is no way that the honest version will come out in the same direction. None of these downsides is unknown to the smoker, but often system 1 accidentally fudges the numbers, and the addiction seems much more persuasive than it actually is.</p>
<p>Of course, none of these techniques are smoking-specific. They are easily co-opted into convincing system 1 of anything. Like how much it hates watching TV for example — or should I say, how much it hates watching the <em>mind melter. While I sorta like having something to fill (read: kill) time when I’m feeling low energy, I recognize that my lethargic states aren’t </em>cured* by the mind melter —- in the long term, they’re caused by it!</p>
<p>Furthermore, watching old video games is a pathetic and ineffective way to attempt to recapture how I felt when I was young. It’s infantilizing — and no better than those adult children who cheer for every new (and inevitably terrible) Star Wars film.</p>
<p>Often I get pulled towards melting my mind when my wrists hurt — preventing me from working on valuable things. But my wrists are hurt by having bad ergonomics, usually when I’m slouching to melt my mind!</p>
<p>I think of the disgust I feel every time someone tells me about the latest and greatest show on Netflix that they binge-watched over the weekend. They inevitably sound like stupid programs (who <em>could possibly</em> care about tiger kings and octopus teachers???), and I silently judge these people. But I’m no better if I’m instead binge watching some guy play Mario for hours at a time. In fact, I might be worse, since Mario isn’t even novel.</p>
<p>What the fuck is wrong with me? How in hell did I waste a month of my waking life last year doing this shit?</p>
<p>All of these things sound harsh, and they probably are, but I can feel it working already. But system 1 also responds well to imagery. Here’s what should come to mind whenever I think about melting my mind:</p>
<center>
<img src="/images/tv.gif">
</center>
<p>This is an image from the fantastic music video for Blockhead’s song <em>The Music Scene.</em> I won’t link you to it for obvious reasons; you know how to find it if you want to.</p>
<p>So, I feel like I’ve successfully convinced system 1 that the mind melter sucks. But, as <a href="https://mindingourway.com/productivity-through-self-loyalty/">Nate Soares</a> says:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>A problem isn’t solved until it’s solved automatically, without need for attention or willpower.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In the spirit of this, I’ve also installed <a href="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/stayfocusd/laankejkbhbdhmipfmgcngdelahlfoji?hl=en">StayFocusd</a> to my browser, and have marked the mind melter as a forbidden site. By default it gives me 10 minutes a day across all of my forbidden sites, which is helpful in that it will let me scan videos for information, but isn’t enough time to get hooked. Furthermore, I’ve used <a href="/blog/reclaim-your-attention/">uBlock</a> to delete all of the recommendations on the mind melting site, so that even if I slip up, it will be hard to <a href="https://mindingourway.com/failing-with-abandon/">fail with abandon</a>.</p>
<p>Even though I’m pretty sure my new mindset around mind melting will be sufficient, it’s nice to have a backup plan.</p>
<p>Finally, it’s nice to have something to substitute this behavior with. If I’m still feeling burned out and low energy, I’m going to just pick up my book instead. It will scratch a similar itch, but at least I’ll have to exert some attention, and create some room for daydreaming.</p>
      ]]></content:encoded>
  </item>
</channel>
</rss>
